<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: projects | drseergio. finito.]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/projects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-29T21:59:43+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing qeytaks: trivial photo tag editor]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-qeytaks-trivial-photo-tag-editor/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T10:38:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-qeytaks-trivial-photo-tag-editor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous post I have introduced <strong>photofs</strong> &ndash; a tool I have written for myself that universally solves my photo management problems.</p>

<p>With <strong>photofs</strong> I can easily locate photos by albums, tags, dates. But how would I add the tags in the first place? I use Adobe Lightroom and absolutely love it! I don&rsquo;t use it to manage photos. Lightroom is a gateway from the camera to my collection. Once I&rsquo;m done processing photos Lightroom kisses them goodbye.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>What if I mislabel something? For example, I typically use album names with the following template: &ldquo;YYYY.MM.DD &ndash; &lt;album name or event name or something descriptive&gt;&rdquo;. I could easily make a typo or choose a wrong year. Or what if I want to add an additional tag to some of the pictures?</p>

<p>Originally, with <strong>photofs</strong> I would need to somehow magically figure out what are the true paths to the files I want to alter. Then I would need to use a tool such as exiv2 to make the changes.</p>

<p>I immediately realized that this is not a work-able solution. So instead, I&rsquo;ve added support of modifying files through the virtual view. In other words, if you edit a file that you have opened through <strong>photofs</strong> the changes will be transparently channeled to the original images.</p>

<p>Furthermore, I had to implement a hack to let exiv2 library work (exiv2 is the only widely supported and maintained library for altering image photo data I could find). When a file is sufficiently large, exiv2 library wants to write its changes to a temporary file in the same folder as original and then rename it. Obviously, this cannot &ldquo;just work&rdquo; in a virtual folder so I had to implement a mechanism that tricks exiv2 into believing that a temporary file has been opened. In reality, <strong>photofs</strong> opens a file in memory and lets exiv2 write into it. When exiv2 tries to do a rename operation <strong>photofs</strong> dumps the file in memory to the original image.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/qeytaks.png" width="400"> Back to our problem. So now we have a possibility to not only view photos in some virtual arrangements but also modify photos. In other words, it&rsquo;s now possible to locate all photos with tag &ldquo;travel&rdquo;, modify them (say, by adding tag &ldquo;fun&rdquo;) and expect the original photos to have a new tag &ldquo;fun&rdquo;!</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s great but what to use for editing tags? I&rsquo;ve mentioned in my last post that I am using XMP label tag as a marker for album names. I&rsquo;m almost certain nobody else is using it in the same way. I also don&rsquo;t want to use overly complex and ugly programs for changing just 2 things.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to write my own simple tool &ndash; meet <strong>qeytaks</strong>. Essentially, <strong>qeytaks</strong> is a pane of pictures, 2 fields and a &ldquo;Save&rdquo; button. With <strong>qeytaks</strong> I can add new tags and alter existing ones. <strong>qeytaks</strong> indicates when a tag is not common to all selected pictures with a pre-pended star (*) similarly to how Lightroom does it. I&rsquo;ve added integration with KDE by creating a contextual right-click menu entry. When I am browsing photos through <strong>photofs</strong> view I can simply select some photos and open them in <strong>qeytaks</strong> for editing tags.</p>

<p><strong>qeytaks</strong> is written in Python and uses PyQt4 to create the UI. I&rsquo;ve never worked with Qt before so I had to learn its concepts first. I&rsquo;ve got an impression that the Qt concepts (at least the UI part, Qt library includes a lot more than just UI) are very similar to other desktop UI frameworks (e.g. events handling).</p>

<p>Again, I solved a personal problem and I am very happy with the result. I&rsquo;ve spent total of about a day working on it and learned a couple of things along the way. You can clone the github repository if you&rsquo;re interested. I&rsquo;ve documented the requirements and instructions in the README file.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing photofs: FUSE file-system for browsing photos]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-photofs-fuse-file-system-for-browsing-photos/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T09:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-photofs-fuse-file-system-for-browsing-photos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With yeach passing year the number of photos in my collection is growing. The trend only hockey-sticked once I got my own camera. I&rsquo;ve tried various programs to organize and browse photos. I recall using or trying ACDSee, digiKam, Adobe Bridge, IrfanView, F-Spot, Shotwell and possibly others that I don&rsquo;t recall.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The thing I don&rsquo;t like about these tools is that they build an index of photos in their proprietary formats. Usually, it takes a while to generate the index and the programs will obviously work only on the computer where the program is installed.</p>

<p>The other problem is performance. With 15 000+ photos many of the photo organizers simply don&rsquo;t work well: become slow, crash and hang. Applying changes to many photos at a time is especially thorny.</p>

<p>Finally, I like to have photos to be neatly organized not only in the indexes inside of the photo management programs but also on disk. It&rsquo;s quite possible that I will switch to another program in future (or to another operating system altogether). Having a manageable folder structure is crucial. Otherwise, I need to go through re-organizing all photos every time this happens.</p>

<p>My first attempt of solving this issue was to write a simple desktop program that imports photographs and sorts them nicely on disk in a well-defined folder structure. This is convenient because I can browse the collection on any computer running any operating system.</p>

<p>However, I quickly realized that there is not a single definitive way of arrangement that would be useful in all occasions. Sometimes, I want to look at pictures taken in certain years. Most of the time I really care about albums. I also like the idea of tags. It&rsquo;s obvious that a static arrangement won&rsquo;t answer all useful queries.</p>

<p>Couple of weeks ago an idea struck me. Why not to create a virtual file-system that would take meta-data information from the photos (dates, tags, album names, camera settings) and create a hierarchy that would be transparent to the operating system. You would simply browse a folder with your favorite file manager or photo viewer and photos would be neatly organized in various ways. Furthermore, if you store photos on a NAS you could run the virtual file-system on it and the view would be exposed to all clients of the NAS.</p>

<p>And that&rsquo;s exactly what I have done in <strong>photofs</strong> project. Simply put, <strong>photofs</strong> takes a path to folder with your photos and creates a set of virtual views of the photos at a specified mount point. Internally, it creates an index similarly to how the other photo management tools do it. The advantage, however, is that in the end you seemingly get a regular folder with files in it. You can browse photos using a terminal, any file-manager or even expose the view via network to other computers.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a screen-shot of Dolphin file-manager showing 4 panels with the modes that <strong>photofs</strong> supports:</p>

<p><img src="/images/photofs.png"></p>

<p>Upon first invocation <strong>photofs</strong> generates an index and creates 4 virtual sub-folders at the mount point. Each of the sub-folders, in turn, exposes a single view of your photos:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>albums</strong> lists all albums in your photo collection as folders. To determine what album a photo belongs to <strong>photofs</strong> reads XMP label. This is what I have decided to use as an album marker. Each album sub-folder has a <em>selects</em> sub-folder. That is intended for separating really good pictures from the rest. A picture is deemed as <em>select</em> if it has IPTC keyword &ldquo;select&rdquo; (IPTC is what almost all photo management tools use for storing tags in photos).</li>
<li><strong>date</strong> creates a hierarchy of date information: YYYY/MM/DD. At each level you can view all photos for that period by going into <em>all</em> sub-folder (e.g. all photos for year 2012).</li>
<li><strong>camera</strong> creates a hierarchy based on camera settings that had been used when a photo has been taken. For example, you could find photos taken at 2.8F on a 55mm using Canon camera with this view.</li>
<li><strong>tags</strong> exposes a tag view. You can choose photos based on intersection of tags. For example, to find photos that have tags &ldquo;milan&rdquo; and &ldquo;racing&rdquo; you would go into sub-folder milan/racing.</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>photofs</strong> is written in Python and runs on Linux only because it relies on inotify kernel feature of Linux to know when certain files have changed without doing full traversals of the photo folder. The core of <strong>photofs</strong> is built on top of FUSE &ndash; a Linux kernel feature that allows user-land programs to act as file-systems. I believe <strong>photofs</strong> could be adapted to OSX by using an alternative to inotify (not sure what that is in OSX). The index is stored as a sqlite database.</p>

<p>You can argue that what I have done with <strong>photofs</strong> is yet another program that runs on one O/S only and also has a proprietary index. However, I believe it&rsquo;s different because <strong>photofs</strong> exposes a file-system. At home, I expose a virtual <strong>photofs</strong> view via NFS and Samba to other computers and it works well enough.</p>

<p> <strong>photofs</strong> is not perfect. First and foremost, it solves a problem I personally had. If you believe you can make use of it or even improve it &ndash; go ahead and clone the github repository. Requirements and installations steps are documented in the README file.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
