<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reflections | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/reflections/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-07T16:46:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee experiment 2 months later]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-07T16:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I had initially <a href="/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/">experimented with drinking enormous amounts of coffee per day</a> I abandoned coffee completely. The side effects were too bothersome. I slept too long, crashed too hard during the day and felt pronounced headaches unless I&rsquo;ve drank a cup a day. Two extremes got me thinking &ndash; could I perhaps find an optimal middle ground?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13697133974/"><img class="left" src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/13697133974_4624909376_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" title="&lsquo;My favorite cup&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<p>With that in mind I&rsquo;ve attempted a moderate approach. I have consumed at most 2 cups (or equivalent amount of caffeine-containing substances) a day. One cup almost immediately upon waking up and another one after lunch or in the afternoon. The morning coffee ritual became essential as I made a push away from evenings into early mornings. I have realized that with a full time job doing anything extra curricular in the evenings is difficult as there is little energy left. Now, I mostly use evenings for being with my wife, reading and relaxing. Of course, there are occasional activities so exciting that even low energy can&rsquo;t stop me. Mornings is a completely different story. When fully rested I feel energized to work on difficult yet fun stuff. For example, every morning for the past 2 months (with rare exceptions) I&rsquo;ve been studying German. I cannot imagine to study a foreign language in the evening. I feel tired, unmotivated and learning feels like a drag. In the long term I hope to gradually break into a habit of waking up at something like 5am while going to bed at 9pm or so. I&rsquo;ll leave the evenings for wine and cigars.</p>

<p>Do I notice any side effects? Not really. I don&rsquo;t feel too bad on days that I miss coffee. I don&rsquo;t get insomnia after drinking an espresso shot at 7pm. I don&rsquo;t feel particularly cranky. I don&rsquo;t crash at 3-5pm.</p>

<p>Moderate amount of caffeine gives a subtle but noticeable mental boost. I am pleased with the results. I will likely continue the practice indefinitely. Perhaps I am stating the obvious with this experiment. Most people consume 1-2 cups a day anyway. In everyday life I take a lot of things for granted. But sometimes, I like to take out a piece of my life-style and change it to see if the change makes a difference. More often than not I arrive at trite conclusions and revert to the old ways. In rare cases I change my habits significantly. But in either case I come out with a better understanding of myself.</p>

<p>I should insert a disclaimer that I don&rsquo;t pay much for coffee. It is free at work and at home I use an inexpensive capsule-based coffee maker. Occasionally (i.e. once every two months or so) I go for an extravagant drink at a coffee shop. If I had to pay for every coffee it costs in coffee shops I would abandon the practice very quickly. Sorry, but very few people realize just how expensive their coffee habit really is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee is not my friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T17:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About 2 years ago I completely gave up on caffeine. I&rsquo;ve stopped drinking coffee, most kinds of tea and caffeinated beverages such as diet coke. Giving up was not that difficult. I&rsquo;ve never been a die hard fan of coffee though I savor a well prepared black tea and an occasional coke.</p>

<p>A negative consequence of completely giving up on caffeine is that even the tiniest bit disrupts a good night sleep. Feel like a having a cold bursting diet coke at 4pm? Face insomnia the following night! Same for tea or anything containing caffeine. I had adapted by finding valid substitutes. A cold highly carbonated water is as satisfying as a diet coke. Nothing trumps black tea but rooibos tea is enjoyable in its own way.</p>

<p>Back in the day I don&rsquo;t remember if giving up on caffeine had made any life improvements. A couple of months ago I started having difficulties falling asleep quickly so I decided to carry out a couple of experiments. One of the experiments was to consume caffeine in large quantities (5+ caffeinated beverages per day). The experiment handsomely reminded me of all the benefits of not being addicted to the mainstream drug of caffeine!</p>

<p>But I digress, there are observable benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>My heart rate has dropped. Increased heart rate was one of the factors that kept me up at night.</p></li>
<li><p>I feel energized and enthusiastic. I feel excited doing things that normally get postponed. Even mundane things get done with a spark of creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>I can sustain energized and enthusiastic performance for about 4-6 hours. This has to be supported by regular caffeine consumption.</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s a pronounced sharp productivity and energy crash in the evening at about 5-6pm. While the crash prevents me from doing creative work in the evening it allows me to disconnect quickly and relax. More on that later.</p></li>
<li><p>Surprisingly, I fall asleep much quicker! While I could have previously lied in bed for 15-45+ minutes now I lose grip on reality in a couple of minutes at most and less than a minute at best.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve continued with the experiment for about 4 weeks. I am abandoning it because I find the habit completely incompatible with my lifestyle and the following negative effects:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Headaches. I get headaches if I don&rsquo;t consume enough. When I wake up I have about one hour to drink a cup of coffee before strong headaches kick in. In the evenings the headaches are partially responsible for impairing any remaining productivity. I tried going without coffee one Saturday. I could not focus on anything. I vaguely recognize this feeling from the days when I had been a regular coffee drinker. It never occurred to me that coffee could be causing this.</p></li>
<li><p>Aggression, anxiety, impatience. In the moments when I don&rsquo;t get a caffeine &ldquo;fix&rdquo; I feel increased level of negative emotions and impatience. Even the most innocent behaviors drive me mad. Curiously, before I gave up coffee 2 years ago I never attributed caffeine as a source of anxiousness and irritability.</p></li>
<li><p>Longer sleep. Although I fall asleep much quicker now and subjectively have great sleep the objective quality must have deteriorated because I need more time to get to a rested state. Sleep is important for me (and should be for everyone in his right mind). I know I&rsquo;m rested when I wake up before the alarm clock goes off. With caffeine I need 2 extra hours to get there.</p></li>
<li><p>Productivity crash. I&rsquo;ve listed it as a benefit but it&rsquo;s also a curse. I find it next to impossible to work on anything in the evening. Evening time is sacred to me. It&rsquo;s when I can do something creative or engage in a side project or read or think. Frankly, I can do nothing now. I can&rsquo;t even read articles and news from my curated RSS feed. I can only imagine watching mindless TV but luckily I don&rsquo;t have one.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m currently on track to reduce caffeine consumption to no more than 1 cup of coffee a day plus a couple of cups of tea. I&rsquo;m doing this to keep immunity from caffeine&rsquo;s effect on sleep while reaping some of the benefits like reduced heart rate. I don&rsquo;t know how useful such a compromise will be but in a couple of weeks I should have a realistic understanding.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t see a reason to ever come back to consuming as much caffeine as I did in the past and during the last 4 weeks. I imagine caffeine is one bad habit that keeps a lot of unaware people in a bad loop. No wonder that few ever want to do anything exciting in the evening when the crash makes you feel so devastated and you think that&rsquo;s normal.</p>

<p>I suppose caffeine has its place. I imagine coffee as a kind of &ldquo;turbo boost&rdquo; button in a critical situation when every extra bit of creativity and energy is needed. This &ldquo;turbo boost&rdquo; comes with sizable payback and so should be used sparingly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dilbert cartoonist on goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T21:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have just finished reading Scott Adams' book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Fail-Almost-Everything-Still-ebook/dp/B00FHI0XK2">How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big: Kind of the Story of My Life</a>. In the book the cartoonist behind Dilbert comic shares his views on success in a witty and humorous way.</p>

<p>He talks about goals among other things. He finds goals to be inadequate for long-term personal success. Among the reasons is the perpetual feeling of failure. And what do you do after reaching a goal? Goals are not relevant for ongoing improvements, like staying fit and well rested. Instead, the author argues for the value of creating habits (or systems, as he calls them) to keep essential efforts going.</p>

<p>The idea struck a chord with me. <a href="/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/">As I&rsquo;ve written before</a> I had never found goals to be especially useful in life. Not only I can&rsquo;t find any motivation for reaching arbitrary targets I also don&rsquo;t understand what am I supposed to do when I reach them. Suppose I&rsquo;ve put a goal to lift a certain weight. Should I stop exercising once I can do it? Pushing goals further is not workable either. I can&rsquo;t increase my strength forever &ndash; there is a limit.</p>

<p>Forming habits has always worked for me. I had spent a considerable amount of willpower once to fall in love with exercising daily. Now I feel bad if I don&rsquo;t do it. I occasionally break out of the routine (e.g. when I travel for weeks at a time) but resuming is never a hassle. However, I find habits/systems to be out of place for things that are to be enjoyed sporadically. It is a lousy habit to go to the cinema every week because it won&rsquo;t be fun.</p>

<p>Also, the line between habits and goals is a fine one. A habit to meditate daily can be framed as a goal. I don&rsquo;t have a good enough grasp to put a clearly defined distinction. Goals are well defined targets with specific dates attached to them. Habits are a collection of embraced practices to continuously maintain and improve prioritized areas of life without excessively expending willpower. More generally, I can think of habits as processes that solve problems and dilemmas of life to get me closer to what I consider important.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve enjoyed the book. Although there&rsquo;s more circumstantial evidence than scientific proof I have discovered a couple of valuable ideas to evaluate and to experiment with. I suggest to read <a href="http://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2013/12/scott-adams-fail-at-everything/">Farnam Street Blog post about this book</a> for an expanded overview.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On goals and purpose]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-25T19:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Christmas and New Year&rsquo;s Eve evoke mass hysteria to reflect and to resolve to change unlike any other time of the year. People write down goals for themselves, think about their purpose in life. Planning and goal setting are praised important even outside of the festivities.</p>

<p>I believe it&rsquo;s mostly harmless but also pointless. I look back to the moment I first embraced the Western custom of goal setting and I don&rsquo;t have much to show for it. Most of the things I have written down for myself became either unimportant or neglected. Any remarkable moments and achievements have been unexpected, spontaneous or had very little to do with the planning.</p>

<p>For one, goals are thought to be an explicit expression of one&rsquo;s desires and life values. It follows that we are fully aware of what is truly important to us and that it&rsquo;s possible to translate our priorities into conscious plans. However, I personally find a significant disconnect between conscious thought and implicit life values. It&rsquo;s difficult to crystallize the  value &ldquo;compass&rdquo; in words. Plans that come out of a rational mind can be in conflict with  governing values.</p>

<p>I have a personal illustration. I have never put the relationship with my wife as a priority or in any of the goals. However, in moments of distress I have dropped everything to take care of her. None of the goals mattered in that instant. I realize now just how important she is for me. Consciously, I did not rank the relationship high in my list of priorities and goals. But subconsciously I knew what is going to rule my behavior, especially in times of difficulty.</p>

<p>Secondly, goals have costs. It is one thing to write goals down. It is another to accept sacrifices that might be required to make them happen. I&rsquo;ve heard complaints about lines of work that are not terribly exciting. Along the complaints came aspirations for entrepreneurship and exhilarating work at emerging start-ups. I confess that the thought is contagious. I entertained it myself. But then I realized that this change has a cost and that I highly value what I already have.</p>

<p>Taken together, these two factors are responsible for destroying many naive goal setting efforts. Symptoms may differ but at the core the problem is that goals simply don&rsquo;t truly matter to the person setting them. It won&rsquo;t help to break down a goal into smaller goals or to have regular progress reviews. It just doesn&rsquo;t work that way.</p>

<p>I often recall an episode when I was about 10 years old. Two of my friends were coached by their parents to think about their lives and set goals and do all sorts of ridiculous &ldquo;self development&rdquo; exercises. I haven&rsquo;t done any of that. Yet all of the things I appreciate this very day did not come out of any priority list.</p>

<p>I believe there is a place for planning but life is not one of them. I see goals useful when an issue is well understood. Setting goals to win a specific sports competition is a technical matter. On the other hand, setting a goal to enter a competition in the first place is an entirely different thing.</p>

<p>My resolution for this NY is to stop doing useless bullshit personal goal setting crap.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated news sources]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T22:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have added a couple of sites and online magazines to my subscription list. Check out the <a href="/news-sources">News sources</a> page for the full updated list:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://aeon.co/">Aeon magazine</a> &ndash; Aeon Magazine is an online magazine about nature, culture and ideas.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://aeon.co/film/">Aeon film</a> &ndash; Aeon Film screens contemporary and classic short documentaries, exploring the intersections between nature, culture and ideas.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://habrahabr.ru/">Habrahabr</a> &ndash; (Russian) an online tech-oriented community/aggregator. Most of the articles are written from scratch, rather than republished. I had to spend considerable amount of time unsubscribing from different channels to bring volume down to a manageable level. But apart from that inconvenince there is lots of interesting material that is not published anywhere else.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://digital-photography-school.com/">Digital Photography School</a> &ndash; regular tips and guides on digital photography. I like the amount of published material. Frequent enough to be intersting to follow but not as much to become overwhelming.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
