<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reflections | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/reflections/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-27T22:04:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I have quit an awesome job]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-16T19:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18863676532"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3716/18863676532_dd50531ca1_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>I woke up at five in the morning today and headed to the airport with my beloved wife to fly out to celebrate our wedding anniversary on one of the beautiful Greek islands. As I am typing this on my computer during the flight I do not yet fully comprehend that our vacation is not going to end like most vacations do: two weeks later at the office. That is because earlier in May I inked a decision to voluntarily resign from one of the best places to work in the world. Since I made the announcement I have been predominantly asked three questions:</p>

<ol>
<li>Why are you leaving?</li>
<li>What are you going to do next?</li>
<li>What are you going to do during your break?</li>
</ol>


<p>I would like to share what made me make such a difficult decision. Hopefully, this short reflection helps others in their search of meaning and happiness. Writing also helps me to make sense of my own life and turn ephemeral, and often confusing, thoughts into concrete insights.</p>

<p><strong>tldr;</strong> answers are as follows: to discover my true passion, I don&rsquo;t know for certain, nothing for a while and then prepare for whatever I choose next.</p>

<p>There was nothing rash or sudden in my actions. If anything, I thought about it beforehand obsessively for several years. The balance of scales was finally disturbed last year when I went on a four week motorcycle tour of Norway and Sweden. Time alone on the road did not give many opportunities to think as I was preoccupied with looking for the fun roads, food and places to stay. But reflections, insights and thoughts stormed their way into my mind in the aftermath, as I reached home. Despite the engine roar, the twists and various incidents I felt calm and free during my little adventure. I felt no worry. But upon returning to the daily work routine the contrast was so stark that my hands began to shake. Stress has quickly re-established its elevated residency which I had not ever noticed before the trip. The background stress is toxic to the body but it is difficult to detect, just like the frog can&rsquo;t notice increasingly hot water it&rsquo;s in until the poor creature boils to death.</p>

<p>It is then that it became obvious to me that I must change either my ways of living or my attitude if I want to exist harmoniously and happily. It something easier said in hindsight as there&rsquo;s rarely a clear unambiguous signal to act in our complex entangled lives. History does not exist while the events are still unfolding. Similarly, factors and reasons rarely come together as neatly as they seem in the retrospect. Furthermore, real decisions usually have a steep price to pay and require to give up something valuable in return. I value and cherish many things that my way of living has given me up to the pivotal moment. Few other have had such gifts from the lady fortune. I found it difficult to seek understanding and support as there are few people I know who wouldn&rsquo;t label me a self-entitled ungrateful and wasteful bastard.</p>

<p>Fear is the other force to hold back. Fear held me a prisoner for years. One expects fear to be pretty obvious though I found it anything but. I have some credentials to back up my stance. In the last couple of years I skydived AFF (which means I did the first jump solo, unlike being strapped to another skydiver in a tandem), rode down-hill mountain bike trails, rode a 200 horsepower motorbike around a race track and did some other feats considered scary and risky by (mostly incorrect) common sense. I know what the obvious fear feels like. The fear of change is different: it lies dormant like a crocodile that snaps its deadly claws upon the motion of potential prey. Only in the case of fear the prey is any kind of uncertainty and change. Human nature is soaked with the poison of fear and we don&rsquo;t realize it.</p>

<p>What was I in? By any objective measure I lived in a paradise: being part of one of the best companies in the world that has shaped humanity and will do so in the foreseeable decades. The compensation, perks, free food and amazing office facilities are nothing to complain about. Nor do humane bosses, tolerant atmosphere, intelligent colleagues, space for initiative and considerable freedom to choose what to work on. Yet something has been amiss from the head start: passion. From the moment I started I did not enjoy what I was doing. I struggled initially but over time I learned skills that made me adapt and grow tolerant. I even excelled by the prevailing performance standards. At times there were assignments that got me really excited but 80% of my work felt empty.</p>

<p>I have not spent the time lazily complaining about the circumstances. I used the opportunity to find meaning outside of profession. I tried out more hobbies than I have toes and fingers combined. I studied and worked on side projects and ideas. I devoured in an intimate relationship with my then-girlfriend wife. I traveled. I read ferociously. I went beyond the confines of my nature-given introversion to meet people and make friendships. I pursued spirituality. But there is only so much time in 24 hours. Dealing with work that does not excite saps you of energy and eventually shrinks the energy capacity. I had genuine opportunities at the company to change into a line of work that is closer to my interests but failed to seize them due to unfortunate combination of reasons. By now I have got very little energy left and I definitely couldn&rsquo;t pull two jobs at once which is somewhat a prerequisite for a successful transfer. I don&rsquo;t see how passion can be compensated. I feel that no amount of hobbies, relationships and interests can compensate an occupation that is out of line with one&rsquo;s values and passions.</p>

<p>Despite what the articles and books say discovering passion is not that obvious. The typical premise is to follow one&rsquo;s goals and values but if it was so simple there wouldn&rsquo;t be so many confused and lost souls. Personally, I find the discovery process the most difficult. I don&rsquo;t understand how anyone can know his values and passions without a serious deal of reflection work. I certainly don&rsquo;t believe that one can substitute the hard work with a half an hour exercise. Without trying out various things it&rsquo;s not possible to determine what one is really excited about. Discovering passion is a process of trial and error. Discovery is about exploring further what little we have experienced so far along with finding new turns. It is not unlike navigating a maze.</p>

<p>One serious obstacle to the process of self discovery is the denial of truth. While it&rsquo;s not possible to know what our passions are without trying we can seriously inhibit progress by refusing to pursue our callings. After graduating from university I chose to work outside of my field of interest. To be honest, I wasn&rsquo;t particularly sure what of the many specializations in my field I wanted to pursue either. But ever since I began to work I did not get closer to finding that out. Instead, I thought of hundreds of reasons why pursuing passion isn&rsquo;t worthwhile. With the right financial disincentives failure to ever return on the path of self actualization is almost guaranteed.</p>

<p>It is also puzzling to me why people living in a westernish modern world rarely ever consider taking a long break from work. We live in an era of unprecedented productivity and economic growth. Yet most of us sit chained to our desks for 8-14 hours a day as if we were coal miners of the bygone centuries. It is impossible to perform uninterrupted quality intellectual work for more than a few hours a day. Somehow we conveniently ignore the truth and let our minds rot while we make ourselves look busy and let the hours pass instead of perhaps lifting some weight to make our backs stronger or learning a new skill. Nobody benefits from the idle hours. It&rsquo;s the same with ridiculously short vacations. Two weeks of vacation cannot replenish an exhausted body and mind.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t wait to take a break for too long. If you&rsquo;re not feeling mostly passionate about what you do chances are you will eventually burn out. There&rsquo;s anxiety and depression around the corner and broken relationships and career prospects (who wants under-performers back?). Instead, plan ahead and do it gracefully: go out with a smile and respect, with friendships and good memories. I think I waited a tad too long but at least I did not experience a complete break down. I feel drained professionally but my inner drive is still alive and ready to kick in a high gear after some greasing.</p>

<p>With all of what I have that said, I don&rsquo;t regret the choice I had made years ago. If I had the opportunity to go back in time and make the choice again I would have picked the same option. I believe I made the right decision given the circumstances. I don&rsquo;t blame anyone for the final outcome. If anything, I&rsquo;m grateful to the company, to my bosses and to my colleagues. I strongly believe that the same job could be blissful and highly rewarding under the right mindset and circumstances. I believe life is not meant to be a perfect well rehearsed sequence of &ldquo;nexts&rdquo; and I have very few expectations about the future. Nobody but me has an obligation to make the most out of my life.</p>

<p>Quitting a great job and taking a long break is the most difficult decision I made in my life so far. There&rsquo;s so much I would like to change and to learn and to experience! It&rsquo;s time to recharge, instill new helpful habits and to prepare for whatever I choose as my next challenge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The problems I don't have]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/03/03/the-problems-i-dont-have/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-03T12:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/03/03/the-problems-i-dont-have</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The bookshelves and the Internet are filled with articles and books containing life-changing ideas. Between fiction, non-fiction, psychology, biographies and self-help literature lies a curriculum unfulfillable in thousands of life times. Many of the ideas have the potential to drastically improve one&rsquo;s life. But there is a world of difference between <em>just agreeing</em> and <em>truly internalizing</em> any one of those ideas. And there&rsquo;s even a wider gap between applying an idea in a safe limited environment versus applying it in a high stakes situation. The former is akin to a sandbox, shielding us from failure and limiting our losses in case of failure. The latter is enshrouded in fear and uncertainty because the potential losses are real, significant and palpable. Though only the latter lets us reap deep benefits and become better selves.</p>

<p>Not only is there a difference between knowing an idea and internalizing idea but there&rsquo;s often no real situation in one&rsquo;s life where that idea could be applied at a given moment. Life-changing ideas are somewhat like tools. To use a tool there must be something to apply it to, a subject. If I suddenly receive an advanced spectroscope I won&rsquo;t have a clue what to do with it. After looking up what a spectroscope is on Wikipedia I&rsquo;ll possibly try to use it to measure something, just to feel good about myself and that I am intelligent enough to figure out how to use it. I&rsquo;ll then put the spectroscope in a box never to be seen again. An astronomer, however, would be glad to have the same tool at his disposal. Unlike me, the astronomer has a real use for the spectroscope. My use of the spectroscope is superficial while the astronomer could use it for a real breakthrough.</p>

<p>It occurred to me recently that getting in trouble is very important for a good lived life. Getting in trouble is the first step of personal growth and improvement in any area. Without trouble there&rsquo;s no use for solutions. Tools are usually created to solve a problem, to get out of trouble. It&rsquo;s not often that a tool is created first and then a use is figured out for it. Literature and media creates an opposite impression. Trouble, problems, inefficiency are portrayed in a negative light. Solutions, ideas, new ways of thinking are then glorified. But in this transition an important aspect is forgotten. Without the trouble in the first place nobody would care about a solution. Two thousand years ago humans could not care less about climate change and improvements to our energy production methods. These improvements are important for our well-being but two thousand years ago there was nothing to apply these improvements to. There was simply no such trouble as environment pollution.</p>

<p>Best-selling manage-everything books similarly portray trouble in negative light and gladly present solutions. For instance, time management books present 1001 strategies on dealing with overburden and stress. But few of the works will take a pause to acknowledge the value of being overburdened in the first place. Being overburdened and stressed means that we have taken on lots of responsibilities. While the situation itself may be undesirable our past courage deserves respect and acknowledgment. If we lied around the house all day and did not do anything at all we would not have these problems! It&rsquo;s not the missing acknowledgment that personally bothers me but the resulting reversal of solutions and problems. I don&rsquo;t need time management advice until I take up too many responsibilities and assignments. When I try to apply all the little tips and strategies I don&rsquo;t need I waste my energy I could have used to actually do something. I also get a false feeling that I am a master of time management. But the reality is that I&rsquo;m no better at time management than I&rsquo;m at astronomy with the spectroscope I had previously been gifted.</p>

<p>My personal take away is to get in trouble more often. I have nothing against reading what the best minds have already figured out. In fact, knowing what exists out there helps when the reality finally confronts with insurmountable obstacles. But I am cautious not to foolishly get enthused about the problems I don&rsquo;t currently have.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee experiment 2 months later]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-07T16:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I had initially <a href="/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/">experimented with drinking enormous amounts of coffee per day</a> I abandoned coffee completely. The side effects were too bothersome. I slept too long, crashed too hard during the day and felt pronounced headaches unless I&rsquo;ve drank a cup a day. Two extremes got me thinking &ndash; could I perhaps find an optimal middle ground?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13697133974/"><img class="left" src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/13697133974_4624909376_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" title="&lsquo;My favorite cup&rsquo;" ></a></p>

<p>With that in mind I&rsquo;ve attempted a moderate approach. I have consumed at most 2 cups (or equivalent amount of caffeine-containing substances) a day. One cup almost immediately upon waking up and another one after lunch or in the afternoon. The morning coffee ritual became essential as I made a push away from evenings into early mornings. I have realized that with a full time job doing anything extra curricular in the evenings is difficult as there is little energy left. Now, I mostly use evenings for being with my wife, reading and relaxing. Of course, there are occasional activities so exciting that even low energy can&rsquo;t stop me. Mornings is a completely different story. When fully rested I feel energized to work on difficult yet fun stuff. For example, every morning for the past 2 months (with rare exceptions) I&rsquo;ve been studying German. I cannot imagine to study a foreign language in the evening. I feel tired, unmotivated and learning feels like a drag. In the long term I hope to gradually break into a habit of waking up at something like 5am while going to bed at 9pm or so. I&rsquo;ll leave the evenings for wine and cigars.</p>

<p>Do I notice any side effects? Not really. I don&rsquo;t feel too bad on days that I miss coffee. I don&rsquo;t get insomnia after drinking an espresso shot at 7pm. I don&rsquo;t feel particularly cranky. I don&rsquo;t crash at 3-5pm.</p>

<p>Moderate amount of caffeine gives a subtle but noticeable mental boost. I am pleased with the results. I will likely continue the practice indefinitely. Perhaps I am stating the obvious with this experiment. Most people consume 1-2 cups a day anyway. In everyday life I take a lot of things for granted. But sometimes, I like to take out a piece of my life-style and change it to see if the change makes a difference. More often than not I arrive at trite conclusions and revert to the old ways. In rare cases I change my habits significantly. But in either case I come out with a better understanding of myself.</p>

<p>I should insert a disclaimer that I don&rsquo;t pay much for coffee. It is free at work and at home I use an inexpensive capsule-based coffee maker. Occasionally (i.e. once every two months or so) I go for an extravagant drink at a coffee shop. If I had to pay for every coffee it costs in coffee shops I would abandon the practice very quickly. Sorry, but very few people realize just how expensive their coffee habit really is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee is not my friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T17:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About 2 years ago I completely gave up on caffeine. I&rsquo;ve stopped drinking coffee, most kinds of tea and caffeinated beverages such as diet coke. Giving up was not that difficult. I&rsquo;ve never been a die hard fan of coffee though I savor a well prepared black tea and an occasional coke.</p>

<p>A negative consequence of completely giving up on caffeine is that even the tiniest bit disrupts a good night sleep. Feel like a having a cold bursting diet coke at 4pm? Face insomnia the following night! Same for tea or anything containing caffeine. I had adapted by finding valid substitutes. A cold highly carbonated water is as satisfying as a diet coke. Nothing trumps black tea but rooibos tea is enjoyable in its own way.</p>

<p>Back in the day I don&rsquo;t remember if giving up on caffeine had made any life improvements. A couple of months ago I started having difficulties falling asleep quickly so I decided to carry out a couple of experiments. One of the experiments was to consume caffeine in large quantities (5+ caffeinated beverages per day). The experiment handsomely reminded me of all the benefits of not being addicted to the mainstream drug of caffeine!</p>

<p>But I digress, there are observable benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>My heart rate has dropped. Increased heart rate was one of the factors that kept me up at night.</p></li>
<li><p>I feel energized and enthusiastic. I feel excited doing things that normally get postponed. Even mundane things get done with a spark of creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>I can sustain energized and enthusiastic performance for about 4-6 hours. This has to be supported by regular caffeine consumption.</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s a pronounced sharp productivity and energy crash in the evening at about 5-6pm. While the crash prevents me from doing creative work in the evening it allows me to disconnect quickly and relax. More on that later.</p></li>
<li><p>Surprisingly, I fall asleep much quicker! While I could have previously lied in bed for 15-45+ minutes now I lose grip on reality in a couple of minutes at most and less than a minute at best.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve continued with the experiment for about 4 weeks. I am abandoning it because I find the habit completely incompatible with my lifestyle and the following negative effects:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Headaches. I get headaches if I don&rsquo;t consume enough. When I wake up I have about one hour to drink a cup of coffee before strong headaches kick in. In the evenings the headaches are partially responsible for impairing any remaining productivity. I tried going without coffee one Saturday. I could not focus on anything. I vaguely recognize this feeling from the days when I had been a regular coffee drinker. It never occurred to me that coffee could be causing this.</p></li>
<li><p>Aggression, anxiety, impatience. In the moments when I don&rsquo;t get a caffeine &ldquo;fix&rdquo; I feel increased level of negative emotions and impatience. Even the most innocent behaviors drive me mad. Curiously, before I gave up coffee 2 years ago I never attributed caffeine as a source of anxiousness and irritability.</p></li>
<li><p>Longer sleep. Although I fall asleep much quicker now and subjectively have great sleep the objective quality must have deteriorated because I need more time to get to a rested state. Sleep is important for me (and should be for everyone in his right mind). I know I&rsquo;m rested when I wake up before the alarm clock goes off. With caffeine I need 2 extra hours to get there.</p></li>
<li><p>Productivity crash. I&rsquo;ve listed it as a benefit but it&rsquo;s also a curse. I find it next to impossible to work on anything in the evening. Evening time is sacred to me. It&rsquo;s when I can do something creative or engage in a side project or read or think. Frankly, I can do nothing now. I can&rsquo;t even read articles and news from my curated RSS feed. I can only imagine watching mindless TV but luckily I don&rsquo;t have one.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m currently on track to reduce caffeine consumption to no more than 1 cup of coffee a day plus a couple of cups of tea. I&rsquo;m doing this to keep immunity from caffeine&rsquo;s effect on sleep while reaping some of the benefits like reduced heart rate. I don&rsquo;t know how useful such a compromise will be but in a couple of weeks I should have a realistic understanding.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t see a reason to ever come back to consuming as much caffeine as I did in the past and during the last 4 weeks. I imagine caffeine is one bad habit that keeps a lot of unaware people in a bad loop. No wonder that few ever want to do anything exciting in the evening when the crash makes you feel so devastated and you think that&rsquo;s normal.</p>

<p>I suppose caffeine has its place. I imagine coffee as a kind of &ldquo;turbo boost&rdquo; button in a critical situation when every extra bit of creativity and energy is needed. This &ldquo;turbo boost&rdquo; comes with sizable payback and so should be used sparingly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dilbert cartoonist on goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T21:38:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have just finished reading Scott Adams' book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Fail-Almost-Everything-Still-ebook/dp/B00FHI0XK2">How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big: Kind of the Story of My Life</a>. In the book the cartoonist behind Dilbert comic shares his views on success in a witty and humorous way.</p>

<p>He talks about goals among other things. He finds goals to be inadequate for long-term personal success. Among the reasons is the perpetual feeling of failure. And what do you do after reaching a goal? Goals are not relevant for ongoing improvements, like staying fit and well rested. Instead, the author argues for the value of creating habits (or systems, as he calls them) to keep essential efforts going.</p>

<p>The idea struck a chord with me. <a href="/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/">As I&rsquo;ve written before</a> I had never found goals to be especially useful in life. Not only I can&rsquo;t find any motivation for reaching arbitrary targets I also don&rsquo;t understand what am I supposed to do when I reach them. Suppose I&rsquo;ve put a goal to lift a certain weight. Should I stop exercising once I can do it? Pushing goals further is not workable either. I can&rsquo;t increase my strength forever &ndash; there is a limit.</p>

<p>Forming habits has always worked for me. I had spent a considerable amount of willpower once to fall in love with exercising daily. Now I feel bad if I don&rsquo;t do it. I occasionally break out of the routine (e.g. when I travel for weeks at a time) but resuming is never a hassle. However, I find habits/systems to be out of place for things that are to be enjoyed sporadically. It is a lousy habit to go to the cinema every week because it won&rsquo;t be fun.</p>

<p>Also, the line between habits and goals is a fine one. A habit to meditate daily can be framed as a goal. I don&rsquo;t have a good enough grasp to put a clearly defined distinction. Goals are well defined targets with specific dates attached to them. Habits are a collection of embraced practices to continuously maintain and improve prioritized areas of life without excessively expending willpower. More generally, I can think of habits as processes that solve problems and dilemmas of life to get me closer to what I consider important.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve enjoyed the book. Although there&rsquo;s more circumstantial evidence than scientific proof I have discovered a couple of valuable ideas to evaluate and to experiment with. I suggest to read <a href="http://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2013/12/scott-adams-fail-at-everything/">Farnam Street Blog post about this book</a> for an expanded overview.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
