<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: reflections | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/reflections/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-14T22:21:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated news sources]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T22:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have added a couple of sites and online magazines to my subscription list. Check out the <a href="/news-sources">News sources</a> page for the full updated list:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://aeon.co/">Aeon magazine</a> &ndash; Aeon Magazine is an online magazine about nature, culture and ideas.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://aeon.co/film/">Aeon film</a> &ndash; Aeon Film screens contemporary and classic short documentaries, exploring the intersections between nature, culture and ideas.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://habrahabr.ru/">Habrahabr</a> &ndash; (Russian) an online tech-oriented community/aggregator. Most of the articles are written from scratch, rather than republished. I had to spend considerable amount of time unsubscribing from different channels to bring volume down to a manageable level. But apart from that inconvenince there is lots of interesting material that is not published anywhere else.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://digital-photography-school.com/">Digital Photography School</a> &ndash; regular tips and guides on digital photography. I like the amount of published material. Frequent enough to be intersting to follow but not as much to become overwhelming.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Feeding brains]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/26/feeding-brains/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-26T23:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/26/feeding-brains</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Finding good sources of information is similar to finding a good diet &mdash; there is an overwhelming amount of stuff available (abundance of calories) but the utility (healthiness) of it is close to zero. Many news outlets and online media have incentives that are in conflict with providing thoughtful quality material. Media chases advertisements. In the race to achieve highest numbers of visits and ad impressions it shamelessly bombards us readers with juicy junk articles with loud headlines that shamelessly grab our attention. These articles give a quick gratification but in the long-term rob us of thoughtfulness.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t see an immediate solution that works for the whole society. However, that does not preclude me from avoiding the poison altogether. I intentionally avoid mainstream news. I don&rsquo;t get sucked into politics and my perception of the world is not skewed by the over representation of certain topics (such as airplane crashes). I don&rsquo;t blindly follow industry news either. There are lots of new tools, frameworks and gadgets coming out every day. It&rsquo;s impossible to learn everything so I prefer to focus on lasting ideas and skills. I can pick-up and learn ephemeral details whenever I have a specific task at hand.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t passively follow what is currently trending or popular. Instead, I actively seeks news through a curated list of blogs and news sources. Even with a curated list I had problems getting overwhelmed with too many items. A low signal to noise ratio takes a lot of effort to deal with.</p>

<p>From now on I will maintain an updated list of RSS feeds of blogs and websites that I am subscribed to on the <a href="/news-sources">News sources</a> page.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Doing it my way]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/25/doing-it-my-way/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-25T21:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/25/doing-it-my-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a habit of regularly reading books that are of pseudo spiritual and self help and personal growth nature. I did not follow their contents word for word but I believed I could glean useful solutions to life problems and new ways to think about reality. Recently, I came to a conclusion that I&rsquo;m not going to read such books anymore. No more productivity books. No more books on settings goals. No more books on personal growth.</p>

<p>At the core of my discontent is a realization that every person exists within a unique set of circumstances. The set of circumstances benefits from a matching set of solutions. Solutions could be anything from spiritual beliefs and value systems to productivity habits and strategies. Whenever a person observes himself succeeding in light of his actions he entrenches in conviction that his discoveries are universal.</p>

<p>I have a problem with this premise. Even in relatively similar environments every person is shaped by an intersection of local influences, actions, ideas, challenges and opportunities. I don&rsquo;t believe there are universal truths as to how to run distinctive lives. Trying to blindly follow someone else&rsquo;s beliefs is akin to dull imitation. In addition, the result is likely to be irrelevant and misplaced.</p>

<p>Most of the self help literature builds upon anecdotes &mdash; stories of highly successful people (I&rsquo;m talking about success in its widest meaning, anything between spiritual enlightenment and lucrative business empire). Authors conveniently escape talking about failures and millions of interrelated things that contribute to extraordinary outcomes. I don&rsquo;t believe it&rsquo;s possible to extract specific traits or behaviors that guarantee success. Some highly successful people are punctual. Others never gave shit about being organized yet are arguably in the same success &ldquo;league&rdquo;.</p>

<p>After all the hours spent on reading these books I&rsquo;ve embraced introspection as an alternative tool. Instead of looking outwards to find solutions I look into myself to understand what challenges I face, what is important, what brings happiness and joy. I also take a moment to appreciate what I already have.</p>

<p>See what I have done here? Exactly what the self help literature does. I&rsquo;ve imposed personal experience to provide seemingly helpful guidance. The problem is that this &ldquo;guidance&rdquo; builds upon my perception and a set of beliefs that are likely to be very different from yours. Maybe if I&rsquo;ve never read any of the self help books my stance would be different. Perhaps you should read all the self help books you can and come to the same conclusion independently.</p>

<p>If there&rsquo;s anything to take away then it&rsquo;s that it helps to be critical when reading other people&rsquo;s ideas.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The photo curse]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/27/the-photo-curse/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T19:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/27/the-photo-curse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am fascinated with photography. A picture inspires, tells a story, expresses an author&rsquo;s view, captures a fleeting moment, gives an aesthetic pleasure. But there&rsquo;s a way to kill inspiration and make this art forever painful for oneself.</p>

<p>Ever since I&rsquo;ve purchased my own digital camera 4 years ago I&rsquo;ve been both blessed and burdened by photography. I have even purposefully abstained from taking any pictures for at least a couple of lengthy periods. Recently I had breakthroughs that have completely changed my attitude and brought the fun back!</p>

<p>At the root of most of my photography problems was an internal conflict between two seemingly contradicting ideas: &ldquo;enjoy the moment&rdquo; or &ldquo;take a photograph&rdquo;. One part of me badly wanted to take the camera out and put it on a tripod to take a shot. The other part was thoroughly disgusted at the sight of tourists pushing each other just to take an unremarkable shot of themselves. This other part of me reminded me not to become a mindless photo zombie machine. It&rsquo;s a common sight to see anxious visitors snap a landmark and then almost immediately move on to something else. I have seen the culmination at the Louvre museum in Paris where dozens of people are trying to take a picture of Mona Lisa. It&rsquo;s ridiculous. Why go to places at all if you don&rsquo;t genuinely marvel at things? That&rsquo;s why I often prefer to stop and really &ldquo;taste&rdquo; a sight.</p>

<p>Getting a sense of satisfaction from a photograph goes a long way. Realistically, nobody cares about my photos. There are just too many great and amazing photographers out there. Without full-time dedication it is not <em>likely</em> that anyone will become a true artist. I don&rsquo;t aspire to become one. I do photographs as a hobby and I seek satisfaction from my work regardless of how many people will ever see my photographs. But even with a very limited audience presentation is important. Everyone occasionally makes amazing photographs but the problem is that those pictures get mixed with the rest and lose their charm. For example, after a journey I end-up with 3 truly amazing shots and 40 good shots (lets say out of 500 total). It&rsquo;s better to separate pictures in sets and present amazing shots individually.</p>

<p>Then there is the feeling of being overwhelmed with options. There are unlimited number of things you can do to a photograph, not even counting limitless possibilities of composition and exposure. You can retouch a portrait, merge multiple photos together, apply various post processing effects and adjustments. Not surprisingly, this sea of options caused me almost an infinite hesitation. Should make a black-and-white picture? Or duo-tone? Or use crazy colors?</p>

<p>The problem with too many options goes beyond software. Hardware. I own two cameras, three lenses and an assortment of accessories (such as tripods, filters, etc). Carrying too much stuff gave me (head)ache for two reasons: hard to decide what lens/setup to use right now and the practical inconvenience of lugging too much stuff around. That&rsquo;s why now I mostly use a mirrorless camera with a fixed lens. For every occasion I now think ahead of what kind of shots I am after. Limits are good for fueling creativity.</p>

<p>The advent of digital cameras meant that nobody was bound by the limit of 36 frames anymore. The down-side is the actual upside. Instead of having 36 or so pictures one can easily end-up with thousands. It is a chore to go through all these pictures. Even worse, without a usable storage scheme/structure it is virtually impossible to navigate through one&rsquo;s own photos. I went through 3 iterations before I arrived at a system that works reasonably well. I&rsquo;ll explain it in a separate post.</p>

<p>Finally, it is the time pressure that exacerbates everything I have mentioned above. Going to an event or a trip with other people means that others expect to see pictures. Of course it&rsquo;s possible to ignore them and not touch the pictures for more than a year. I&rsquo;ve done that so many times! Obviously, postponing means that the backlog of pictures will grow to thousands (if not tens of thousands) of pictures. At some point there is a mounting pressure to get over the past photos before touching anything recent. It&rsquo;s a down-spiral from here. Why take pictures if I have not touched any from the past year?</p>

<p>The breakthrough that has helped me overcome problems is simple. I&rsquo;ve asked myself what kind of pictures I am taking and why. Depending on the answer I plan accordingly. I keep two major categories in my mind: photos for reporting and photos for pleasure.</p>

<p>The reporting pictures ideally take little to none processing and are mostly for documenting journeys and moments. Rules of good composition still apply but I would not plan on doing black-on-white shots or time-consuming post-processing effects. I keep these photographs as simple as possible. This allows me to share pictures most people care about quickly.</p>

<p>The other kind of photos is for joyous purposes. That includes interesting shooting angles, time-lapses, stitched panoramas, HDR shots and all kinds of fancy processing in software.</p>

<p>The important part is to separate photos into these categories as soon as possible. Then there is no pressure to finish everything at once. I find that having a separate backlog for artistic photos motivating. I return to individual photos and spend time experimenting without pressure. I feel a lot more creative and liberated that way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why write at all]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/21/why-write-at-all/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-21T18:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/21/why-write-at-all</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of weeks ago I have deactivated my Facebook account. I&rsquo;ve been intending to do that for months. Finally, I&rsquo;ve left the service for good.</p>

<p>Looking all the way back to 2006 I don&rsquo;t have much to show for it. You can&rsquo;t call me an addict because I&rsquo;ve never been hooked as much as people around me. Nevertheless, whenever I had cared to open Facebook&rsquo;s trendy blue interface I have been bombarded with meaningless status updates and viral junk. Numerous pointless apps and games just intensified the noise.</p>

<p>The noise itself never bothered me that much. What really bothered me is the dismal quality of what users share. It&rsquo;s seems to be a common problem with all social media. Most users simply don&rsquo;t share anything worth anyone else&rsquo;s attention. Instead of sharing genuine experiences, reflecting on one&rsquo;s life or authoring insightful writing I&rsquo;ve seen boasting, junk videos, cynicism, meaningless quotes and cryptic posts. Combined, these make their authors feel special and invite pointless discussions.</p>

<p>Facebook always made me feel bad about myself or my life. Other people&rsquo;s experiences seem just so much more authentic and full of life. It&rsquo;s basically like trashy advertising that shows you happy folks cleaning toilets with a certain kind of solvent. But instead of random folks you see whoever you had added to your Facebook &ldquo;friends&rdquo; and instead of cleaning toilets you see them doing whatever is that they were doing.</p>

<p>There are ways to read the &ldquo;stream&rdquo; without feeling insecure and unsatisfied. But it&rsquo;s hard mental and spiritual work. Despite spending considerable time to embrace mindful and present living I find Facebook to be a tough opponent. Facebook pierces through peace like a full metal jacket bullet. It&rsquo;s better to let go and give it up altogether.</p>

<p>Generally, I like the premise of a social network like Facebook. In theory it could be great. Imagine having a close circle of people who exert an effort to distill and publish their thoughts. Imagine a circle of friends who take the time to break down their adventures and experiences into stories. I am in total awe when a person cares to think and write down her thoughts instead of just slapping a bunch of photos in my face. Even if a story is not very coherent or deep.</p>

<p>I understand why Facebook, or any social media for that matter, is like that. It&rsquo;s easier to write and share junk. It&rsquo;s our brains wired for infinite satisfaction. A collection of juicy and emotional posts trigger our long-forgotten instincts just like an unhealthy sugary/fatty meal does. Nobody voluntarily wants to spend time writing or reading long posts when a &ldquo;Wall&rdquo; is bursting with sugar-high gossip, funny and disgusting media. One must willingly overcome animal desires and instincts. Choose a high-value diet &ndash; provoking and challenging information sources.</p>

<p>Not to seem like a hypocrite but I can&rsquo;t say I&rsquo;ve shared much in a meaningful way myself. I have not shared much at all. I intend to change with this personal home page. It&rsquo;s far from being a first blog of mine &ndash; there were many before it. For me the hardest part in keeping a personal page is finding a meaningful reason to share. It&rsquo;s all to easy to make a blog nothing else but a collection of the same crappy posts you see in social networks. The reason I think it&rsquo;s different this time is I feel no rush. I enjoy reflecting and writing down thoughts. I truly don&rsquo;t care if there is no value in these musings. I truly enjoy doing it right now.</p>

<p>Hopefully, by some serendipitous encounter you will find this site and share either thoughts or values or hobbies with me. Although even less likely, I hope we meet and do something fun together!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
