<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-02T20:01:55+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The many faces of my consumerism addiction]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/08/02/the-many-faces-of-my-consumerism-addiction/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-02T19:57:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/08/02/the-many-faces-of-my-consumerism-addiction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just like junkies deny their addictions I denied mine for as long as I could. Perhaps I am predisposed to addictions as I notice just how quickly obsessions form in my mind from even the most remote sparks of excitement. Mainstream drugs &mdash; alcohol, nicotine, etc &mdash; have never caught my fancy but the more subtle hijackers haven&rsquo;t left my brain&rsquo;s reward system untouched. In this post I&rsquo;m going share my struggle against a deeply rooted consumerism addiction that I have only recently taken a hold of. Overcoming consumerism, along with personal growth in <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure/">other areas</a>, was high on my priority list entering <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/">an ongoing sabbatical</a>. And similarly to the recognized addictions I find getting oneself free of consumerism is a continuing challenge. I made a habit of writing personal checklists for repetitive tasks and also memos for tackling difficult situations. A couple of months ago I outlined concrete steps to take when I find myself again in the inevitable grip of the addiction. That memo is essentially the backbone of the post you are about to read.</p>

<p>What does &ldquo;consumerism&rdquo; actually mean? At the most basic level it is the insatiable preoccupation with acquiring shiny new things. Consumerism has many faces and forms &mdash; it is a true chameleon. It hides behind many facades and is called many names, such as &ldquo;gear acquisition syndrome&rdquo;, &ldquo;shopping&rdquo;, hobby&#8221;, &ldquo;upgradeitis&rdquo;, and, as paradoxical as it may seem, even &ldquo;minimalism&rdquo;. The big issue with consumerism is that most people, myself included, are typically unaware of their strong addiction. Very few admit that their burning desire to buy something is a symptom of an illness. Instead, the need is perceived as part of a hobby or as a strong belief that the purchase will significantly enhance something in one&rsquo;s life. In fact, I see now that some of the hobbies I had pursued were fueled almost entirely by an attraction to the complementary gear, such as camera lenses or bike upgrades.</p>

<p>&ldquo;So what?&rdquo; one may ask. Isn&rsquo;t that harmless behavior, or a part of someone&rsquo;s (lack of) character? I find the various forms of consumerism a dentrimental habit that saps one of energy and focus. It is not just the burden on personal finances. It disrupts life and detracts attention from meaningful but difficult undertakings and realities to a form of immediate gratification. Consumerism is so deeply established and widespread that it&rsquo;s almost impossible to discuss it with anyone. It&rsquo;s like something everybody sees but doesn&rsquo;t want to talk about or address. Based on personal observations I see consumerism forming due to following triggers:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Emotional fulfillment</em> &mdash; shiny new things soothe (albeit temporarily) pain in times of emotional discomfort, be that stress at work or unfulfilled ambitions. The common wisdom is that possessions don&rsquo;t bring long-term happiness. I naively believed that my purchases were purely rational and had nothing to do with the pursuit of happiness or emotional comfort. Yet I eagerly anticipated every courier delivery and experienced an intensive but a short-lived rush of joy upon receiving the object of desire. How ironic.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Escapism</em> &mdash; similarly, an urge to buy arises often when faced with difficult obstacles. Ambiguous long-term projects (e.g., at least few months long), fatigue from training, overload from too many priorities and an inability to change current negative circumstances are all examples of such obstacles. Consumerism diverts the attention from solving problems to thinking about the next best thing.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Daydreaming</em> &mdash; typically almost every purchase is accompanied by fantasies of improved life circumstances, exciting work opportunities, some kind of consistency and order (e.g. speakers in every room, Apple devices), amazing creativity, new ways of travel, better self-image or doubled productivity. A new minimalist wallet is so convenient it will immediately make my life focused and organized. A new camera lens will make me take ten times more pictures. New racing wheels will make me ten times faster. A computer upgrade will make me ten times more productive. It sounds ridiculous when put into words but images like that run through almost everyone&rsquo;s mind at one point or another.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The difficulty of addressing consumerism is its obsessive and impulsive nature. Once an impulse arises in the mind it is next to impossible to get rid of it. Once established, every second thought races to the idea of getting that one thing and the improved existence it brings along. It is the obsessive character of the consumerism that prevents productive existence, stifles creativity and detracts from the present moment. Typically, it all starts with an accidental glance at a product review, an ad or a random article. At times I initially found the thing even ridiculous or useless. But as the time went by the planted seed grew into a monster. Rational measures against consumerism are futile because the roots of the problem are emotional. No amount of budgeting or prohibition helps. There is always the &ldquo;one last purchase and then I&rsquo;m all set&rdquo; argument, as if the purchase completes some kind of a perfect inner world or a survival toolkit. Naturally, the state of equilibrium is brittle and doesn&rsquo;t last very long &mdash; there are accessories to add and new &ldquo;minimalist&rdquo; gear to replace the old stuff with. I have mentioned &ldquo;minimalism&rdquo; many times in the context of consumerism. I don&rsquo;t have anything against the ideology of getting by with as few things as possible. At the same time I see that the noble pursuit often turns into an infinite buying spree. Something is fundamentally wrong when the ambition of minimalism is realized through even more acquisitions.</p>

<p>It is difficult to overcome any addiction, be that smoking or something as seemingly benign as consumerism. Even when I finally admitted to myself that I have an issue I couldn&rsquo;t quit the habit. The process took <em>years</em> and the recovery is still in progress. Deep down I know that I can fall into the trap anytime again if I&rsquo;m not careful. As I already mentioned, rational measures are ineffective. I couldn&rsquo;t fully address the problem without solving underlying emotional problems. For me that meant a sabbatical and a complete change of circumstances. Once the major problems were taken care of I could watch myself more closely and establish a set of checks to recognize early symptoms and avoid forming an obsession. It is important to recognize the emotional state associated with consumerism to resist it. In my memo have outlined the following steps:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Recognize the feeling</em> &mdash; it is an unmistakable rush, with elevated heart rate and total obsession with the purchase. It often feels like the purchase is the last one ever as if I&rsquo;ll be completely set for the future (for who knows what!). It feels like I&rsquo;m incomplete, incompetent, weak without the new thing. Once recognized, following the impulse is a clear weakness and an inability to resist.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Recognize unhealthy minimalism</em> &mdash; there&rsquo;s nothing wrong striving for fewer possessions and simpler living but most of the time for me it means more purchases. Once the one or few small items are sold I dream of something better, &ldquo;more minimal&rdquo;, to replace them with. It is like a purge before the next big wave of purchases.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Postpone purchase for later</em> &mdash; the impulses are unavoidable. What is avoidable is acting on them. That very moment it feels like the new thing is ABSOLUTELY necessary, it makes life simpler, better BUT it&rsquo;s WRONG. It is next to impossible to completely disavow the purchase but scheduling it for future will ensure that the purchase is emotionally cool and not a perverted way of compensating for personal inadequacies.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Emotional purchases as rewards</em> &mdash; some purchases are completely emotional and I know that there&rsquo;s no practical reason for them. That moment I feel like I still want it, like a kind of ornament or jewelery. Then, postpone such purchases as rewards for significant accomplishments. Something, that is far in the future and difficult (completing Iron Man, for example, or completing a difficult project at work).</p></li>
<li><p><em>Eliminate immediate triggers</em> &mdash; whenever the impulse arises it is necessary to avoid any reminders of the new shiny thing. Don&rsquo;t read web articles, reviews, forum posts, auctions or ads. Just accept that you&rsquo;ll get the thing later either as a reward or just simply later. There will be opportunities and sales, especially one year later. You&rsquo;re not losing it and nobody is taking it away so you can relax and stop reading.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>In conclusion I think that completely abstaining from any kind of purchase is not healthy either. Certain purchases improve well being and enable opportunities (although honestly very slightly and very seldom). When the mind is not infected with consumerism a purchase is not viewed as desirable but as necessary. When a purchase is needed there&rsquo;s no rush to buy it. It feels I&rsquo;d rather postpone the purchase for as long as necessary or even find a way to do without the new thing. I am happy to report that during the last 6 months I have avoided potential traps and shed more things than I acquired. May further purchases be emotionally cool and the mind clear!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Farewell, BMW F800GS Adventure!]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-23T19:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28495010395"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8479/28495010395_0fe544ede9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Yes, my beloved motorbike is gone to another owner. This leaves me with zero motorized vehicles. At the outset of 2016 I have decided to part ways with a BMW F800GS Adventure I had purchased brand new about two years ago. With a little help from my matchmaking the beamer and the new owner successfully found each other and left the garage not to be seen again. I&rsquo;ll keep fond memories of the wonderful spaceship-like machine that enabled <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/">an epic and life-changing 8000Km tour of Northern and Central Europe</a> and left positive emotions. I don&rsquo;t intend to completely quit riding bikes but I have no intentions to own another motorbike in foreseeable future.</p>

<p>The sale came as an indirect consequence of a <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/">sabbatical I have taken last year</a>. I had plenty of time to reflect on my ways of living and to reassess whether the things I did brought me joy and contributed to my well-being. In fact, the revelation that I don&rsquo;t actually enjoy motorcycles that much came rushing to me, along with other thoughts, as I was laboriously <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/">approaching snow covered peaks</a>. That very moment I became very honest with myself. How many other hobbies and directions was I pursuing that actually left me disengaged? What kept me blind in the face of growing dissatisfaction and emptiness? The inquiry has set me on a path to slash and eliminate everything from my life that&rsquo;s not essential. The many hobbies I had were the first obvious target.</p>

<p>How did I stumble into the world of motorbiking? I was fascinated with bikes and being always told that bikes are dangerous and forbidden by everyone around me set the desire in stone. Plus, the ubiquitous images of fancy bikes and ride reports don&rsquo;t help an impressionable mind running with wild fantasies. I feel these contagious fantasies are often at the root of many misguided pursuits and a heavy weapon in marketing&rsquo;s arsenal. The desire to ride bikes for me came as a desire to become the images I have seen. It was a desire to become something else. And in there lies the problem. It is not the desire to be something or someone but the actual joy of doing that drives positive pursuits. When an activity brings true joy it shouldn&rsquo;t matter what kind of image it invokes. Many non-bikers don&rsquo;t know about &ldquo;waving&rdquo; &ndash; a subtle gesture every motorbiker does when seeing another biker in the opposite lane. The custom immediately makes bikers, especially newcomers, feel part of a club. Seeing other bikers off-the-bike I regularly caught myself thinking that I can&rsquo;t wave and, hence, demonstrate to everyone around that I&rsquo;m also a biker. It almost felt I&rsquo;d like to wear some kind of badge that would make everyone realize I also belong to the club. And the same thought ran through my mind when I was doing one thing but seeing others do something else. Like hiking but seeing mountainbikers. Or touring and seeing road bikers blaze by.</p>

<p>But during the same pivotal mountaineering tour, maybe for the first time in my life, I felt I couldn&rsquo;t care less about other activities I wasn&rsquo;t doing then. It didn&rsquo;t matter anymore if I&rsquo;m perceived &ldquo;correctly&rdquo;. I cared only for what was directly in front of me. And I truly enjoyed the activity for itself. Not for the gear or the popular images of famous climbers or explorers. I think that a dichtonomy for &ldquo;being&rdquo; versus &ldquo;doing&rdquo; fits in nicely. &ldquo;Being&rdquo; is like striving to become something: a motorbiker, a badass climber or an iron-strong athlete. &ldquo;Doing&rdquo;, on the other hand, concerns itself only with the activity itself: riding, climbing or training. &ldquo;Being&rdquo; sets us on an infinite and empty chase for secondary attributes, like possessions, never deeply satisfying. Many an activity in &ldquo;being&rdquo;-mode consists of little but internal complaints and racing thoughts towards the next step or level, whatever that might be. &ldquo;Doing&rdquo;, however, focuses on the activity and nothing else. &ldquo;Being&rdquo; makes one worry if he&rsquo;s doing enough. &ldquo;Doing&rdquo; concerns only with the present &mdash; mastery is gained eventually. I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s possible to judge easily if someone is in &ldquo;doing&rdquo; or &ldquo;being&rdquo; mode &mdash; that could only be revealed through honesty with oneself. I&rsquo;m also not saying that ambition and possessions are unnecessary or somehow evil. In fact, it feels great to find oneself in a need of a new shiny thing that could be put into immediate and useful purpose.</p>

<p>Driven mostly by the &ldquo;being&rdquo; outlook I followed a long list of interests, many of which I have since given up. Frankly, some of the pursuits transformed from &ldquo;being&rdquo; into a &ldquo;doing&rdquo; mode, such as hiking/mountaineering and photography. Other hobbies went the way of dodo. And boy, I had lots of those: climbing, mountain biking, road cycling, rc helicopters, motorcycling, weight lifting, wind surfing, not to mention various side projects and pastures I don&rsquo;t recall anymore. Not only were these numerous hobbies unsatisfying but they kept an additional pressure to keep up in all of them. Any free time would be a source of contention and uncertainty &mdash; what should I be doing right now? Should I train mountain biking skills? Should I practice new photography techniques? Am I doing enough of this or that? Motorcycling actually came as a symptom. As a typical weekend approached I would almost never choose to ride a motorbike over riding a bicycle. That was a clear signal that motorcycling is not my thing and that I&rsquo;m knee-deep in unnecessary struggles I produced myself.</p>

<p>I mostly see extraneous hobbies as a distraction from dissatisfaction now. For me personally it came from a disconnect between what I was doing everyday at work and what I would rather be doing. Money buys a lot more distraction than any available time can offer. It&rsquo;s all to easy to fall into a trap of visualizing joy after viewing colorful magazines, website and ads. But no amount of stuff can compensate the emptiness and discontent. I am extremely grateful for an opportunity to stumble upon all these realizations and make a change in my own course. I have just one hobby now and that&rsquo;s triathlon. I came into it through love of cycling and trying my hand, or should I say legs, <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals/">at competitive running</a>. How does one find what truly interests him? As contradicting as it may seem but trying out things is the only way to figure out. But it&rsquo;s important not to chase everything at once. There&rsquo;s nothing wrong with giving up a hobby and replacing it with another. Indeed, one of joys in the world is its diversity. Finally, there&rsquo;s the attitude &mdash; not to take any of it too seriously. Nobody truly cares about one&rsquo;s interests and pursuits. When something clicks and the activity brings joy everything else will eventually follow &mdash; passion, ambition and, with good fortune, results.</p>

<p>Do I regret the motorbike purchase? Not a bit. I thoroughly enjoyed touring across Europe. Just that one month-long ride was the gateway into my decision to take a sabbatical and change my life. Due to lack of confidence and experience I couldn&rsquo;t stomach renting a bike at the time &mdash; I was certain I will drop it. However, I haven&rsquo;t actually dropped my bike once! I improved significantly as a rider and with many dealerships in Switzerland offering rentals I can now simply grab a bike whenever I fancy without paying out regular expenses associated with ownership.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - Silent Nanztal Valley Crossing]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/20/photo-report-silent-nanztal-valley-crossing/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-20T20:26:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/20/photo-report-silent-nanztal-valley-crossing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past Sunday I hiked a fantastic route together with my wife. It&rsquo;s the first real hike this year and given the busy times it&rsquo;s unsurprising. But it wasn&rsquo;t just the first of a season. It was the most difficult hike my wife has ever completed and I was left totally impressed with her pace and endurance. Not only we walked for more than 15 kilometers but we also climbed almost a thousand vertical meters. For my wife, who normally prefers flat walks along ridges or lakes, it is a considerable accomplishment.</p>

<p>Day&rsquo;s track on Strava: <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/645364892">https://www.strava.com/activities/645364892</a></p>

<p>Inspiration: <a href="http://www.myswitzerland.com/en-ch/silent-nanztal-valley-crossing.html">myswitzerland.com</a></p>

<p><em>Total distance walked</em>: 14.7km</p>

<p><em>Vertical ascent</em>: 968m</p>

<p><em>Total time</em>: 5:35:00</p>

<p>The day started early as we had to make it to one of the most remote places relative to our home. All in all, about 4 hours of public transport to get there. For me it&rsquo;s the second weekend in a row of visiting canton Valais. There was an accident on the train tracks along the route so our arrival was delayed for about an hour which made us understandably cautious given that our way back depended on a chair lift and chair lifts don&rsquo;t run 24/7. Still we sticked to the original plan and started walking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27778716403"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8896/27778716403_ef72bbbe0e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>It was scorching hot almost everywhere in Switzerland. One of the benefits of staying at higher altitudes is the cooler weather. There was a pleasant breeze throughout the route.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28112075750"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7775/28112075750_9dac6cbea9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Despite the numerous hikes I am still amazed at the scale and the magnificence of mountain landscapes. My mind simply can&rsquo;t grasp the distances. It needs something to put the size into perspective. Nothing gives a better sense than a huge panoramic shot with a tiny human silhouette somewhere in the picture.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28394972325"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8791/28394972325_76349c7ed7_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>For the first time ever we brought trekking poles with us. They were a real boon for my wife. Sadly I&rsquo;ve got none of that as we own just one pair. The poles provided significant support on the way up as well as on the way down. I see now that trekking poles allow us to take more challenging routes. The tactical advantage also evens out our walking paces. Perhaps we could rely on the same strategy for future difficult hikes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28290462142"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8718/28290462142_54c8aa0547.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27778755273"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8595/27778755273_2ac31ec0e2_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>Closer to the end of the hike we stumbled into a herd of cows.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28290496852"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8176/28290496852_10f6070427.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27778226974"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8213/27778226974_d863c73e84.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>I dislike walking fast. When I was much younger I had a tendency to walk so fast that I almost ran. It took me years of deliberate practice to get away from it. It feels great to walk slow and to contemplate the present instead of racing towards yet another passing thing. Still, it&rsquo;s important to keep planned estimates and actual walking speeds in mind. Astonishingly, we have finished quicker than the official signposts suggested! For our dynamic duo it&rsquo;s a remarkable achievement given that we normally arrive 1-2 hours later than any kind of estimate.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28112148850"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8877/28112148850_633a7a517b_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The arrival at the chair lift was disappointing to say the least. We were looking forward to eat a typical mountain Rosti but the kitchen in the restaurant at the lift was already closed. We had no other choice but to scout for food upon descending into the valley. In any case, it was yet another great day in the mountains!</p>

<p>Full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/albums/72157670521888611">available on Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cube Cross Disc Mk3]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-19T21:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have purchased the Cube Cross Disc bicycle second-hand back in 2014 as an ultimate do-it-all machine to replace somewhat petite <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/">BMC hybrid bike</a> I had started cycling on. No other bike in my stable went through as many alterations as the venerable Cube, transitioning from an object of admiration to almost scrap and most recently getting resurrected to fulfill a pragmatic new purpose. It was the bike I rode during the <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">legendary Rhine tour</a>. Perhaps it is also the bike I&rsquo;ve learned most of the bike mechanic skills on.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27799786284"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8682/27799786284_5b8f05055e_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27800895753"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8268/27800895753_4dabb15424_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Originally intended as a noble cause to minimize the number of bikes I own the project turned into an ugly obsession to combine the most exotic parts in a wild chase to build the perfect bike. Following the purchase I stripped the bike to the frame and <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/05/26/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-3/">rebuilt it with custom chosen components</a>. Barely finishing the Rhine tour I went into another frenzy, adding and replacing a good chunk of parts again. A disaster happened one evening when I was fiddling with the bottom bracket. Being distracted by a conversation I have inadvertendly destroyed the thread where the bottom bracket is screwed in. Very often that&rsquo;s the death of the bike frame. And at the time I assumed the bike was gone. I took it apart and, eschewing the faux minimalism, purchased the marvelous <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/">Fargo</a> touring bike and the <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/">BMC road bike</a> I&rsquo;m currently training on. The experience taught me a good lesson about minimalism. It is not always rational, nor cost effective, nor even meaningful. In pursuit of a do-it-all bike I&rsquo;ve ruined the bike by squeezing too much into it. There were panniers&hellip; and aerobars. A lot of parts were installed simply because of hype. Months later, when I brought the destroyed frame to a local bike shop I didn&rsquo;t expect the fatal mistake to get fixed. But it was! The mechanics were able to get the threads rechased. Not knowing what to do with the sudden fortune I left the frame to marinate in the cellar.</p>

<p>Until one day it occurred to me that I have accumulated so many spare bike parts from all the upgrades and replacements that I could probably rebuild the Cube without purchasing much. I also didn&rsquo;t have a city bike that could be left at train stations and public places without too much worry. With the priorities clear I decided to move forward with the rebuild. The priorities were: cheap (as few new parts as possible), disposable (no high-end components) and safe to leave. I am happy to report that I&rsquo;ve been riding this workhorse for more than half a year. It is not sleek nor glitzy but it&rsquo;s a pleasure to use everytime I&rsquo;m off to the swimming pool or to run an errand. I would like to share a couple technical challenges along the way as well as few cool things I came across when putting it all together.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28134119330"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8462/28134119330_605b8e76be.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Guided by the cost I built the drivetrain with a combination of Shimano Zee and Shimano XT components. This being an errand bike I chose to forego the front derailleur and use 10 speeds in the rear for simplicity&rsquo;s sake. The gear range was nicely extended by a spare Wolf Tooth Components 42t sprocket I had. That&rsquo;s how many of the components ended up on the bike &ndash; I simply had them already. The 1x10 system didn&rsquo;t work flawlessly though and I have done lots of small changes to make the chain slide smoothly. The underlying issue was the chainline &mdash; the chain was too skewed in the largest rear sprocket. One could feel the tension. The front sprocket sat too far from the middle, relative to the cassette. That meant that smallest sprockets worked well but anything in the upper middle didn&rsquo;t. Getting the chainline right took many iterations.</p>

<p>At first I moved the bottom bracket spacers from the drive side to non-drive side. A free and noticeable improvement. Next, I have replaced a part of the Shimano XT derailleur with something called a <a href="http://www.wolftoothcomponents.com/products/goatlink">GoatLink</a>. I am not completely sure it made a big difference. The derailleur itself is quite important for the 1x10 drivetrains &mdash; it should be equipped with a clutch mechanism. I&rsquo;m personally using Shimano RD-M786. The final step was to install chainring spacers. That required longer chainring bolts and appropriate spacers. I found it somewhat difficult to track these parts. I found the fitting bolts on CRC although their original purpose seems different: <a href="http://www.chainreactioncycles.com/ch/en/race-face-poly-bashguard-fastener-bolt-kit/rp-prod46947">Race Face Poly Bashguard Fastener Bolt Kit</a>. The spacers must have inner diameter of 10mm. I found those at <a href="http://www.oneupcomponents.com/products/spacer-chainring-10mm-id-4-pack">OneUp</a>. Most recently I replaced the stock 36t Zee chainring with a 38t one. All in all, it works well enough now. I look forward to a time when internal gearboxes, such as the brilliant <a href="http://pinion.eu/en/">pinion</a>, become more widespread and affordable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28383845426"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8619/28383845426_bb078fb0da.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The rest of the bike was put together similarly. The wheels are the cheapest 29&#8221; wheelset I could find on the market at 120 eur for a pair. Similarly, the saddle was only 20 eur. When any of these cheap parts gets stolen I&rsquo;ll just replace them with equally inexpensive alternatives. Knowing that I&rsquo;m going to leave the bike in public spaces I equipped the bike with a few theft deterrents. The first obvious deterrent was a heavy lock. I didn&rsquo;t spare cash on the lock. In fact, it might be the most expensive part of the bike. Secondly, I splurged for a set of Pitlock parts: skewers, stem bolt and the seat post collar bolt. Basically, Pitlock replaces standard skewers and bolts with specially shaped ones that require one of 256 individually-shaped locking tools, called &ldquo;Pits&rdquo;. Here&rsquo;s a visual demonstration how these Pitlock parts look like (front skewer, rear skewer, stem cap):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27799822554"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8834/27799822554_4ef7630a54_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28383884506"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8620/28383884506_ee0db673a1_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27800915953"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8618/27800915953_3472fd2b3e_m.jpg" width="240"></a></p>

<p>At the moment the bike has no original parts left except the frame and the headset. It may be the only Cube Cross Disc in the world with such a long history. Here&rsquo;s the complete list of parts from the build:</p>

<ul>
<li>Frameset: Cube Cross Disc 2013 59cm (stock)</li>
<li>Wheelset: Mavic Crossone 29&#8221; (new part)</li>
<li>Headset: FSA Orbit Z-t, top 1 1/8&#8221;, 44mm, bottom 1 &frac12;&#8221; (stock)</li>
<li>Tires: Specialized Trigger Sport 33-622 (left over from an abandoned project)</li>
<li>Brakes: Shimano Deore BR505, 180mm rotors (left over from an upgrade)</li>
<li>Stem: Ritchey WCS C260 25° 31.8 (left over from Mk1)</li>
<li>Handlebar: Ritchey 580mm (new part, added recently)</li>
<li>Grips: ACROS Bike24 (new part)</li>
<li>Chain: Deore XT 10 speed (spare part)</li>
<li>Derailleur (rear only): Shimano XT RD-M786 (new part) + Wolf Tooth Components GoatLink (new part)</li>
<li>Crankset: Shimano Zee 68/73mm w/ Bottom Bracket (new part) + Wolf Tooth Components 38t (new part, added recently) + <a href="http://www.oneupcomponents.com/products/spacer-chainring-10mm-id-4-pack">OneUp chainring spacer ID 10mm kit</a> + <a href="http://www.chainreactioncycles.com/ch/en/race-face-poly-bashguard-fastener-bolt-kit/rp-prod46947">Race Face Poly Bashguard Fastener Bolt Kit</a></li>
<li>Cassette: Shimano XT CS-M771-10 (left over from an abandoned project) + Wolf Tooth Components GC 42 (left over from an upgrade)</li>
<li>Gear lever (rear only): Shimano Zee SL-M640 (new part)</li>
<li>Saddle: Selle Italia X2 (new part)</li>
<li>Seat post: Cane Creek Thudbuster ST (left over from an upgrade)</li>
<li>Extras: Pitlock set (skewers, stem cap, seat post clamp), ABUS Granit CityChain X-Plus lock (new parts)</li>
</ul>


<p>Head past to the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/albums/72157671282205005">photo gallery</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First 4000m climb]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/16/first-4000m-climb/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-16T08:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/16/first-4000m-climb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am not a peak collector by any stretch of imagination. Indeed I avoid &ldquo;the best&rdquo; like plague. I leave &ldquo;the best&rdquo; for the unsuspecting tourist crowds and boastful blabbers. But the fact is that I&rsquo;ve climbed to the highest altitude in my life. And I&rsquo;ve already paid my dues by feeling the wrath of Gods &mdash; reaching the peak left me untouched and the corresponding up-and-down motions were anything but mindful. Yet the purpose of this 2-day mountaineering trip has been fulfilled &mdash; I am now <em>formally</em> skilled in the basic skills of alpine walking and climbing.</p>

<p>Ever since my <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/">first true alpine adventure last year</a> the pasture of trekking mountains and glaciers attracted me. I have not gone crazy about it and I don&rsquo;t currently have ambitions to get exceedingly great at it. Instead, hiking and mountaineering remain for me a gateway into a state of mind where little matters beyond what&rsquo;s immediately in front of me. I don&rsquo;t care about having the best gear. I also don&rsquo;t care about perceived challenge of this or that route. And I&rsquo;m definitely not going to train for it, say, by attending a climbing wall regularly.</p>

<p>With that said when I saw an opportunity to attend a 2-day mountaineering tour at <a href="http://www.meetup.com/SwissAlpineAdventure/">SwissAlpineAdventure</a> aimed at educating beginners I couldn&rsquo;t pass. A little bit of structured knowledge and training couldn&rsquo;t hurt. The tour brought me back to region of Valais. Our starting point was the town of Saas Fe. The planned itinerary was not difficult. The goal of the first day was to get acquainted with the basics in a sandbox environment and then ascend Allalinhorn (4027m) the following day.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28184032622"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8741/28184032622_23699b3cbf_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27672040364"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8688/27672040364_482b6ed4b2_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28184048972"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8745/28184048972_a7d3ce3ec7_m.jpg" width="240"></a></p>

<p>This is how our movements looked like:</p>

<ul>
<li>Day 1 track: <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/642367091">https://www.strava.com/activities/642367091</a></li>
<li>Day 2 track: <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/642368714">https://www.strava.com/activities/642368714</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Our schedule was generous with late starts, plenty of idle time and lots of help from lifts and cable cars. We didn&rsquo;t come up all the way from the valley. Instead we arrived by cable car to Felskinn station (3000m):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27672071334"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7313/27672071334_89dbebae5b_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The way from the station to the <a href="http://www.britannia.ch/">Britannia hut</a> (3030m) was a short and mild stretch of slushing through snow. Our guide from <a href="http://www.bergundtal.ch/">bergundtal</a> Stephane Tuni engaged us regularly by educating about the hiding dangers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27672389023"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8597/27672389023_93b0741595.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a baby peak Klein Allalin (3070m) opposite the Britannia hut which we have used throughout the first day to practice. We learned how to correctly hold the axe, how to tie the ropes and how to safely walk with crampons.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28209634331"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8576/28209634331_6e4a49b05d.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28209631481"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7062/28209631481_d9eef0a8c8.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The views from Klein Allalin are grand:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28209622501"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7712/28209622501_1e7956d0d2_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28253906596"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8625/28253906596_86403bccd1.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Seeing Ilya on this tour was a true serendipitous encounter. We haven&rsquo;t coordinated our participation. It just happened by chance. Ilya rightly complained about a recent trip to our beloved outdoor gear shop Transa and how much it cost him. I can relate easily as I&rsquo;ve done that trip last year. Right now I&rsquo;m all set with the gear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28184107462"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8671/28184107462_8d34f89268.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>The Britannia hut is relatively large and quite modern. I admit I&rsquo;m spoiled by great huts. Last year&rsquo;s trek was accompanied by huts that were as good and as modern. The hut is situated close to the cable-car station so it attracts a lot of visitors, especially during a weekend. It feels more like a hostel that just happpened to be in mountains. It was packed.</p>

<p>Knowing that I wouldn&rsquo;t fall asleep easily I decided to take a tripod with me and stay on Klein Allalinhorn until it gets dark to see the stars. The sky was relatively clear.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28288171755"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8862/28288171755_3c9cc512a8_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27672137354"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7704/27672137354_ef13a732b7_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Unfortunately, I did not stay long enough to make worthwhile pictures of a starry night but I enjoyed the sight myself. Fantastic. When the complete darkness fell upon the mountains I felt a bit uncomfortable. Movements behind my back stirred alertness. A running marmot was the final drop on my nerves so I decided to get back to the hut and sit on a bench, marvelling at the sight.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28288177805"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8598/28288177805_472acd0af9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>My predictions about inability to sleep came true. I could hardly sleep that night with so many people in the room. Perhaps there was also part of altitude difference playing its role. In any case we got up relatively late at 5am to have breakfast and left the hut at about 6am.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28253929596"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8651/28253929596_07c62879ac_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>There was no rush as we were going to take a lift to Mittelallalin (3457m) station and walk from there. As it turned out, the lift opened later that we had expected so we had to wait. Furthemore, the Metro Alpin lift broke down. We waited in suspension hoping for the best. Fortunately, the team of mechanics departed with a helicopter and all technical problems were adressed in a couple of hours. Since our plans had sufficient slack even a significant delay like this didn&rsquo;t prevent us from completing the tour.</p>

<p>After the ride with the lift the tour turned bitter. Especially on the way down. I found the way to the summit and back uncomfortably fast. At times I felt that the rope is pulling me forward, dragging the ground from underneat my feet. I still don&rsquo;t understand why we had to rush so much. There were also too many other groups on the way. These two factors somewhat spoiled the atmosphere. The tour didn&rsquo;t feel good anymore. It felt like we were a tourist group shown around a popular sight somewhere in a middle of a large city.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27672491473"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8637/27672491473_8d76450ce6_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Reaching the summit did not feel anything special. It was not deserved &mdash; we cheated our way through cable cars and lifts. And there were so many other folks!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27672185304"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8742/27672185304_c2567bf916.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>Our crew at the summit:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28006658860"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8597/28006658860_19a702d00b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure I&rsquo;d like to visit such popular peaks again, especially during a busy time like the weekend. I am also not sure about going with groups of people I haven&rsquo;t met before. It&rsquo;s certainly nice to meet new people but I think I prefer to go with the people I already know and trust. Despite certain mental dissatisfaction I&rsquo;m already signed-up for a follow-up trip in August. Let&rsquo;s hope we&rsquo;ll avoid some of the issues.</p>

<p>Head past to the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/sets/72157670336416871/">full gallery</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Better at Solving Coding (Interview) Problems]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/08/getting-better-at-solving-coding-interview-problems/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-08T18:37:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/08/getting-better-at-solving-coding-interview-problems</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is part 2 of a series of articles themed &ldquo;Preparing for Software Engineer Interviews&rdquo;. My goal with the series is to document the steps I took while preparing for interviews for a software engineering position after working six years in predominantly support-leaning roles. I won&rsquo;t break new ground here but rather share personal experience &mdash; anything you see here is an echo of what you can find elsewhere on the Internet. But too much of a good thing could be bad. Too much advice obscures itself and makes it hard to navigate. In <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code/">part 1</a> I explained how I improved my knowledge of algorithms and data-structures as well as introduced a regular coding exercise. In this part I will explain how I went about improving interview coding skills.</p>

<p>When I was originally confronted with preparing for interviews I pulled many online resources together: posts on quora and stackoverflow, blog posts, articles and forum discussions. Some of the posts were quite detailed and comprehensive. There is lot of common advice but I struggled because there was just too much to do and too many ways to go about it. I decided to follow a simple plan which I will shortly explain below.</p>

<p>What is so special about software engineer interviews? The basic premise of most coding interviews (we&rsquo;re talking about interviews at mostly large tech companies here) is to present a candidate with a novel problem that he has never seen before to see how good his reasoning and problem solving skills are. Presumably, a coding interview is a good indicator of candidate&rsquo;s abilities and real-world productivity. Seeing how the candidate struggles under pressure, comes up with brilliant solutions and communicates with the interviewer is a telltale sign of his future success at the company. Unfortunately, that&rsquo;s only a presumption and the reality is complicated but at the moment most tech companies stick to the same format which means that candidates must eventually go through it. So let&rsquo;s look through some preparation ideas and shed some bullshit along the way.</p>

<p>First, there&rsquo;s the novelty issue. It is not feasible to come with a completely new coding problem for every interview. Instead, inteviewers usually rely on a limited repertoire of problems. These problems eventually leak out and get shared online. More importantly, though, many problems share similar problem-solving strategies. Once the insight is known to a candidate the problem reduces to relatively painless translation to code. I&rsquo;ve seen judgements against candidates that try to memorize solutions. But how can a solution be memorized? There are not 10 or 20 problems out there. There are hundreds, even thousands. Nobody would try to memorize the solution code line by line. But it is fair to assume that candidates memorize ideas and patterns behind the problems. How else could the candidates do well on interviews? Let&rsquo;s take mathematics. Undeniably there is lots of memorization involved when learning any subject in mathematics. We can&rsquo;t assume that candidates come up with algebra concepts from scratch during their short stay. Why then would it be fair to expect candidates to come up with algorithms that took very distinguished and persistent computer scientists and engineers to come up with?</p>

<p>In short, obtaining the insight and patterns behind coding problems and memorizing the right things is in my opinion the essence of interview preparation. Even the most distinguished engineers admit that in their day to day work they rarely get a chance to tackle difficult algorithmic challenges. I&rsquo;m not saying that advanced skills are unnecessary and everyone should be an API coding monkey. I&rsquo;m saying that candidates must work through typical coding problems, extract vital problem solving patterns and approaches. The fact remains, though, that some amount of memorizing is unavoidable. If a candidate didn&rsquo;t have a need to optimize things at a very low level it&rsquo;s unlikely he&rsquo;ll come up with a good solution for bit twiddling questions even though he understands the underlying concepts well. He just wouldn&rsquo;t have enough time. And certain efficient solutions are very clever to the point of being obscure and unintuitive. There&rsquo;s little chance of coming up with one during 45 stressful minutes.</p>

<p>In fact, I would go as far as to say that some solutions must be memorized almost to the point of line by line. Okay, maybe not that far. But there are a some smaller-sized questions that interviewers like to ask as a warm-up. For example, to implement a power function or the greatest common divisor function. The thing is, interviewers expect flawless and, most importantly, quick (read immediate) implementation. Even if a candidate understands the idea it might take too long to translate that idea into code on the board. Plus, there are many possibilities for subtle common bugs, such as off-by-one errors, out-of-bounds, etc. Normally, a programmer is not rushed so there&rsquo;s sufficient time to think, sketch pseudocode, implement and take care of edge cases. Because the problem is not difficult the interviewer will pick apart even the smallest mistakes and attach disproportionate weight to them. Clearly, candidates that prepared well will look more capable although it is debatable if their performance difference would translate in anything measurable in the real world.</p>

<p>Once a candidate gets exposed to a sufficient amount of problems (in the range of hundreds) there comes a plateau point. That&rsquo;s completely normal and expected. Despite the acquired experience many problems won&rsquo;t seem any easier. That&rsquo;s also normal. In fact, this discourages many aspiring competitive programmers from further pursuing the challenge. Certain kinds of problems do not fall under neat patterns and require a different mindset. I personally haven&rsquo;t yet managed to overcome this plateau. The good news is that such problems are rarely, if ever, asked in interviews. The bad news is that getting good at difficult problems worsens performance at interview problems. And the reason is that one tries to apply unconvential and complex data-structures and algorithms whereas most interview coding problems are centered around a set of relatively simple tools. Dead-ends are time consuming and reduce chances of solving the problem. After going through many rounds of mock interviews (which I discuss in the 3rd part of the series) I realized that I must recalibrate my toolkit and stick to simplest tools unless everything else fails. When my first thought reaches for a suffix tree I resist and instead try one of the following (not exhaustive): sorting, using a queue/stack, traversing, reversing, doing binary search, recursing. I also find it helpful to think of a brute force solution first. The lesson is that most coding problems are simple and rarely involve anything exotic. When they do the interviewer is prepared to almost immediately spill the beans on the magic insight.</p>

<p>So how to go about actually preparing? I have taken a whole month of full-time effort to specifically practice interview coding problems. There are many popular sources with coding problems, to name a few:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.topcoder.com/">TopCoder</a> &mdash; not suited well for interview preparation because of the nature of the problems, weird problem classification and an arcane UI. TopCoder is really a tool for competitive programming and it&rsquo;s not designed for practicing interview problems. Given time constraints and different goals in mind I wouldn&rsquo;t spend time on TopCoder.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://uva.onlinejudge.org/">UVA judge</a> &mdash; automated system for submitting solutions to various competitive programming problems. Suffers from similar problems as TopCoder. Also, just like with TopCoder, it is hard to keep track of progress or to cover all topics.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cracking-Coding-Interview-Programming-Questions/dp/0984782850">Cracking the Coding Interview book</a> &mdash; extremely popular book with around 150 coding problems and solutions. I went through an earlier edition years ago. Haven&rsquo;t seen or used the recent one.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.interviewbit.com/">interviewbit</a> &mdash; a well designed system specifically for preparing for interviews. Problems are classified by topics. There&rsquo;s search functionality that lets, for example, to search for problems asked at certain companies. interviewbit also has an excellent gamified progress tracking functionality. Unfortunately, I found out too late about it. Otherwise, I would have likely used it as a primary preparation tool.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Elements-Programming-Interviews-Java-Adnan/dp/1517671272">Elements of Programming Interviews in Java (EPI) book</a> &mdash; this is my choice! The books comes with hundreds of problems with clear explanations of brute-force and optimal solutions. C++ edition is also available.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.hackerrank.com/">HackerRank</a> &mdash; feels like a system which serves both competitive programming and interview preparation well. There are many practice problems classified by topics and regular hosted competitions. I have used HackerRank as a complementary resource.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.geeksforgeeks.org/">GeeksForGeeks</a> &mdash; a daily blog of coding problems. I have yet to come across an interview coding problem that is not published there.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Once I settled on a primary source I&rsquo;ve done two passes:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Go through every problem in the EPI book and solve them algorithmically without writing any code. I&rsquo;ve set a time limit of 10-15 minutes per problem. Once the time limit expired I consulted the solution. I think it&rsquo;s better to have a time limit rather than get stuck for hours on a problem. Generally, I think it&rsquo;s great to sometimes persist on a problem until it cracks but given the goals of interview preparation it&rsquo;s more effective to absorb as many concepts as possible. For every problem I wrote down the main insight. It took me about 2 weeks to finish the whole book.</p></li>
<li><p>Go through every solved problem and write code for it. This is where I realized that my previously-written notes were terrible so I often had to solve the problems again. I wrote code on paper and I felt that writing code with the insight in hand is easy. I&rsquo;m sure there are folks for whom finding the insight is easier.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>I complemented EPI with problems from the HackerRank site. Finally, during two weeks leading to interviews I also solved every problem marked with the company I was applying for on interviewbit. You&rsquo;d be surprised just how often widely publicized problems are still actively asked in interviews so it pays to go through them. I haven&rsquo;t actually used interviewbit as a platform. Instead, I just read the problem descriptions and solved them on paper. Whenever I got stuck I consulted the hints or complete editorials (solutions).</p>

<p>After putting so much effort in the preparation can I say it was worth it? Did it help to get an offer? Getting good at solving coding interview problems takes a considerable effort and it is not a sure guarantee of success. However, a lack of such preparation is a sure guarantee of failure. There are too many factors vying for the final hire/no hire decision and success is anything but guaranteed. Just like with the algorithm and data-structure study I feel this effort made me a little bit better as a programmer. And just like with <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code/">algorithm katas</a> I would like to adopt a habit of regularly solving coding problems to improve further.</p>

<p>In the concluding part 3 I will talk about the final interview preparation steps and also talk about the psychological challenges that many candidates such as myself face before and during the interviews and the ways to tackle them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Triathlon progress update]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-23T20:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I enjoy training for triathlon immensely. The sport attracts me with multidimensionality and the numerous skills involved. There is so much room for growth. It&rsquo;s an art really. I will regularly share some of my observations as I progress towards my next triathlon goal &ndash; <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/">completing a half Ironman</a>.</p>

<h2>Cycling</h2>

<p>After <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/">raving about Zwift</a> and following its 4 month training program I chose to continue my training using <a href="https://www.trainerroad.com/">TrainerRoad</a> software instead. These two programs cannot be directly compared because they serve completely different purposes. While Zwift provides a 3D virtual world to make indoor rides exciting TrainerRoad focuses instead on a quality selection of training programs and virtual coaching.</p>

<p>What do I mean by virtual coaching? During each session TrainerRoad guides you with advice regarding correct technique and the training session itself. The implementation is very simple &ndash; just regular text messages. But for a newbie like myself getting bite-sized pieces of fundamental cycling wisdom is invaluable.</p>

<p>For example, I had a bit of a toe-numbing problem. My toes would get numb by the middle of the training session. I have partially solved the problem by sliding my feet forward in relation to the pedal spindles and also by moving the saddle slightly forward. However, numbing did not disappear completely. Out of despair I contemplated buying road-specific shoes and pedals. But during one of the first sessions TrainerRoad addressed the issue by explaining the correct kick-and-pull pedaling technique. The idea was reinforced by the single-leg cycling intervals. Numbing went away once and for all!</p>

<p>Same goes for other basics, like breathing and body position. Explanations are brief and to the point. The ideas are regularly reminded and reinforced through practice.</p>

<p>Initially, I chose a medium-volume training program and sticked to the assessed FTP value of 204 watts. After a couple of training sessions I realized this is above my level so I reset my FTP at 190 watts and chose the most basic training program. There&rsquo;s no point trying to jump ahead of myself. Overtraining leads to exhaustion and loss of motivation. I&rsquo;m in this sport for the long-haul so I must not torture myself if I want to go on.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m all set with cycling for the next 3-4 weeks. Afterwards I&rsquo;ll choose a training program that builds on top of the current one. I feel TrainerRoad will provide me with sufficient training material for the next couple of months.</p>

<h2>Swimming</h2>

<p>I started with swimming in October 2015. I went for a week worth of private coaching. I never trained so my form was as bad as it gets. At the time I had no idea how front-crawl works but I knew an efficient swimming form is vital for competition. Following that session I made a habit to visit a local swimming pool 3 times a week. I alternated sessions between doing crawl-related exercises and longish 2k breast-stroke swims. The latter also improved my breathing and endurance.</p>

<p>In March 2016 I signed-up for a front-crawl course. At the moment I can swim crawl 50 metres non-stop and actually feel relaxed and enjoy it! The next step is to do 200-300m stretches without any rest. During a typical training session I combine exercises (e.g. kickboard) and training intervals, typically 200m long. In a few months I&rsquo;ll need further coach input to improve my form but at the moment I have plenty of practice to complete on my own.</p>

<h2>Running</h2>

<p>This is the saddest part. While my <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">fractured tibia seemed to be completely recovered</a> it started to act up again. About two weeks ago I started with 4 short runs per week (each 3km long). After the 5th session I felt my tibia again. It&rsquo;s nowhere close to the <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">pain I experienced during the half-marathon when it actually fractured</a> but I must be careful not to make it worse. I wouldn&rsquo;t even call it pain. It&rsquo;s more of a whining feeling.</p>

<p>I have decided to space out the runs until there&rsquo;s no pain remaining. I&rsquo;m looking at a run every two weeks right now. I definitely won&rsquo;t make any aerobic advancements with such a tempo but my primary target is to get the bone strong again. I also consider incorporating intervals into the sessions. And by intervals I mean interleaving walking with running.</p>

<h2>Gear</h2>

<p>As I mentioned in the cycling section I <em>wanted</em> (already a wrong attitude) to buy road-specific shoes (likely black SIDIs) and road-specific pedals (likely Shimano 105). Better pedaling technique solved the problem so for now I can keep my trusted Shimano XT pedals and Specialized Rime shoes (which are walkable off the bike).</p>

<p>Despite previous discomfort I re-installed a proper racing seat &mdash; Brooks C13. Turns out I had incorrectly kept my body on the seat. The correct posture keeps both siting bones in contact with seat wings. Instead, I had been leaning my hips too much forward, causing too much stress on the pubic bone. Once I changed my posture comfort issues went out of the window!</p>

<h2>Misc</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve done a first pass through &ldquo;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Triathletes-Training-Bible-Joe-Friel/dp/1934030198">The Triathlete&rsquo;s Training Bible</a>&rdquo; &mdash; an excellent book for anyone who&rsquo;s seriously interested in the sport. It&rsquo;s much better than a few titles I had previously laid my eyes on. The book is ripe with subtance and with experience distilled from a career of coaching. I feel I&rsquo;m getting a little bit ahead of myself. Most of the advice in the book applies to experienced athletes with at least a couple of years of experience who are aiming at improving performance. My current goals are far less ambitious. I want to gracefully finish a half Ironman. But I figure there&rsquo;s no harm knowing what lies ahead and avoiding common pitfalls.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;ve started regular triathlon training (roughly January 2016) I&rsquo;ve lost 5 kg. The current weight seems to be stable at about 74kg. I&rsquo;m not yet doing anything special in regards to nutrition yet but I&rsquo;m planning to introduce a post-training recovery drink next month.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s about it for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Kata of Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-12T15:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is part 1 of a series of articles themed &ldquo;Preparing for Software Engineer Interviews&rdquo;. My goal with the series is to document the steps I took while preparing for interviews for a software engineering position after working six years in predominantly support-leaning roles. I won&rsquo;t break new ground here but rather share personal experience &mdash; anything you see here is an echo of what you can find elsewhere on the Internet. But too much of a good thing could be bad. Too much advice obscures itself and makes it hard to navigate. In this part I will explain how I went about refreshing and improving knowledge of algorithms and data structures.</p>

<p>A fancy word makes even the most mundane things sound legitimate. Enter &lsquo;kata&rsquo; &mdash; a fancy way of saying that one does something mundane, regularly. Originally, the Japanese word &lsquo;kata&rsquo; stands for a very specific kind of practice in traditional arts. But in the programming world it&rsquo;s synonymous with a repetitive coding practice. I have no opinion in the linguistic department but I believe the practice might have some substance. Let me rewind a little bit.</p>

<p>Exactly one year ago I <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/">left a wonderful job in one of the best places to work</a> on this planet. With such a drastic move there&rsquo;s a multitude of reasons. One of the major ones is my ambition to become an excellent software engineer and steer away from the technical support role I had so far pursued.</p>

<p>The first obstacle on the way are the well-known and sometimes wacky software interviews that most respectable companies seem to rely on for choosing among candidates. To prepare myself for the challenge I devised a multi-month plan. About 3 months ago, as I was done with another full-time endeavour, I put the plan through its paces. In this article I&rsquo;ll do my best to explain the first step of the plan &mdash; the study and practice of algorithms and data-structures.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not like I&rsquo;ve never studied algorithms. In fact, I hold a computer science degree and have completed several excellent online algorithm-focused courses with top marks (<a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partI">Algorithms Part I</a>, <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partII">Algorithms Part II</a>). But annoyingly if you had asked me to implement a path-finding algorithm or even an O(N*LogN) sorting algorithm I would have struggled without referring to technical books or articles. Should you have asked the same question straight after I had just completed the courses I would have absolutely no issues. From a limited personal survey of fellow engineers it is a very common situation. Few keep algorithms in their heads.</p>

<p>Clearly, without an excellent understanding of algorithms passing a coding interview is unlikely. Besides, algorithms and data structures are the cornerstones of computer science and software. Without the understanding of basic structures it&rsquo;s not possible to solve most of the coding challenges. So I dedicated the first month of preparation to the study of algorithms.</p>

<p>However, as I&rsquo;ve already learned, the chosen method of study is critical. It&rsquo;s all to easy to complete a course or a book and then forget everything few weeks after. It is also not sufficient to merely browse through a book or a bunch of articles. Superflous reading creates a perilous illusion of understanding. It is imperative to work through. That&rsquo;s why going through one algorithms book takes a month of full-time effort and not an afternoon. I also emphasize that I had completed algorithm courses before starting this effort. Otherwise, it would make sense to study through the online courses mentioned above first. It would also significantly lengthen the plan.</p>

<p>As there are many more algorithms than the time available to me I had to optimize. It makes little sense to study the most esoteric and domain-specific algorithms for the purpose of preparing for software interviews. I made a survey of interview-related Q&amp;As and websites and came up with the following initial list of algorithms and data structures (in no particular order):</p>

<pre><code>* Stack/Queue (based on LinkedList)
* Selection Sort
* SeparateChainingHashST
* LSD/MSD sort (Radix)
* Graph/Digraph/WeightedGraph
* Edge/EdgeWeightedGraph
* DFS/BFS
* Binary Search
* Weighted Quick Union
* Insertion Sort
* Shell Sort
* DFSPaths/BFSPaths
* Cycle detection in undirected graph
* Connected Components with DFS in undirected graph
* Bipartite check in undirected graph (two color)
* Merge Sort
* Bottom-up Merge Sort
* Quicksort
* 3-way Quicksort
* CountSort
* Min/MaxPQ
* Heapsort
* BST
* Red-black BST
* LinearProbingHashST
* Cycle detection in directed graph
* DFS order and Topological sort
* Kosaraju-Sharir Strong Connected Components in directed graph
* Kruskal MST
* Prim MST
* Dijkstra SP
* Acyclic SP
* Bellman-Ford SP
* Knuth-Morris-Prath search
* Boyer-Moore search
</code></pre>

<p>It is debatable if some of the algorithms in this list are already too complex for general software engineering interviews (knowledge of esoteric algorithms might be required for more senior or specialized roles). In fact, as practice went by I added a few additional ones and removed a few.</p>

<p>The book I chose for my study is &ldquo;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-4th-Robert-Sedgewick/dp/032157351X">Algorithms, 4th edition</a>&rdquo; from Robert Sedgewick at Princeton University. It&rsquo;s written by the same professor that teaches the corresponding online courses. What sets it apart from other famous algorithm texts is the focus on visually illustrating algorithms and doing algorithm-tracing exercises. Working through an algorithm on paper and tracing all the steps helps to grasp what the algorithm really does. Through these exercises I uncovered that my mental models for some of the algorithms were wrong. The other huge benefit of this book is a <a href="http://algs4.cs.princeton.edu/">complementary codesite</a> with lots of high-quality and clearly-written implementations of algorithms in Java.</p>

<p>My daily routine consisted of reading about one topic and related algorithms and then trying to re-implement the algorithms myself. As soon as I stumbled I looked-up the text. The complementary code is extremely readable. The implementations may lack some of the fanciest and trickiest optimizations but are invaluable tools for learning. Once I implemented the code I erased and started from scratch, testing thoroughness of my understanding.</p>

<p>As the days went by and I progressed further I felt that I no longer remembered the details of algorithms I had already worked-through. That&rsquo;s when I decided to introduce additional regular algorithm coding practice &mdash; katas. I grouped some of the algorithms together. Then during each practice session I would implement algorithms and data-structures from the top of my head, copying only test cases from the reference implementation. At times I would get stuck. In those moments I learned a little bit more about each algorithm. Often, I would get confused and need to look-up the reference implementation. Next time, though, the practice would become easier and more automatic. Katas keep the algorithm knowledge functional and fresh. Furthermore, being able to implement some of the tricky algorithms from the top of my head on a napkin increases confidence which may sometimes shake under the many stresses of interviews. Finally, being able to implement many algorithms quickly pays off in coding competitions.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know if the original katas are canonical. My coding katas are certainly not. They evolve and change with time. At some point easier algorithms and data-structures become trivial and it no longer makes sense to practice them. I don&rsquo;t practice writing a stack/queue anymore. Sometimes I realize how similar few algorithms are so I leave one of them out. Many graph problems reduce to DFS. Occasionally I study through new algorithms and add them to katas. For example, I&rsquo;ve recently added SkipList and SuffixArray. I also group algorithms so that each kata is of similar size. At the moment I have <a href="https://github.com/drseergio/practice/tree/master/katas">5 katas in my repertoire</a>. It takes about 30-60 minutes to complete each one. I aim to complete all of the katas once a week &mdash; on average less than one kata per day. I&rsquo;m also timing my practice now to see how long each kata takes.</p>

<p><strong>Here&rsquo;s a distilled version of the algorithm study plan (~1 month of full-time effort)</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>List algorithms/data-structures you need to learn deeply. When in doubt leave it out. Make it as short as feasible. Can always add more later.</li>
<li>Choose an algorithms text. I recommend <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-4th-Robert-Sedgewick/dp/032157351X">&ldquo;Algorithms, 4th edition&rdquo; by Robert Sedgewick</a>.</li>
<li>Schedule sufficient time each day to read the text and implement algorithms by hand. Keep premature enthusiasm at hand and keep the workload manageable. There&rsquo;s a reason it takes a month.</li>
<li>Collect algorithm implementations and group them into katas.</li>
<li>Regularly perform katas by reimplementing algorithms.</li>
<li>Revise katas, remove trivial algorithms and add new ones as you see fit.</li>
<li>Repeat 6, 7.</li>
</ol>


<p>I&rsquo;d like to believe that this study of algorithms and practice of katas will pay off. It is hard to say, taking into account the many factors that affect a hiring decision. Doing a comprehensive study like this won&rsquo;t guarantee success but doing nothing almost certainly guarantees failure. The study of algorithms is just the first interview preparation step. I&rsquo;ve introduced katas as means to not forget what I&rsquo;ve just learned. But as I&rsquo;ve practiced and grown my personal collection I see myself continuing with katas.</p>

<p>In the <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/08/getting-better-at-solving-coding-interview-problems/">next part (2)</a> I explain my strategy for getting better at solving coding problems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Samaria Gorge hike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-30T21:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exactly two weeks ago I thought I was exhausted from preparing for job interviews (I will write a separate post explaining my study strategy). After all, I have been averaging 6-8 hours of algorithms and Java study almost every day for 2 months (I am switching careers and going full-time in software engineering). In reality, it was a virus that caused physical break-down, an eye infection and fever. In what can be described as the most spontaneous decision of my life I decided we need to take a short break and go to the sea. How spontaneous? I felt debilitating headache Monday morning and we flew out on Wednesday.</p>

<p>So we chose a destination we could fly to ASAP that had decent weather and warm sea. In the end we went to Crete. I had previously visited Crete 10 years ago. Crete left an impression not only with the warm Mediterranean climate and usual resort-world bells and whistles but also with a natural wonder I couldn&rsquo;t visit at the time. I&rsquo;m talking about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samari%C3%A1_Gorge">Samaria Gorge</a>. It was time to finally hike it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720077554"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7444/26720077554_8d954f1239_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I am amazed at how the local businesses managed to market and sell Samaria Gorge and lull even the most unprepared unfit tourists, making it a must-visit attraction. In the high season, which unsurprisingly is the worst time of the year to visit it, Samaria Gorge attracts 30,000-40,000 tourists per month. Some of those tourists later write horror stories as to how difficult and extreme the whole experience was. Legends get born and rumors get spread.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here to bust some myths. First of all, it is not the largest Gorge in Europe. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verdon_Gorge">Verdon Gorge</a> is. Second, it is not an extremely difficult adventure. It&rsquo;s best described as a hike of medium-easy difficulty. Most of the time the route descends which is admittedly not my favorite (I prefer ascents or mixed terrain). While the terrain is rocky there is nothing extreme about it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720813773"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7251/26720813773_bb58db0b87_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27052274170"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7653/27052274170_654d0d72a3_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27257029391"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7006/27257029391_246c4a35bb_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>In terms of gear the hike requires mostly decent shoes. I brought the most minimal and lightweight shoes I own and they were just fine. Apparently the overly successful marketing attracts unsuspecting couch potatoes in flip-flops but I haven&rsquo;t spotted a single person whose clothing stood out as outlandlishly inadequate.</p>

<p>Without any strain we completed the walk in 5:45. We took lots of pictures and made one stop for packed breakfast in the old Samaria village which is in the middle of the route. My watch counted 20Km but I suspect that&rsquo;s due to errors due to poor sky visibility in the gorge. Officially, the total distance from the park entrance to the beach is approximately 17Km. Sounds realistic.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/590696789">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>End of May is a fantastic time to visit it because the gorge is full of life: vegetation and flowers. Most importantly, it is not scorching hot. I find that the scenery becomes interesting after the Samaria village, roughly 8-10Km into the hike. The first half is similar to a walk in a park and it&rsquo;s not possible to see much of the gorge. But the actual gorge looks breathtaking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27230250722"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7349/27230250722_01d870f748_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>In fact, I would consider visiting the park in the opposite direction: arriving by ship at the end of the route in the morning, exploring the gorge area up to the Samaria village and taking the ship back. It&rsquo;s possible to pull this off with a rental car by keeping it in the town from where the ship departs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27257075871"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7001/27257075871_daabee70cf_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27230278702"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7370/27230278702_2a68bc4ed6_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27052293150"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7439/27052293150_bf9f47ae31_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Speaking of transportation it&rsquo;s not great. There are only 3 ships per day: 2 in the morning and only one in the afternoon at 17:30. Those who finish reasonably at about 14:00-15:00 are doomed to stay in the area. Admittedly, the area ain&rsquo;t bad and the beach is completely worth a visit. In case somebody doesn&rsquo;t make it to the ship there are plenty of rooms available for rent.</p>

<p>We chose to get to the park and back by taxi. The price is not unreasonable if staying near city of Chania. For us, the higher taxi price was worth extra hours in the morning and in the evening. A tourist bus takes longer because it needs to pick-up tourists from various hotels.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720065894"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7558/26720065894_49f0bc7d21_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re visiting Crete pack a pair of shoes &mdash; the gorge is worth a visit!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indoor cycling lab]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-28T18:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Around Christmas in 2015 I received doctor&rsquo;s diagnosis that my left tibia bone is fractured and that I can&rsquo;t run for the foreseeable future. Of course, I tried against all reason but the persisting pain made me realize it&rsquo;s in my own best interest to let it heal peacefully and not break it completely. Luckily, I discovered that cycling and swimming don&rsquo;t hurt at all. I suppose that&rsquo;s because the load spread is altered and tibia is not as stressed.</p>

<p>I decided not to lose any time and began training straight away. I have setup an indoor training &ldquo;lab&rdquo; and rigorously followed a training routine three times a week. Although I have been an avid cyclist my level of cycling fitness could have been ranked as &ldquo;beginner&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;ve had plenty of distance under my belt but insufficient endurance to sustain intensive effort necessary in competitive cycling. The training program has slowly come to a successful end and I would like to showcase my setup.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306868565"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7345/27306868565_5c29150c79_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I previously found the idea of indoor cycling trainers a boring pasture. However, training indoors has its merits. The biggest advantage I see is the possibility of structured training where the load of every training session is carefully chosen to stimulate improvement in the areas that need it the most. It is very difficult to go for a ride with friends and keep a specific tempo. With an indoor trainer it&rsquo;s possible to define fine-grained intervals with specific intensity. There are training programs for improving overall cycling fitness or, for example, improving climbs or sprints.</p>

<p>Of course, there is also the convenience factor. With an indoor trainer I have no excuse skipping a training session due to bad weather. It&rsquo;s always available and takes no time to get started with it.</p>

<p>But what really attracted me are the so-called smart trainers, like the <a href="http://eu.wahoofitness.com/devices/kickr.html">wahoo Kickr</a> that I purchased. The smart trainers are dynamically controlled by software so the resistance is continuously updated. Smart trainers can simulate changing terrain and most importantly let the user focus on cycling. With the regular &ldquo;dumb&rdquo; trainers the user must adjust resistance manually. I think I would get tired of it very quickly and would definitely cheat by not being timely in amping up the difficulty.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26700511863"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7605/26700511863_2f9435ffaf_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27236905401"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7352/27236905401_bf09f5907b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>There are various tools for controlling smart trainers. Some run on Android and iOS devices while others require full desktop OSes. Either bluetooth or ANT+ wireless protocols are used to interface with the trainers. I purchased an ANT+ adapter for my computer for the purpose of controlling the smart trainer and also for accessing data from a heart rate band and a power meter sensor on my bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27209876762"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7323/27209876762_5bafeb4735.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The &ldquo;killer app&rdquo; for me is surely <a href="http://zwift.com/">Zwift</a>. It&rsquo;s a well-implemented detailed immersive 3D virtual cycling world. Zwift is capable of controling smart trainers and simulating terrain. For all the user cares he is presented with a detailed simulation that brings variety and much needed distraction to otherwise boring workouts. Zwift is a open-world multiplayer game with other cyclists riding along. Zwift integrates nicely with Strava, here is a couple of my own workouts:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/554205363">https://www.strava.com/activities/554205363</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/536343127">https://www.strava.com/activities/536343127</a></p>

<p>Zwift also supports structured training. There are multiple training programs to choose from. It&rsquo;s also possible to create a custom one. I chose a 12-week program aimed at increasing overall cycling fitness and specifically improving the Functional Threshold Power (FTP). With ilnesses, travel and other commitments in place the program actually took me more than 4 months to complete.</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/tqf5dD-ofQg "></iframe></div>


<p>I have complemented the setup with a webcam mounted on a tripod and connected to my mobile computer. This allowed to see my posture and make continous corrections. A mirror would work even better but there is no place in my room for one and I already had all the components to make a &ldquo;high-tech mirror&rdquo; solution work.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26699661594"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7311/26699661594_317dc183ac_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>This is how I see myself during a typical workout (videos are not focused very well but the idea should be clear):</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/QnhQLFUJRjQ "></iframe></div>




<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/CntF-2F9kGc "></iframe></div>


<p>Speaking of complements I discovered a few additional pieces of technology I consider vital for training and worthy of an immediate purchase. First of all, a bicycle computer or a training watch equipped with GPS and ANT+/Bluetooth interfaces. I went for both, choosing a Garmin 920XT watch and a Garmin Edge 500 cycling computer. These gadgets track workouts and allow the user to see his progress and make corrections. Having these devices is a luxury that had been available only to professional athletes in the past. Basically, it&rsquo;s like having a personal coach watch over your shoulder every moment.</p>

<p>The reason I own both is because a cycling computer is convenient for glancing at many fields at a time, without taking the hand off the handlebar. I use the cycling computer exclusively for viewing data. In fact, I bought it used at a bargain price. I don&rsquo;t cosider fancier products worthwhile.</p>

<p>Finally, a power meter is becoming increasingly popular. I&rsquo;m going so far as to say that a power meter is a complete must, especially if the user is an amateur interested in racing. A power meter basically quantifies the effort the user is currently putting out. It takes guessing out of the training. With a power meter I can adjust my power output and effort during a ride. For example, in a race I could adjust power output depending on the course to avoid overstrain. I could immediately see if the current effort is sustainable or not based on past observations. Smart trainers come with built-in power meters but I&rsquo;ve added a relatively inexpensive <a href="http://stagescycling.com/us/products/">Stages power-meter</a> for upcoming outdoor rides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306885605"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7208/27306885605_5158cd1438_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26699671554"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7311/26699671554_64e405b1c0_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>With the program almost finished what do I plan to do next? My <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">tibia has recovered</a> and I&rsquo;m almost finished with a 4-month swimming training program. I am going to develop a new plan for the next 3-4 months. With the summer here I&rsquo;m definitely going outdoors but I&rsquo;ll combine the outdoor rides with more structured indoor training to hone some of the skills, like climbing. Training ain&rsquo;t easy but I get lots of satisfaction and joy out of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rigimarsch 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T20:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another year, another <a href="http://rigimarsch.ch/">Rigimarsch</a>! <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/">Last year</a> I&rsquo;ve participated in an annual night hike up to the Rigi mountain. It was a tough yet exhilerating experience. This year I&rsquo;ve repeated the challenge together with John.</p>

<p>The route was the same as always: 50 or so kilometers with a 1500m ascent in the last 10 kilometeres. However, the hike felt refreshingly different.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/566448675">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>For me personally the hike was a test for the healing Tibia bone that fractured during last year&rsquo;s <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals/">half-marathon in Lausanne</a> (I ran 1/3 of the marathon with a fractured bone).</p>

<p>John looks cheerful but everybody is cheerful at the start:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262027875"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7316/27262027875_338b6e78de_z.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>According to the official information a record 2363 people turned up for the event. Despite the crowd the registration went smoothly. We started walking at around 20:00.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655251944"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7278/26655251944_ef51583b8c.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262034825"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7542/27262034825_1b63a4dd46.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The Rigi mountain. It is intimidating to see the peak far ahead throughout the hike:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26656292463"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7482/26656292463_6e22257b37.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262042505"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7337/27262042505_5bd6972a41.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262043975"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7659/27262043975_f7ddbf3988.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>This year&rsquo;s Rigimarsch took place on May 4th which is relatively early, compared to previous and future years. The event date is tied to Ascension day. Thanks to the early start there was plenty of snow at the top and the night temperatures were quite cool. I wore every piece of clothing I brought along.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655268824"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7360/26655268824_c98e764931.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I felt energized and positive even in the last hours of the challenge. This is a huge departure from last year&rsquo;s impression. I still vividly recall just how difficult last few hours were. I think several factors are at play. First, I&rsquo;m in much better physical shape for aerobic activities because I switched from weight lifting to triathlon. Second, we brought trekking poles with us for the ascent. Finally, I came to the hike completely rested and fresh.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27192498811"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7539/27192498811_04efa1224b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>John is still smiling at the top, that&rsquo;s the way to do it:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655286494"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7711/26655286494_f43a8df2f0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Return train from Rigi to Arth-Goldau. There were enough places in the train for everyone to take a seat:</p>

<p><a href="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7443/27164821172_47541b80f6.jpg"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7443/27164821172_47541b80f6.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The hike took us about 12 hours to complete which is almost the same as last year. However, our moving time is a whole hour shorter which means we walked measurably faster but took longer breaks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bike fitting basics for triathlon and road cycling]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-19T16:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a complete triathlon newbie I benefit tremendously from the experience and knowledge of others. Just a few little steps save years, if not decades, of trial-and-error, not to mention decrease chances of injuries and increase enjoyment of the sport. My friend Ilya Nedbailo who has successfully completed his first 70.3 Ironman in Rapperswil this year generously shared a couple of tips.</p>

<p>The first of which is getting a professional bike fitting service. I strongly believe that money spent on professional advice is worth much more than any piece of gear one may buy. A lot of human knowledge cannot be easily encoded in articles or books. One really needs one-to-one contact and quick feedback to understand the nuances of physical movement.</p>

<p>Ideally, one should do bike fitting before buying a bike. But almost any existing bike will do just fine. It&rsquo;s not unheard of to see people competing in triathlon on rigid mountain bikes. An existing road bike is certainly sufficient.</p>

<p>Choosing the right professional could be tricky, especially when there are many options. I followed Ilya&rsquo;s recommendation and went to a triathlon-focused sport store <a href="https://www.tempo-sport.ch/">Tempo-Sport AG</a> in Thalwil. I&rsquo;m glad I did because René Kuster is an experienced and dedicated counsellor. As someone who participates in the sport himself he went above the mandatory adjustments and explained what is important in the bike position and why. I find such human experience and knowledge vastly superior to impressive computerized tech. Surely a computerized solution yields correct measurements consistently every time. But who will check your pedaling technique, advise on body posture and check that you are using the right muscles when the fancy system is operated by a disinterested or an inexperienced clerk?</p>

<p>Surprisingly, my bike fits me like a glove. Even the stem length is perfect. We got the handlebar height and saddle position adjusted and then installed clip-on aero-bars. Then René explained me how to pull the pedals and told me to utilize core muscles to stabilize the body. In the subsequent training sessions I could really tell the difference: I kept myself in a good position by engaging core (acknowledged by disappearing wrist pain) and I did the pedal pull movement correctly (acknowledged by feeling muscle pain in a previously unknown area).</p>

<p>René has also suggested an upgrade path when I&rsquo;ll get the itch to spend money on improving my cycling performance. His top 3:</p>

<ol>
<li>road-bike specific pedals and shoes (I&rsquo;m currently using a XC combination of Shimano M780 pedals along with Specialized Rime shoes)</li>
<li>tight aero clothing</li>
<li>deep rim racing carbon wheels</li>
<li>everything else</li>
</ol>


<p>Once I got the bike fitted I built myself a &ldquo;cycling training lab&rdquo; at home which I&rsquo;ll explain in a separate post. For the other two disciplines I&rsquo;m going through a similar phase of collecting advice and early error correction. I&rsquo;ll share more as soon as I learn!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A long new journey ahead]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T19:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Training for a half-marathon and then successfully finishing one (although not without an injury) hooked me on pursuing further challenges. I haven&rsquo;t run a half-marathon as a way to prove anything. Rather the competition had given me an opportunity to reassure myself that I&rsquo;m capable of carrying out longer undertakings. Ten weeks from zero to finish has been a fantastic learning experience so I am looking forward to the next step which is not only longer but also more challenging. I am committed to successfully finishing a complete Ironman triathlon (IM) race, that is: consecutively swimming 3.86Km, cycling 180.2Km and running 42.2Km while not dying in the process.</p>

<p>Just few months prior as a part of my life-changing course I have given up a lot of pseudo hobbies that I had never really enjoyed. I basically scrapped everything I did and started fresh. I found out that having just one hobby at a time is surprisingly satisfying. I doubt this is a widespread problem. For me, though, too many hobbies not only spread time and attention really thin but also take away joy. I feel happy to accept triathlon as my only hobby and to say &ldquo;no&rdquo; to anything else that comes my way. It&rsquo;s cheaper this way, too.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen variable amount of craziness across the web and in real life. Some Ironman participants set highly ambitious goals of preparing in shortest time possible. I am not one of them. I want to enjoy the whole process of training and the steady growth, just like I did with running. I had a belief I hate to run. With a little help from patience and discipline I followed a careful plan. And I enjoyed every single run. Not for a moment I thought about the upcoming marathon or what lies ahead. I focused on one and only moment &ndash; the present one.</p>

<p>I intend to piggy-back on the same mindset for IM. A chord of stress has already struck me when I realized that I must rush to prepare myself for the next step: completing a half Ironman next year. As soon as I noticed the fleeting feeling I stopped immediately. I&rsquo;m not going to rush which means I&rsquo;m likely falling out of the 2016 season. I&rsquo;m aiming for an entry into a full IM in 2018. There, I wrote it. I find it REALLY difficult to commit to something so far ahead. But I believe it&rsquo;s going to be yet another fantastic outlet for learning.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile I&rsquo;m going to train and the things get really interesting from here. Unsurprisingly, there is so much information and advice available on the topic that I can&rsquo;t put it in just one entry. So I&rsquo;m going to write semi-regular posts on my training progress and findings. I&rsquo;m completely unfit and unprepared for this challenge right now. I don&rsquo;t even know how to swim properly. But I&rsquo;m excited and looking forward to the long journey ahead!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The wonderful way of carabike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T20:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In September, following a <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/">Fargo rebuild</a> with s Rohloff Speedhub I have went to ride it in Italy. This time, though, I haven&rsquo;t ridden my bike from A to B. Instead, I cheated and went my wife on a car. The revelation that had followed I have succinctly nicknamed &ldquo;car-a-bike&rdquo;.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22802670766"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5719/22802670766_f754cb289e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In a very concrete sense this is a huge departure from self sufficiency that I strive to achieve. However, it&rsquo;s a fantastic motivation for traveling. Usually I don&rsquo;t like visiting cities that much. I consider most kinds of conventional travel unsatisfying. Yet after a difficult day in the saddle it is a joy to take a hot shower, take a nap on a comfy bed and then proceed for an evening stroll in the area followed by a nice dinner.</p>

<p>The car lets you focus on the most difficult and challenging roads. A cycling tour, however, requires careful planning to ensure the route is not too exhausting. Also, to get to the truly exciting parts one needs to cycle through relatively long stretches of uninspiring roads.</p>

<h2>The full cycling itinerary</h2>

<p>Most of the route planning was undertaken by my wife. There&rsquo;s an excellent resource <a href="http://italy-cycling-guide.info/">Italy Cycling Guide</a> which offers loads of routes and suggestions.</p>

<h3>Day 1 (aka Speedhub in Italy)</h3>

<p>I had zero problems with the bike. Test riding and debugging beforehand helped immensely. The gearing on Speedhub along with a 36t felt sufficient for the steepest climbs.</p>

<p>To fit everything into a rented Volvo V60 station wagon I had to disassemble pretty much everything. Having a bike with Rohloff makes it much easier: there&rsquo;s no derailleur sticking out and there&rsquo;s no cable adjustments necessary.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22622541430"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/612/22622541430_d5dacd5eac.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22828655905"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5799/22828655905_91b6e455a9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22797055442"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5762/22797055442_0d8bfc782c.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 77.1km, 1630m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/390769207">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day1.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day1.png" width="120"></a></p>

<h3>Day 2 (aka Riders on the storm)</h3>

<p>Raining cats and dogs for about 2-3 hours. I got completely soaked. Still, getting soaked in summer in Italy is way better than getting soaked along the Rhine river in early spring.</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 86.4km, 1822m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/391527939">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day2.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day2.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 3 (aka The easiest ride in life)</h3>

<p>What was anticipated as another 1800m+ climb day turned out to be a blazing fast descent. The route went from the hills all the way down to the beach. I averaged 26kmh on my Fargo which is a lot more than my usual touring speed of 13-18.</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 67.1km, 26.4kmh average speed (on a Fargo!), <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/392113290">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day3.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day3.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 4 (aka The best 60km of my life)</h3>

<p>Hills and mountains make cycling challenging and painful but so rewarding and addictive. Though I started cycling up mountain passes less than a year ago I can&rsquo;t get enough of it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22797085762"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5811/22797085762_b3dc567372.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22622584440"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/764/22622584440_5f695d6134.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 59.7km, 1954m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/392828417">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day4.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day4.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 5 (aka The final day of biking)</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22392234497"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5640/22392234497_9383cf387f.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 60.6km, 1864m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/393913583">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day5.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day5.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to more of these rides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22640701230"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5770/22640701230_435b7c0896.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22187841494"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/722/22187841494_e0683a1b83.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-31T18:26:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;<strong>I FUCKING DID IT</strong>&rdquo; keeps resonating in my head as I am crossing the finish line. I can already feel latent excruciating pain (amplified by an adrenaline-fueled last half-mile sprint) slowly setting in. Few minutes later I won&rsquo;t be able to walk but at this glorious energizing moment I feel that my whole life is coming together.</em></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how successfully finishing a half-marathon felt to me.</p>

<p>In addition, I hereby completely reverse my opinion of life goals. I used to believe that goals are a sick abomination propagated by clouded minds of semi-religious self-improvement cults. I had my reasons. For one, I couldn&rsquo;t see what&rsquo;s one supposed to do when goals are fulfilled. And most importantly, I couldn&rsquo;t come up with any (&hellip;that I didn&rsquo;t abandon few days/weeks later).</p>

<p>Well, on a sunny day roughly 11 weeks ago I was walking past an advertisement billboard for an upcoming marathon. My mind was clear of stress and worry, thanks to the elapsed three months of sabbatical. Right there, on the spot, I have decided to run it.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m generally fit and sportive I had never run before. Hell, I have always despised running and especially all kinds of competitive events. I used to repeat a cliché: &ldquo;running is wasted time that could otherwise be spent cycling&rdquo;. Successfully finishing a difficult undertaking like that couldn&rsquo;t be achieved in an instant and there was no way to cheat. The instant gratification was out. I knew it was a long path that required disciplined training.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025248504"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5699/22025248504_84a4c75689.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>For the next 10 weeks I adopted a simple training program with 4 runs per week (basically, one of the first results in web search). The distances increased progressively until they winded down few weeks before the race. My first training run was 5km long. I could barely finish it. Thoughts were storming through my mind: &ldquo;how am I supposed to run 21km if 5km is already so difficult&rdquo;. That was my first lesson: don&rsquo;t think about the goal and instead focus on the current step. Every time I trained I focused on finishing just that training, nothing else. Miraculously, I haven&rsquo;t given up once and completed every single training run.</p>

<p>Time went by and the d-day approached. While my mind was calm my body was having some doubts. I could feel an increased heart rate during the days leading to the race. The race took place in Lausanne, French part of Switzerland. The vibe at such events is extremely positive and supportive with both, runners and bystanders, cheering for you.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025252164"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/765/22025252164_58a0ba4662.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The first two thirds of the race went steady. I maintaned a sustainable pace by regularly double-checking my speed on a sports watch. I followed my breath, movements and hydration. Not much else was going through my mind. It was systematic and joyful. In fact, I smiled a lot.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22634485092"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5826/22634485092_9b94d001a9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22460088480"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/670/22460088480_499343801b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>On the 14th kilometer something happened to my left leg. I felt pain in the quad muscle area and began to slow down. The pain was so strong I had to change the way I ran to a very inefficient one. While I lost a minute or more on every kilometer I couldn&rsquo;t imagine facing the intense pain for the last 7 or so kilometers. Even with the new foot strike the pain slowly built up and intensified. I realized that if I stop just for a moment it would be the end of the race. Most likely the legs would swell and I wouldn&rsquo;t resume. So I kept on. Inefficient, painful but persistent. As I got closer to the finish line cheering crowds and music electrified me. Despite the pain I ran faster and faster, approaching a sprinting pace. The joy culminated as I crossed the line. The emotional spike came so strongly to me that I wanted to cry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22659237311"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/616/22659237311_8dd3c46841.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know what exactly happened to my legs. Almost a week later I am still limping but the pain has mostly subsided. I trained carefully and had plenty of long distance runs. I had sufficient nutrition and hydration. I suppose nobody is exempted from risk at such endurance events, even with the best preparation. Once the pain is fully absent I&rsquo;ll surely be back with new goals in mind.</p>

<p>The experience taught a me a couple of invaluable new lessons as well as cemented a few old ones. Like never before, I believe that lessons from sports are relevant to other areas of life.</p>

<p>First, I came to realize that it&rsquo;s important to strive for the difficult and challenging things. It became immediately obvious to me that in the last couple of years I haven&rsquo;t dreamed big enough and settled for things that were easy to imagine. I tended to favor problems for which I already had an idea in my mind. Half-marathon seemed initially impossible to me which made it a clear practical example of what scale of problems to go after. When something seems almost impossible it&rsquo;s worth going after!</p>

<p>Second, as I had already admitted in the opening, I understood the value of setting life goals. It does not matter what kind of goals to choose initially, as long as they are non-trivial. As life generally doesn&rsquo;t have meaning any arbitrary goal might get one going. The success in one area will prepare you for unrelated challenges. Competitive sports offer a great training opportunity.</p>

<p>Third, there&rsquo;s nothing confusing about what to do when goals are complete. In fact, the finite lifespan of goals is very motivating and energizing. Pain and hardship don&rsquo;t last forever. Once you complete the goal it&rsquo;s over. Enjoy the moment and have some rest. Then, choose and go after a new goal!</p>

<p>Finally, when it&rsquo;s too hard to come up with any good meaningful goals it might be a sign that you are purposefully ignoring and supressing your true interests. At least I found myself in such a situation. All the goals I was coming up with ignored my most prominent ambitions and genuine interests. It was hard to face the reality and acknowledge the potential price to pay. That&rsquo;s how comfort zones shrink. It&rsquo;s a slow but sure way to die inside.</p>

<p>Training for and then running a (half)-marathon is potentially a life changing experience but only when the success comes hard and the mind is fertile and open. It didn&rsquo;t come easy to me and I can&rsquo;t appreciate enough everything I have learned and realized.</p>

<p>I am also indebted for the success of my first race to my beloved wife. Without your support and understanding nothing would come out of it. You have a 20% stake in this achievement!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salsa Fargo Mk3 - now with Rohloff!]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-03T18:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I fell in love with a Salsa Fargo bicycle exactly one year ago. The bike made me newly excited about cycling. No wonder I&rsquo;ve put more than 4000 kilometers on it. I never rode the bike stock and rebuilt it with custom parts as soon as I received it by post (frames were out of stock in July last year).</p>

<p>Following the tour around France I decided to change a few things on the bike to better suit the kind of riding that I do:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>install the original rigid carbon fork instead of a suspended RockShox Reba: I did not feel very confident desceding from mountain passes on windy paved roads even with the lock-out engaged; plus, the original fork has bosses for mounting so-called &ldquo;Anything cages&rdquo; for holding drybags</p></li>
<li><p>remove Cane Creek Thudbuster seatpost: I feel annoyed by the occassional squeaking but it is possible I&rsquo;m going to reinstall it if I notice increased fatigue</p></li>
<li><p>install Rohloff Speedhub 14 IGH: while a derailleur system generally works pretty well internally geared hubs have certain advantages which pique my interest</p></li>
<li><p>change tires: 70-80% of riding I do on this bike are on paved surfaces and gravel, it does not make sense to wear out off-road tires and lose efficiency on the asphalt</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This resulted in the 3rd reincarnation of my favorite bike: Salsa Fargo make 3!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20497054903"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5802/20497054903_7e29d55136.jpg" width="333"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20497047673"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5777/20497047673_f30a77b4cf.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>It is often difficult to understand whether certain parts will work together. I hope this information helps you to (re)build your bike.</p>

<p>I filmed the process of breaking down and re-assembling the bike:</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/u7KHGC5LjJQ "></iframe></div>


<h2>Random pieces of wisdom</h2>

<h3>Chainline</h3>

<p>To achieve a completely straight chainline I&rsquo;m using Shimano XT M780 cranks with a Woolftooth 36t narrow-wide single chain ring. I know Middleburn RS8 X-Type Rohloff crank also works but is way too expensive and ugly for my taste. I couldn&rsquo;t confirm if any other (e.g. ethirteen, truvativ) cranks can be run with the right offset.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20931357759"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/747/20931357759_6128e45f3d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h3>Alternator dropout</h3>

<p>Salsa Rohloff alternator dropout works with Rohloff OEM mount. OEM2 plate is not needed. See photo below to understand how the hub/wheel is held in place:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21108031852"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/21108031852_fcaf00487d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h3>Rohloff cable routing</h3>

<p>The external Rohloff gear box can be rotated for the best placement. The Fargo frame has cable guides on the seatstays which allow for 3 cables: rear brake and 2 Rohloff cables.</p>

<h3>Rohloff installation</h3>

<p>The installation is simple. Follow the original instructions. Co-motion provides an excellent HOWTO video for their shifter:</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/O3up1eZT3Pg "></iframe></div>


<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to put oil in! The hub is shipped without sufficient oil inside. A tube of oil is included in the package.</p>

<h3>Removing rear wheel</h3>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t find any information on how hard is to remove the rear wheel when using Rohloff. It is easier than with a derailleur system! First, remove the external gear box. Then, open the quick release axle and slide out the wheel. Done!</p>

<p>When re-installing the wheel put the chain on the rear sprocket and slide the wheel in like on any other bike. No need to break the chain or disengage the drop-outs. It&rsquo;s easier than a derailleur system because it&rsquo;s not necessary to fiddle with the chain to get it on the cassette.</p>

<h3>Mounting E3 tail light on the rear rack</h3>

<p>While the alternator rack does not have holes to install a rear tail light I attached the E3 tail light with a double-sided tape and a couple of plastic zip ties. The cable can be guided along the top tube of the rack.</p>

<h3>Salsa rear rack (non alternator version)</h3>

<p>Non-alternator Salsa rack does NOT fit an alternator-equipped Salsa frame.</p>

<h3>Cockpit housing routing</h3>

<p>It is not trivial to route the brake housing when using Co-Motion drop-bar shifter. It is especially tricky with Supernova handlebar extender. I used a staged approach:</p>

<ol>
<li>leave the stem bolts loose to allow handlebar movement left and right</li>
<li>move Co-Motion shifter onto the bar but don&rsquo;t tighten the bolt yet</li>
<li>install brake levers</li>
<li>install the first part of housing (to the barrel adjusters) and route the right one through Co-Motion shifter</li>
<li>slide the handlebar right and temporarily move Co-Motion shifter as left as possible</li>
<li>tape the right side of the handlebar up to the tapered point of the handlebar</li>
<li>slide Co-Motion shifter to the right; I moved it as far right as the wide diameter of the bar allows it</li>
<li>install Supernova handlebar extender (for mounting the front light on) and route the brake housing through openings</li>
<li>continue as usual</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20495491904"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5816/20495491904_32d8e3b11e_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20930242178"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5782/20930242178_5a68f88e78_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h2>First impressions</h2>

<p>The bike came together cleanly. Salsa designed the Fargo frame around possible Rohloff use. The frame has sufficient cable guides and the Rohloff Alternator dropout is easy to install and use. Adjusting chain tension is straightforward. No need for chain half-links or an eccentric bottom bracket.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21125844901"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/587/21125844901_1e84167b89_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20929989490"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5740/20929989490_1bb98c75c7_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The drivetrain is quiet. It is slightly unusual that shifting under load does not always work and can sometimes temporarily send the hub in the higher gear. The upside is that shifting works in a complete standstill. It will require some getting used to.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20495479424"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/20495479424_e8de8a8285_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The shifter is not indexed. Everything happens inside the hub. The upside is simplicity and higher reliability. The downside is reduced feedback in the shifter. The shifts are felt but are nowhere crisp as they were on the SRAM Red/X0 combination I had before.</p>

<p>All in all I&rsquo;m satisfied with the result. In fact I&rsquo;m going to put a Rohloff on my second adventure bike which is going to be a so-called 31er/29+ Surly ECR. I came back from the test ride with a huge smile on my face. I just fucking love bikes.</p>

<h2>Final build kit</h2>

<p>The full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/albums/72157658151072695">is available on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h3>Frame</h3>

<ul>
<li>Salsa Fargo 2 bomb pop blue 2014 frame</li>
<li>Salsa Carbon Firestarter through-axle</li>
</ul>


<h3>Drivetrain</h3>

<ul>
<li>Rohloff Speedhub 14</li>
<li>Co-Motion drop-bar Rohloff shifter</li>
<li>Shimano 10-speed chain</li>
<li>Chris King bottom bracket</li>
<li>Alternator dropout + single-speed driveside dropout</li>
<li>Shimano XT M780 crankset</li>
<li>Wolftooth 36t single narrow wide chainring</li>
<li>Shimano XT pedals</li>
</ul>


<h3>Wheels</h3>

<ul>
<li>Schwalbe Big Apple 2.35&#8221; tires</li>
<li>SON Schmidt 28 15 dynamo front hub</li>
<li>DT Swiss TK 540 disc rims</li>
</ul>


<h3>Seat</h3>

<ul>
<li>Brook Cambium C17 carved</li>
<li>Thomson Elite seatpost</li>
</ul>


<h3>Cockpit</h3>

<ul>
<li>Salsa Woodchipper handlebar</li>
<li>Salsa Guide stem</li>
<li>Chris King i7 headset</li>
<li>Salsa gel cork tape</li>
<li>Supernova handlebar extension</li>
</ul>


<h3>Brakes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Avid BB7s road brakes</li>
<li>SRAM S900 brake levers</li>
<li>200mm Avid G2CS front rotor</li>
<li>160mm Avid G2CS Rohloff-specific rear rotor</li>
</ul>


<h3>Electronics &amp; accessories</h3>

<ul>
<li>Supernova E3 Pro front light</li>
<li>Rack-mounted Supernova E3 tail light</li>
<li>Salsa Alternator rack</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trip report from bicycle tour across France]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-07T20:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Riding vs buying</h2>

<p>I am amused with the nontrivial amount of invented needs by the bicycle industry as well as the strength of its marketing departments. Each year brings new wheel/tire size standards, new drive-train groupsets and mass-produced lifestyles and attitudes. Suddenly, many enthusiasts desperately realize their need for full-suspension fat bikes with a certain kind of axles for &ldquo;backpacking&rdquo; &ldquo;adventure&rdquo; &ldquo;expeditions&rdquo;. I don&rsquo;t see how bicycle gear obsession is any different from the common consumerism. In the photography world it&rsquo;s called &ldquo;GAS&rdquo; &ndash; gear acquisition syndrome &ndash; which is known to be unconducive to original work.</p>

<p>I am not immune to the disease either. In fact, I have a very heavy case of it. I&rsquo;m obsessed with bikes and bike parts which doesn&rsquo;t land financial wellbeing a huge favor. But the solution is actually pretty simple: just ride the goddamned bike [you already have]!</p>

<p>When I have had photography GAS at one moment I had owned 4 digital cameras. My photographs were not amazing and most of the gear sat idle. Now I own 1 camera and 2 lenses: 35mm and 55mm. I appreciate the limitations and praise the amazing camera body every time I use it. I&rsquo;m definitely not doing any worse than before. If anything, I feel a bit more creative having just 2 prime lenses. It&rsquo;s the same with bikes. I recently caught another potentially expensive itch to get a new bike. And that meant one thing only: not enough saddle time!</p>

<h2>Putting the cranks where my mouth is</h2>

<p>With my diagnosis unambigously established, me and John decided to go for a cure cycling tour across France.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/france-tour.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/france-tour.png" width="1021"></a></p>

<p>Our actual route traced through the following places: <strong>Dijon</strong> &mdash; <strong>Morvan national park</strong> &mdash; <strong>Nevers</strong> &mdash; <strong>Bourges</strong> &mdash; <strong>Saint-Aignan</strong> &mdash; <strong>Tours</strong> &mdash; <strong>Saumur</strong> &mdash; <strong>Nantes</strong> &mdash; <strong>Noirmoutier</strong> &mdash; <strong>Jard-sur-Mer</strong> &mdash; <strong>La Rochelle</strong>. The route incorporated parts of Eurovelo 6 and Eurovelo 1. We rode for 8 days and totaled approximately 1100 Km. The distances across days were spread the following way: <strong>115</strong> &ndash; <strong>108</strong> &ndash; <strong>170</strong> &ndash; <strong>140</strong> &ndash; <strong>155</strong> &ndash; <strong>166</strong> &ndash; <strong>116</strong> &ndash; <strong>119</strong>. We allowed ourselves 8 days to complete it. However, we bought flexible return tickets and had 2 extra days just in case.</p>

<p>Originally, we were thinking of a much grander 2-3 week tour this year in a northern European country. But I&rsquo;m glad we decided against it because we weren&rsquo;t yet ready for potential adversity.</p>

<h2>Our story</h2>

<p>One early Sunday morning I woke-up at 3:55. I had a nice warm breakfast cooked by my dear and understanding wife. I then drove in a rented car to the train station and from there carried my packed bike and panniers across two train stations before meeting John. We then took a train to Basel where we ran with the ultra-uncomfortable heavy Tranzbags across our shoulders to the French part of the train station. I felt slightly nervous because of the french TGV train. Although SNCF (the French train company) clearly states that packed bikes are allowed on all trains I knew enough of the culture to realize we might still have trouble. Gladly we had zero issues and soon enough we arrived in Dijon and unpacked our bikes. I suppose traveling first class has its merits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190464608"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3807/20190464608_e6a225fdb3.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>We bought some snacks at the train station and then some groceries in a Thai shop along the way. We planned our first few days to be the hardest with the most elevation gains. It&rsquo;s better to plan for tough days first while you&rsquo;re still rested and fresh. We learned this the hard way in the last year&rsquo;s Rhine tour. Back then we rode for 30 or so kilometers the first day. And we had to ride until midnight the many days after to compensate for it.</p>

<p>From early on we joined local insignificant roads and cycling paths. We followed beautiful Canal de Bourgogne with its many boats. There were numerous recreational weekend cyclists on the paths close to nearby cities.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755784074"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/465/19755784074_decd610c30.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Once we departed from the canal the scenery abruptly changed into typical rural country-side France: lots and lots of fields and small run-down villages. The scenery reminded me of my home country Latvia. The weather was too perfect to be true: cloudy and around 17C.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190413600"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/261/20190413600_79cd562045_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Our first destination was the Morvan national park. As we got closer our path has led us into forests and unpaved roads. Parts of the roads were washed out. Others had huge trees lying across them so we had to lift our bikes. At times we had to walk. Frankly I didn&rsquo;t anticipate we would need to negotiate such terrain but these challenges set the right adventure spirit early on. Our average speed fell quickly and it was hard to imagine we would do the original 130km planned for the day.</p>

<p>I learned that &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; means different things to Swiss and French. In Switzerland &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; means a finely packed gravel you can ride with a road bike. In France &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; may mean a mud bath, a single-track or an alltogether abandoned path last driven on a grandfather&rsquo;s Land Rover 20 years ago.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20384617841"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/317/20384617841_6ee210343b_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I felt I should have changed my worn tires before this tour but I can only imagine how much worse it was for John who had touring tires without any knobs.</p>

<p>It is amazing how much the scenery changes during the day while cycling. At first the scenery appears to drag on forever. But once the day is over and you look back it&rsquo;s hard to comprehend it all happened in one day. That also presents a challenge for taking photos: nothing seems interesting enough until it&rsquo;s all over. And then you regret not taking enough of shots.</p>

<p>The weather started behaving and we had to wait out a couple of showers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20369920682"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/433/20369920682_26264c1d93.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>At about 18:30 we had to stop cycling because we were soaking wet and shivering from cold. Somehow my original plan of not taking rain-proof gear didn&rsquo;t account for 14C temperature in summer. We were lucky to find a small house and not camp the first night. It would have been a miserable experience. A nearby campsite had a working cafe so we downed a couple of burgers before settling down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352235486"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/448/20352235486_f92b3f8c0b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In the morning we had to wait out a couple of determined showers despite our ambition to leave early and make the most out of the day. This tour taught me patience as ambition in the wrong circumstances is foolish. We stopped at a local grocery store to stock up on food. After a couple of days shopping for groceries became routine. I learned that restaurants and cafes are far from necessary when it&rsquo;s possible to buy varied and fresh food from the local market.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20192163249"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/20192163249_0a62a831cb_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20192166779"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/554/20192166779_14b5d71f6a_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757883033"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19757883033_f5a418d2e9_m.jpg" width="240"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190673638"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/385/20190673638_1fb6dcd2b4_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>There were a couple of lakes along the way but the scenery appeared ominous because of the drizzling rain and gray skies. As the unpaved forest roads made their grand reapperance I became quite worried as you can read from my facial expression:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191863269"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/378/20191863269_a06f4cf6de.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190506138"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/20190506138_946012d336.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I felt anger and anxiety because we were crawling and I didn&rsquo;t plan for such extended terrain contingencies. I was counting on fast packed gravel speedways! Eventually, the skies cleared and we returned to the country-side. We made a decision to divert from the original route and stick to secondary asphalt roads to get to our next target.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378510665"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20378510665_0e62a9bb50.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755836414"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/434/19755836414_06bfcb25cb_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We arrived in a town Nevers and camped in the municipal camp site. We checked the weather forecast in advance to make sure it won&rsquo;t rain or else camping would be a suboptimal choice. It was our first camping night and I was pleasantly surprised it took us only about 20 minutes to set everything up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191886119"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/430/20191886119_3efc34e661_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Sleeping though was an entirely different story. I couldn&rsquo;t fall asleep and felt cold during the night. I was restless and half awake the whole night. I forgot to take ear plugs with me. At least I&rsquo;m glad we had decided to purchase summer sleeping bags. Our original plan was to use silk liners.</p>

<p>We woke up early at 5:20 to make the most of the day as we had seen the forecast predicting rain after 18:00. Something kept me going but sleep deprivation felt miserable. This can be judged by the amount of photos taken during the day: very few.</p>

<p>As we got to a big city Bourges by lunch time we couldn&rsquo;t find a working cycling store because everyone one of the four stores was prematurely closed for a lunch break. John forgot his helmet in the train and needed to get a new one. In the next two hours we purchased groceries and went to a posh burger place. Once we bought a helmet we made a decision to continue for an extra 80 kilometers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755853054"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/356/19755853054_8683722906_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Our progress seemed very slow. The roads were winding up and down slightly and we were going against the wind. In addition, we had taken a somewhat busy road with lots of truck traffic.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190478720"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/281/20190478720_4a234e170f_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>At about 17:00 it predictably started to rain. My spirits were really low because I knew the forecast. We refused to stay in Bourges because that would end the day too early. There were no places to stop between Bourges and our next target. It is a persistent challenge to find accommodation at the right time.</p>

<p>We had to continue despite the rain. The rain wouldn&rsquo;t go away. So we climbed our bikes, wore the wind-proof jackets and pushed on. We soon realized it wasn&rsquo;t so bad. The wind has subsided and the road radiated heat. We were wet but not cold. Our bodies eventually dried our clothes.</p>

<p>Few hours into the ride we called a couple of hotels to book a room so that we have a place to stay when we get to the town late in the evening. At 130-140 kilometer mark we felt energized. I realized it is a very common occurrence. The first 70-100 or so kilometers are the hardest. The first 70 are, in fact, torturous because progress appears too slow.</p>

<p>Admittedly, up to this point I felt similar to how we felt in our previous Rhine tour. Anxious and nervous we&rsquo;re not making enough progress among unexpected difficulties. The tables turned the next day when I felt, for the first time, confidence and freedom from the shackles of our original plan. Our goal is to enjoy the journey and we can alter and change the route in any way we like.</p>

<p>On the following days we got on to route EuroVelo 6 and from there traced the longest French river La Loire. To take the shortest path we used Google Maps directions and a micro SD slot on my phone to create a GPX track that can be swallowed by Garmin.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757620813"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19757620813_2a3a7ce575_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190496210"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3769/20190496210_a0ca74be9d_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>The scenery offered views on splendid bridges over La Loire and its many castles.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755932284"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/260/19755932284_5e72621630_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191955409"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/331/20191955409_25370d9e47_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20384749161"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/444/20384749161_cfa7653ddf_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The larger French cities, such as Bourges or Nantes appeared surprisingly industrial.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352310756"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/369/20352310756_b9f046df00_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352384086"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/468/20352384086_688f768bd1_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We got into a habit of arriving somewhat late to the campsites. Most of the receptions close at 18:00. We basically had to trespass, find empty pitch spots and then pay in the morning upon departure. This made the staff quite confused. But finishing our days at 18:00 or so seemed too early. As we didn&rsquo;t cook dinner there wasn&rsquo;t much to do. Why stay bored in the campsite when we can be enjoying the road?</p>

<p>We caught up with the planned schedule in Nantes. But once we have got there we decided to take a train to La Rochelle to make the last few days easier. I am so glad that the morning train was full and we decided against it! Instead, we continued EuroVelo 6 route to the coast of the Atlantic ocean and then continued South through EuroVelo 1. The road along the ocean has quickly overshadowed everything we cycled so far. To make the last few days easier we decided to take a train from La Rochelle to Bordeaux thinking that we&rsquo;ve seen enough of French country side roads.</p>

<p>Pine trees, the smell of open water and white sand reminded me of my home country once more: it was like a bigger and better version of Jurmala. Our first day along the coast stretched late into the evening because we have run into a few problems. Namely, the road to an island we hoped to take was flooded that time of the day, we have ridden into a dead end trying to take another road and we lost each other. The reward was one of the most beautiful sunsets I have ever seen.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19756050324"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/528/19756050324_a5a3a86ed8_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352477786"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3695/20352477786_c6ef2586f1_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19756058424"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/560/19756058424_566d9388f7_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352483906"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/407/20352483906_298bf3f6b0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Camping (unathorized, as usual) on the Noirmoutier island was fantastic. In the morning I discovered a flat rear tire which was promptly fixed:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190685130"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/305/20190685130_742f00a4e4_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378747705"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/468/20378747705_4307880bd4_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>We continued along the coast until we reached La Rochelle. There were a few resort towns along the way which made me panic. I don&rsquo;t like crowded places. We breezed through them quickly. On the weekend cycling paths were crawling with beachgoers. Cycling in the early hours of the day was much better. There are also annoying obstacles, such as gates, to slow the cyclists down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20370219732"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/437/20370219732_f34afd8105_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757824133"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/365/19757824133_b811dbda41_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757863073"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/384/19757863073_2f9ae1edbf_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190820048"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/348/20190820048_e660b17120.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757891663"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/371/19757891663_db6e7eeb50.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378822715"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/557/20378822715_5899351d4e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190768350"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/502/20190768350_bdd1a58d8b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Once we arrived in La Rochelle we cycled across an enormous bridge to the Isle of Rhé and bathed in the ocean.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190837468"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/434/20190837468_ddf9a1b4c5.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20370279592"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/449/20370279592_cd45c78dbc_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>The full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/sets/72157654009464044">is available on Flickr</a>. Links to the individual day tracks in strava: <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743564">8</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743578">7</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743583">6</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743582">5</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366746443">4</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743556">3</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743543">2</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743544">1</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Across France on a bicycle]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T19:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following numerous episodes of soul searching I finally came to realize that enjoy cycling more than an average person. While I enjoy many flavors of it, such as road cycling and mountain down-hill riding my absolute favorites are endurance and touring rides.</p>

<p>My dream is to visit as many places on a bicycle as I could. Somehow biking[1] feels to me just the right way to explore the world. Last year I joined my very first cycling tour along the river Rhine. That tour had its ups and downs. I learned a lot and wrote about the lessons in earlier posts. <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">post1</a> <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">post2</a></p>

<p>This year me and John are expanding our comfort zones. While we&rsquo;re still within the safe confines of Europe we&rsquo;re not going for hotel accommodation. Instead, we&rsquo;re going to camp. Hopefully, we will learn new lessons and don&rsquo;t repeat the previous mistakes. Step by step we make our tours more challenging and more exciting.</p>

<p>Our destination this year is Northern and Western France. We&rsquo;re starting off from city Dijon to which get by a high-speed train. French TGVs disallow  assembled bikes onboard so we had to purchase so-called TranZBags and partly disassemble our bikes (note that I leave the tent attached to the bike):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20008244211"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3673/20008244211_5f2ddde0f4_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>To fit the bike comfortably inside the bag I took extra steps and removed the seat-post and pedals. That should also minimize the risk of broken spokes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19380398634"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/294/19380398634_2e95a27719_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I hope we won&rsquo;t have problems. Just in case we purchased 1st class tickets expecting fewer passengers and fewer confrontations.</p>

<p>From the outset our gear list is much shorter than last year which is plenty remarkable as we haven&rsquo;t camped and instead stayed in hotels and hostels. Here&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m bringing:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19816344399"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/359/19816344399_5c8e06b5f9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<ul>
<li>bike repair kit (napkin, pump, spare tube, 2x multi tool, leatherman knife, tape, zip ties, plastic gloves, chain bits)</li>
<li>flexible bike lock</li>
<li>TranZBag (for transporting bicycle on trains)</li>
<li>2x 60g tubes of chamois cream</li>
<li>3x packs of hydration tables</li>
<li>swimming trunks</li>
<li>hiking towel</li>
<li>inflatable sleeping mat</li>
<li>compact summer sleeping bag</li>
<li>cash wallet</li>
<li>15000mah portable battery</li>
<li>passport</li>
<li>bank access code generator</li>
<li>head torch</li>
<li>notebook and pen</li>
<li>Garmin 62s and one set of spare batteries</li>
<li>credit card wallet</li>
<li>leg warmers</li>
<li>phone</li>
<li>one extra cycling shirt</li>
<li>ultra-light wind-proof jacket (packed into red sack)</li>
<li>one extra cycling bibs</li>
<li>arm warmers</li>
<li>one extra set of socks</li>
<li>medicine</li>
<li>compact digital camera (not shown)</li>
</ul>


<p>This is the stuff I&rsquo;m going to wear on me (helmet is not shown):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19815037210"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/396/19815037210_82c57f6492_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>This time I&rsquo;m not taking any kind of rain gear because it is pointless in summer heat. I&rsquo;m also not taking any food. Instead, we&rsquo;ll scout for grocery stores along the way.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t publish anything during the ride but I&rsquo;ll keep some notes for a report upon our return. Wish us good luck!</p>

<p>[1] walking, hiking, climbing are the other preferred means</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountaineering in Valais]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-10T15:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There comes a moment in a life of a dormant adventurer when the curtains of undesired comfort are torn away and the world is finally seen through wide-open eyes, fueled by challenge and gore, excitement and joy. In this very moment feelings of inadequacy and out-of-placeness give way to sincere enthusiasm and appreciation and beauty of the world. I am boundlessly joyful to cross that imaginary line and thirstily imbibe from the cup of mountaineering and alpine beauty.</p>

<p>Such life-changing shift of perception comes from just a single adventure that I have had the tremendous luck to be a part of. Last Saturday I joined company of JD, Samuel and Clément to trek for 5 days through a mountain range in the French canton Valais of Switzerland, through ice, snow and rock. In the best tradition of Sergey the journey has been one of the hardest things he has ever done in his life.</p>

<h2>Preparation (lack of thereof)</h2>

<p>An invitation to join the expedition came from my friend JD unexpectedly following the 420km bicycle challenge that I completed few weeks ago. I knew JD went on awesome mountaineering trips before so I had repeatedly pestered him to invite me next time he goes. Over a phone call he congratulated me on the achievement and casually mentioned that he&rsquo;s going on a 5-day mountaineering trip and wondered if I may be interested. I suspect he did not expect my overeager enthusiasm nor participation.</p>

<p>But contrary to my outer timidity I immediately lit up with excitement in my mind like a deranged gasoline-soaked martyr. Though I could satisfactory climb in the gym I knew very little about mountaineering: what to bring, what to wear, how to navigate glaciers and snow, how and why to use the rope, what to do with the ice axe and when to wear the crampons. Nor did I have much time to fill the gaps. Instead, I trusted experience of my companions and hesitated very little to ask stupid questions.</p>

<p>Since the invitiation was on a short notice there have been only a couple of available days between other trips. JD and me went to a climbing gym once to practice ropes and lead climbing so that I could demonstrate my satisfactory skill and both of us could get a warm-up.</p>

<p>While I already own a relatively impressive set of outdoor equipment I lacked essential items required for mountaineering. Specifically, my supposedly bad-ass high-cut hiking boots were unsuitable for crampons due to excessive flexibility. So I had to get a new pair of steel-stiff shoes. I also had to purchase: an ice axe (plus a blade protector so that I didn&rsquo;t accidentally murder a bystanding old lady in a train), crampons (plus a protector bag so I didn&rsquo;t rip my backpack open) and an ice screw (existence of which puzzled me at first). Initially I felt that all the stuff is excessive. However, as soon as we hit the high-altitude track usefulness of every piece of gear became readily apparent.</p>

<p>I am proud to not only have carried the required gear but also to not have brought too much unnecessary bits and bobs. I erred on the side of bringing too little. So I had only one set of everything which sounds slightly unhygienic and off-putting. The arguably good thing about mountains is that there are very few connoisseurs and, in general, people.</p>

<h2>Day 1: from Arolla to Cabane des Vignettes (3200m)</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653806"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-1.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 5.82km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 1101m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 57m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 4:01&#8217;45.1</p>

<p>We met 8 in the morning and went on a 4-hour car ride to the town of Arolla (2006m) from which we needed to climb to our first hut &ldquo;Cabane des Vignettes&rdquo; (3157m).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19396916240"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/454/19396916240_7204d49735.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558716196"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/288/19558716196_003a5f463e_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>After consulting with my experienced companions I have unloaded 10% of gear and learned how to correctly attach an ice axe to a backpack (the photo shows incorrect axe placement).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962326704"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3677/18962326704_eae7247a8c_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962368554"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/295/18962368554_034e6e971c_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18964030073"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/467/18964030073_73487bb76b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Most of the way on the first day was hiking. The first 300-400 vertical meters felt really tough and in my head I wondered whether I will ever make it. Fortunately, my experience from all other difficult activities told me to ignore the first steps. First steps are always hard. I don&rsquo;t know if the body adjusts or the mind changes perception. When it gets really hard I look one step ahead and keep my head down not to see just how high our destination is. At some point the moves got automatic: step, breathe, step, panic, step, breathe, step, ad nauseam. As little thinking as possible. These moments of utter concentration are a total blessing compared to anxiety-induced modern existence.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19584905205"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/339/19584905205_e10e6cb348_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398332399"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/364/19398332399_faebdd746a_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578027852"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3742/19578027852_3508a5344b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>After 600m of climbing the body adjusted sufficiently that I did not feel like I&rsquo;m going to faint. Relief. I felt surprisingly comfortable in the new stiff shoes though I held no illusions about upcoming blisters: new shoes are always a bad idea.</p>

<p>At some point we approached snow and I got my first taste of mountaineering. We got all roped together. The rope is a safety device against a risk of hidden crevasses (cracks in the ice). Crevasses themselves are not that dangerous because you can see them and avoid them (or jump over) but when crevasses are hidden underneath the snow you could accidentally fall through. That&rsquo;s when your buddies are going to pull you out. As the least experienced I was put second, the most experienced went to the front and the end of our life-saving connection. We kept about 10m of rope between each other. It&rsquo;s important to keep the rope sufficiently tight so that in an event of a fall the rope does not create a too strong of a jerk.</p>

<p>We then slogged through snow until we reached our first hut. Crampons (I much prefer the Russian word for it, &ldquo;kittens&rdquo;) were not necessary yet because the snow was slushy. Crampons are useful when the snow is hard or icy. I closely followed the footsteps of Clément because sliding sideways and falling wastes precious energy. I learned how to hold an ice axe and what is it for. An ice axe is mainly a stability and a braking device. An ice axe is held against the slope. It is also an effective brake when you&rsquo;re either sliding down a slope or your comrade is falling in a crevass. The lower part of an ice axe is used the most: an ice axe is like a hiking pole. You don&rsquo;t use an ice axe crazily swinging it around. So I was a bit disappointed because of that. I still had no idea what an ice screw was for.</p>

<p>On the way to the hut an ambitious Swiss duo accidentally injured JD by sticking an ice axe into his leg. I really can&rsquo;t think of a way you accidentally stick an ice axe into someone&rsquo;s leg but the person apologized at the top and gave his contact information so that he could pay for mending JD&rsquo;s brand new pair of mountaineering trousers. Fortunately, the damage to the leg was limited to a couple of nasty scratches.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558789636"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/354/19558789636_6bfe198ce6_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Reaching the hut rewarded us with splendid views on the surrounding peaks and glaciers though, as I learned later, the views are not what mountaineering and hiking are all about.</p>

<p>Views from the hut area, note The Bishop (l&#8217;évêque) peak close to the left edge &ndash; we ascended it on the second day:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398402569"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/523/19398402569_e05be53d23_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558817716"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/437/19558817716_6fe36b8686.jpg" width="500"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589304621"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/439/19589304621_cbfb9dc2a0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I have never stayed in a mountain hut before. Swiss mountain huts are impressively equipped. Some of the huts even offer microbrewery beers. Prices reflect the difficulty of bringing the stuff up to high altitudes. Normally, a hut provides a bunk bed, breakfast and dinner. The food was delicious: a thick minestrone soup followed by pasta bolognese. Mountain food is high on calories because climbing mountains ain&rsquo;t easy.</p>

<p>Overall, I found the experience of the first day highly reminiscent of any other challenge I had faced in my life. Looking back I am astonished at how transferable are the skills of sports to everyday adversities. I made a mental note to look back at physical challenges in search of answers and motivation next time I run up against a wall of life&rsquo;s conundrums.</p>

<h2>Day 2: The Bishop climb (3707m)</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653815"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-2.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 10.87km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 882m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 865m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 7:04&#8217;38.7</p>

<p>Mountains run on their own time. I coin this peculiar phenomenon &ldquo;mountain time&rdquo;. Normal people wake up at 7 or 8. Mountain people, though, finish with their breakfast at 4 and are all packed up ready to go at 4:30. And I used to think I am an early riser&hellip; The reasons have to do with weather conditions and snow. It&rsquo;s better to have extra time for unexpected adversity than to get stuck in the dark. I&rsquo;ve been told that if it&rsquo;s 6pm and you&rsquo;re still out there you are clearly red lining and in very real danger.</p>

<p>Actually the second day was a bit of luxury as we had breakfast at 4:30 and left the hut at 5:15. Our goal was a peak called &ldquo;The Bishop&rdquo; (l&#8217;évêque) which was clearly seen from the hut the day before. There is another mountain phenomenon I call &ldquo;mountain scale&rdquo;. Apparently, human brain cannot judge the sheer vastness of mountains and the perception of distance is seriously distorted. Mountains seem much closer than they really are and only with some points of reference can the real size be understood. For example, tiny humans (that seems more like ants) put things into perspective.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398433189"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3771/19398433189_e2ff6eb29d_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397041088"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3731/19397041088_fd6f06b0f6_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t grasp how far The Bishop was. The first part of the ascent was very difficult for me. My body still haven&rsquo;t fully adapted to walking up with a heavy backpack. At some point I felt taste of blood in my mouth (seems similar to taste of metal). It&rsquo;s a sign that I&rsquo;m doing an honest exercise. The second part was much steeper but felt easier due to short rhythmic movements. We wore crampons from the start as the snow was just in the right shape for them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398450589"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/539/19398450589_b30335ca48_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>The final part of the ascent involved an easy rock climbing section. Grabbing rock edges and moving above thousands of meters is breathtaking. At 09:00 we reached the top of The Bishop (3707m). At the top I learned another unusual fact about mountaineering and hiking. I thought we&rsquo;re going to marvel at the surroundings for hours so just to confirm my obvious expectation I asked Sam how long are we going to stay at the summit. He answered briefly: &ldquo;about 10 minutes&rdquo;. After an awkward pause I calmly said: &ldquo;So we had climbed for 4 hours up. We stay on the summit for 10 minutes. Then we climb down for another 3 hours. Is this a fair summary of what we&rsquo;re doing?&rdquo;. Obviously, there&rsquo;s a reason. It&rsquo;s better to go back as soon as possible because the weather is somewhat unpredictable and snow gets slushy quickly. Climbing, mountaineering, hiking are not about the summit (goal). It&rsquo;s more about the journey itself.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19585025825"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/401/19585025825_ddb4549644_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589341891"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3681/19589341891_59ba03ff6f_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578145332"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19578145332_180cb7d095_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Panorama from the top of The Bishop:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589363141"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3711/19589363141_dc2817975f_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>On the way back I ran out of water. I had 1.5L with me which was clearly not enough. That whole time I was dreaming of an ice cold bottle filled with sparkling water. On subsequent days I&rsquo;ve squeezed in 2.5L of water. As you imagine, on those days I had more than 1L left. And I finally earned two big blisters at the back of my heels. As I said, new shoes are always a bad idea.</p>

<p>We got back to the hut at about noon. Clément went down to Arolla with another group as he was joining us only for a weekend. We ordered a portion of Rösti which was served on a single plate and looked MASSIVE:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18964181283"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/540/18964181283_7d89bccb8c_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>Each of us took a shower that costs almost as much as a service of a prostitute (6CHF/minute). We then slept from about 14:00 till 16:30. It felt great. We played French scrabble with English words. It felt less great. At 18:30 we had dinner similar to the one the day before though it was complemented with Cordon Bleus. There were only 4 more guests besides us that night. The Vignettes hut has capacity for about a hundred.</p>

<p>Once again I was puzzled to observe that most mountaineers stayed indoors and slept pretty much the whole day. Why do you wake up at 4, climb non-stop for 7-10 hours (leaving no more than 10 minutes to awe at the scenery) and then recess inside from the sun feeling bored? I suppose I&rsquo;m too green to know the answer yet.</p>

<h2>Day 3: Pigne d&#8217;Arolla (3788m) and Cabane des Dix</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653818"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-3.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 8.88km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 791m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 1028m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 5:36&#8217;58.3</p>

<p>The day started a bit earlier. Our goal of the day was to climb peak Pigne d&#8217;Arolla and then get to the next hut Cabane des Dix. The third day felt markedly easier and I could enjoy the process and pay attention to the surroundings. Walking up became more natural. Rope and an axe became my perfect accomplices. The route was also slightly easier than on the days before.</p>

<p>Cabane des Vignettes seen from afar:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578208872"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/407/19578208872_86d6d197aa_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397137400"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/551/19397137400_d684f28ee1_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558936076"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/525/19558936076_7c4b7b1802_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397145808"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19397145808_340b94e192_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962590944"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/343/18962590944_d6d60d0e13_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>On the way I couldn&rsquo;t stop noticing dormant insects in the snow and ice. How do the insects get there? What&rsquo;s their story? I also wondered what do the blackbirds feed on at such high altitudes. I suppose on those very insects.</p>

<p>I realized that 3 weeks have passed since I left my job. These 3 weeks felt like a year, full of adventure and new experiences. Despite the spike of energy and enthusiasm I felt that a short vacation cannot heal the damage from long-term stress. I am not yet ready to get back into the professional world. I am glad I had an opportunity to discuss my departure plans with a healthcare professional who shared valuable pieces of wisdom. One of the pearls is to plan at least a 6 month retreat. Otherwise you are almost guaranteed to run into the same issues that plagued you.</p>

<p>We finished our day quite early: at 10:45 we reached the hut. The rest of the day was spent either sleeping, reading or eating. I saw a massive serac separate from the mountain top and go down with a loud bang.</p>

<p>Admittedly, the food in Dix was worse than in Vignettes: blander and less of it. Though Dix offered a nice selection of Belgian-style beers and their paid lunch-time food offerings were delicious.</p>

<p>Cabane des Dix upclose:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962604874"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/450/18962604874_5e03521122_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<h2>Day 4: Mont Blanc Cheilon climb (3850m)</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653814"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-4.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 11.63km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 1189m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 1165m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 9:24&#8217;38.7</p>

<p>Dix served breakfast at 4 so we woke up at 3:40. By the fourth day I got used to waking up at 4 and going to bed at 8. I felt rested and fresh. I was also pretty certain that I handle altitude sickness pretty well. I felt no major headache and felt sufficiently energized.</p>

<p>We left the hut in the darkness, head torches illuminating our way. Far away in the distance I could see groups of alpine fireflies wrestling their way up. They must have left the hut even earlier. JD forgot to take water. Luckily he realized it soon enough.</p>

<p>The pre-dawn sky was illuminated by lightnings, another majestic spectacle of nature. The day started windy and cold. The wind on the north face of the mountain added fierceness and a hardcore atmosphere to our ascent. By all measures the longest and hardest day lay ahead.</p>

<p>Following a long stretch of snow lay an icy surface. I looked at Sam to see why did he stop and what he was doing. It was about the time I learn what an ice screw is for. Sam screwed the ice screw into the surface of the ice and attached a quick-draw to it and then routed his rope through the quick-draw. The edifice served as a stability and safety device. Basically, an ice screw serves a belaying purpose and protects a climber in a case of a fall. As the last person in the group, JD has undone the ice screw and put it into this backpack. Permanently leaving expensive equipment in the ice ain&rsquo;t cool.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589486631"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19589486631_b2b4f9d0ea_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589511721"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/353/19589511721_b9bb748abb.jpg" width="333"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397268730"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/559/19397268730_228be73498.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>We approached the rock and took off crampons. The final 100 or so meters involved climbing up the rock ridge. The experience of climbing at almost 4000 meters is very different from climbing at the gym. For one, the mountaineering shoes are not as responsive and trustworthy as the climbing shoes. Second, the backpack is heavy and restricts some of the movements. There were a couple of moves when we had to take the backpacks off and pass them on.</p>

<p>I added a couple of scratches to my helmet as it saved my head from numerous concussions hitting the rock during some of the moves. What a fantastic piece of equipment a helmet is!</p>

<p>The climb felt like an eternity. I can&rsquo;t say I was afraid of the heights or falling down but there were a couple of really gnarly moves when I hesitated a little. At 9:24 we reached Mont Blanc de Cheilon (3850m). Sitting on the calm south face, I ate some gummy bears and nuts to replenish my energy reserves. I congratulated my companions on the successful ascent. Despite minor annoyances we have been extremely lucky to have almost the perfect weather conditions the whole 5 days.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19585219335"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3754/19585219335_2fe7b60b2c_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Going down proved to be harder than climbing up. My brain was really tired from finding paths between the untrustworthy rock. I could barely understand what I was doing. I felt anger and exhaustion building up. Hard moves were actually easier because my muscles had plenty of capacity. My mind was the real bottleneck. I was glad once the rock section was over. That moment I knew that it&rsquo;s all downhill from there.</p>

<p>On the way back Sam said it would be nice to practice slides on the slope to learn to properly use an ice axe for emergency braking. We were away from the dangerous parts and had our crampons packed. I made a false move and slipped on a patch of ice. Before I realized I was picking up speed and sliding down. Instinctively, I grabbed the axe and tried to stop. Miraculously, I stopped just a few meters short of a fall to a large piece of rock. Sam and JD thought I did that intentionally. They thought I&rsquo;m an impatient learner. The effective technique is to push the axe with both hands into the slope while trying to stand up. I accidentally slipped again so I had yet another opportunity to practice. I said, of course, that the second incident was absolutely intentional and totally controlled.</p>

<p>We were back in the hut at 14:00. I felt really tired and relieved. We had a delicious French crouton with cheese and egg. It was our last day in the mountains so we hoped to take night-time photos of the starlit sky. Unfortunately, thunderstorms came at 20:00 and we ran out of patience to wait for the skies to clear. Instead, we made the best use of the dusk-lit clouds and dramatic light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398682479"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/343/19398682479_98312e60f3_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Day 5: back to Arolla</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653828"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-5.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 8.11 km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 168m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 1010m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 3:24&#8217;19.3</p>

<p>On our final day we woke up at 7. The way back was a piece of cake compared to what we had done on the days before. We crossed small rivers and snow patches and climbed the Pas de Chèvres before trekking down to Arolla.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397321700"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/286/19397321700_470f7acc47_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18964367173"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/340/18964367173_08c9d2c877_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589594251"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/368/19589594251_0994e0f921_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397321168"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/449/19397321168_fda2b71b93_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578416842"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/381/19578416842_e77c44ed23_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Panorama from <em>Pas de Chèvres</em> before we descend back to Arolla:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397352200"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/305/19397352200_8a7d5fb815_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Panorama on the way back to Arolla:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578454902"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/542/19578454902_c9d1b3405e_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>A nice surprise at the parking lot, just in time for a zombie apocalypse:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962778214"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/463/18962778214_e357672b0c_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962783654"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3819/18962783654_cebba175c2_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<h2>Conclusion and final thoughts</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say I had lived in a box. I can&rsquo;t say I hadn&rsquo;t traveled. I can&rsquo;t say I hadn&rsquo;t seen and hadn&rsquo;t been to mountains before. But nothing comes close to the feeling of utter completness and rightness of going through grueling icy and rocky treks up to the peaks and through open vastness of alpine space. Never before I felt so much satisfaction from traveling and exploring the world. For the first time in my life I felt I&rsquo;m doing the right thing and for the first time I felt I couldn&rsquo;t care less about what others are doing. It has been another hardest but greatest thing in my life. I feel infinitely grateful for such a wonderful opportunity to JD, Samuel and Clément. I found the perfect way to explore this beautiful world!</p>

<p>To see all pictures <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/sets/72157655293226359">head over to the Flickr album</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going to a first alpine tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T20:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m feeling excited because tomorrow I&rsquo;m going on my first alpine tour. It&rsquo;s a 5 day tour and we&rsquo;re going to walk on ice and snow. We&rsquo;re heading to region Valais which is not far from Mont Blanc that I had visited earlier this week.</p>

<p>Although I already have relatively lots of mountain/climbing gear I had to purchase new stiff boots and other stuff. Packing is in progress:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19388461925"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19388461925_fbfcdc2fa9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s hope for good weather and some nice shots!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
