<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-12T17:57:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Kata of Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-12T15:28:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A fancy word makes even the most mundane things sound legitimate. Enter &lsquo;kata&rsquo; &mdash; a fancy way of saying that one does something mundane, regularly. Originally, the Japanese word &lsquo;kata&rsquo; stands for a very specific kind of practice in traditional arts. But in the programming world it&rsquo;s synonymous with a repetitive coding practice. I have no opinion in the linguistic department but I believe the practice might have some substance. Let me rewind a little bit.</p>

<p>Exactly one year ago I <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/">left a wonderful job in one of the best places to work</a> on this planet. With such a drastic move there&rsquo;s a multitude of reasons. One of the major ones is my ambition to become an excellent software engineer and steer away from the technical support role I had so far pursued.</p>

<p>The first obstacle on the way are the well-known and sometimes wacky software interviews that most respectable companies seem to rely on for choosing among candidates. To prepare myself for the challenge I devised a multi-month plan. About 3 months ago, as I was done with another full-time endeavour, I put the plan through its paces. In this article I&rsquo;ll do my best to explain the first step of the plan &mdash; the study and practice of algorithms and data-structures.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not like I&rsquo;ve never studied algorithms. In fact, I hold a computer science degree and have completed several excellent online algorithm-focused courses with top marks (<a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partI">Algorithms Part I</a>, <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partII">Algorithms Part II</a>). But annoyingly if you had asked me to implement a path-finding algorithm or even an O(N*LogN) sorting algorithm I would have struggled without referring to technical books or articles. Should you have asked the same question straight after I had just completed the courses I would have absolutely no issues. From a limited personal survey of fellow engineers it is a very common situation. Few keep algorithms in their heads.</p>

<p>Clearly, without an excellent understanding of algorithms passing a coding interview is unlikely. Besides, algorithms and data structures are the cornerstones of computer science and software. Without the understanding of basic structures it&rsquo;s not possible to solve most of the coding challenges. So I dedicated the first month of preparation to the study of algorithms.</p>

<p>However, as I&rsquo;ve already learned, the chosen method of study is critical. It&rsquo;s all to easy to complete a course or a book and then forget everything few weeks after. It is also not sufficient to merely browse through a book or a bunch of articles. Superflous reading creates a perilous illusion of understanding. It is imperative to work through. That&rsquo;s why going through one algorithms book takes a month of full-time effort and not an afternoon. I also emphasize that I had completed algorithm courses before starting this effort. Otherwise, it would make sense to study through the online courses mentioned above first. It would also significantly lengthen the plan.</p>

<p>As there are many more algorithms than the time available to me I had to optimize. It makes little sense to study the most esoteric and domain-specific algorithms for the purpose of preparing for software interviews. I made a survey of interview-related Q&amp;As and websites and came up with the following initial list of algorithms and data structures (in no particular order):</p>

<pre><code>* Stack/Queue (based on LinkedList)
* Selection Sort
* SeparateChainingHashST
* LSD/MSD sort (Radix)
* Graph/Digraph/WeightedGraph
* Edge/EdgeWeightedGraph
* DFS/BFS
* Binary Search
* Weighted Quick Union
* Insertion Sort
* Shell Sort
* DFSPaths/BFSPaths
* Cycle detection in undirected graph
* Connected Components with DFS in undirected graph
* Bipartite check in undirected graph (two color)
* Merge Sort
* Bottom-up Merge Sort
* Quicksort
* 3-way Quicksort
* CountSort
* Min/MaxPQ
* Heapsort
* BST
* Red-black BST
* LinearProbingHashST
* Cycle detection in directed graph
* DFS order and Topological sort
* Kosaraju-Sharir Strong Connected Components in directed graph
* Kruskal MST
* Prim MST
* Dijkstra SP
* Acyclic SP
* Bellman-Ford SP
* Knuth-Morris-Prath search
* Boyer-Moore search
</code></pre>

<p>It is debatable if some of the algorithms in this list are already too complex for general software engineering interviews (knowledge of esoteric algorithms might be required for more senior or specialized roles). In fact, as practice went by I added a few additional ones and removed a few.</p>

<p>The book I chose for my study is &ldquo;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-4th-Robert-Sedgewick/dp/032157351X">Algorithms, 4th edition</a>&rdquo; from Robert Sedgewick at Princeton University. It&rsquo;s written by the same professor that teaches the corresponding online courses. What sets it apart from other famous algorithm texts is the focus on visually illustrating algorithms and doing algorithm-tracing exercises. Working through an algorithm on paper and tracing all the steps helps to grasp what the algorithm really does. Through these exercises I uncovered that my mental models for some of the algorithms were wrong. The other huge benefit of this book is a <a href="http://algs4.cs.princeton.edu/">complementary codesite</a> with lots of high-quality and clearly-written implementations of algorithms in Java.</p>

<p>My daily routine consisted of reading about one topic and related algorithms and then trying to re-implement the algorithms myself. As soon as I stumbled I looked-up the text. The complementary code is extremely readable. The implementations may lack some of the fanciest and trickiest optimizations but are invaluable tools for learning. Once I implemented the code I erased and started from scratch, testing thoroughness of my understanding.</p>

<p>As the days went by and I progressed further I felt that I no longer remembered the details of algorithms I had already worked-through. That&rsquo;s when I decided to introduce additional regular algorithm coding practice &mdash; katas. I grouped some of the algorithms together. Then during each practice session I would implement algorithms and data-structures from the top of my head, copying only test cases from the reference implementation. At times I would get stuck. In those moments I learned a little bit more about each algorithm. Often, I would get confused and need to look-up the reference implementation. Next time, though, the practice would become easier and more automatic. Katas keep the algorithm knowledge functional and fresh. Furthermore, being able to implement some of the tricky algorithms from the top of my head on a napkin increases confidence which may sometimes shake under the many stresses of interviews. Finally, being able to implement many algorithms quickly pays off in coding competitions.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know if the original katas are canonical. My coding katas are certainly not. They evolve and change with time. At some point easier algorithms and data-structures become trivial and it no longer makes sense to practice them. I don&rsquo;t practice writing a stack/queue anymore. Sometimes I realize how similar few algorithms are so I leave one of them out. Many graph problems reduce to DFS. Occasionally I study through new algorithms and add them to katas. For example, I&rsquo;ve recently added SkipList and SuffixArray. I also group algorithms so that each kata is of similar size. At the moment I have <a href="https://github.com/drseergio/practice/tree/master/katas">5 katas in my repertoire</a>. It takes about 30-60 minutes to complete each one. I aim to complete all of the katas once a week &mdash; on average less than one kata per day. I&rsquo;m also timing my practice now to see how long each kata takes.</p>

<p><strong>Here&rsquo;s a distilled version of the algorithm study plan (~1 month of full-time effort)</strong>:</p>

<ol>
<li>List algorithms/data-structures you need to learn deeply. When in doubt leave it out. Make it as short as feasible. Can always add more later.</li>
<li>Choose an algorithms text. I recommend <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Algorithms-4th-Robert-Sedgewick/dp/032157351X">&ldquo;Algorithms, 4th edition&rdquo; by Robert Sedgewick</a>.</li>
<li>Schedule sufficient time each day to read the text and implement algorithms by hand. Keep premature enthusiasm at hand and keep the workload manageable. There&rsquo;s a reason it takes a month.</li>
<li>Collect algorithm implementations and group them into katas.</li>
<li>Regularly perform katas by reimplementing algorithms.</li>
<li>Revise katas, remove trivial algorithms and add new ones as you see fit.</li>
<li>Repeat 6, 7.</li>
</ol>


<p>I&rsquo;d like to believe that this study of algorithms and practice of katas will pay off. It is hard to say, taking into account the many factors that affect a hiring decision. Doing a comprehensive study like this won&rsquo;t guarantee success but doing nothing almost certainly guarantees failure. The study of algorithms is just the first interview preparation step. I&rsquo;ve introduced katas as means to not forget what I&rsquo;ve just learned. But as I&rsquo;ve practiced and grown my personal collection I see myself continuing with katas.</p>

<p>I will add links here once I write about further steps of my software interview preparation plan.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Samaria Gorge hike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-30T21:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exactly two weeks ago I thought I was exhausted from preparing for job interviews (I will write a separate post explaining my study strategy). After all, I have been averaging 6-8 hours of algorithms and Java study almost every day for 2 months (I am switching careers and going full-time in software engineering). In reality, it was a virus that caused physical break-down, an eye infection and fever. In what can be described as the most spontaneous decision of my life I decided we need to take a short break and go to the sea. How spontaneous? I felt debilitating headache Monday morning and we flew out on Wednesday.</p>

<p>So we chose a destination we could fly to ASAP that had decent weather and warm sea. In the end we went to Crete. I had previously visited Crete 10 years ago. Crete left an impression not only with the warm Mediterranean climate and usual resort-world bells and whistles but also with a natural wonder I couldn&rsquo;t visit at the time. I&rsquo;m talking about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samari%C3%A1_Gorge">Samaria Gorge</a>. It was time to finally hike it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720077554"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7444/26720077554_8d954f1239_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I am amazed at how the local businesses managed to market and sell Samaria Gorge and lull even the most unprepared unfit tourists, making it a must-visit attraction. In the high season, which unsurprisingly is the worst time of the year to visit it, Samaria Gorge attracts 30,000-40,000 tourists per month. Some of those tourists later write horror stories as to how difficult and extreme the whole experience was. Legends get born and rumors get spread.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here to bust some myths. First of all, it is not the largest Gorge in Europe. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verdon_Gorge">Verdon Gorge</a> is. Second, it is not an extremely difficult adventure. It&rsquo;s best described as a hike of medium-easy difficulty. Most of the time the route descends which is admittedly not my favorite (I prefer ascents or mixed terrain). While the terrain is rocky there is nothing extreme about it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720813773"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7251/26720813773_bb58db0b87_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27052274170"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7653/27052274170_654d0d72a3_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27257029391"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7006/27257029391_246c4a35bb_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>In terms of gear the hike requires mostly decent shoes. I brought the most minimal and lightweight shoes I own and they were just fine. Apparently the overly successful marketing attracts unsuspecting couch potatoes in flip-flops but I haven&rsquo;t spotted a single person whose clothing stood out as outlandlishly inadequate.</p>

<p>Without any strain we completed the walk in 5:45. We took lots of pictures and made one stop for packed breakfast in the old Samaria village which is in the middle of the route. My watch counted 20Km but I suspect that&rsquo;s due to errors due to poor sky visibility in the gorge. Officially, the total distance from the park entrance to the beach is approximately 17Km. Sounds realistic.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/590696789">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>End of May is a fantastic time to visit it because the gorge is full of life: vegetation and flowers. Most importantly, it is not scorching hot. I find that the scenery becomes interesting after the Samaria village, roughly 8-10Km into the hike. The first half is similar to a walk in a park and it&rsquo;s not possible to see much of the gorge. But the actual gorge looks breathtaking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27230250722"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7349/27230250722_01d870f748_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>In fact, I would consider visiting the park in the opposite direction: arriving by ship at the end of the route in the morning, exploring the gorge area up to the Samaria village and taking the ship back. It&rsquo;s possible to pull this off with a rental car by keeping it in the town from where the ship departs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27257075871"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7001/27257075871_daabee70cf_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27230278702"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7370/27230278702_2a68bc4ed6_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27052293150"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7439/27052293150_bf9f47ae31_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Speaking of transportation it&rsquo;s not great. There are only 3 ships per day: 2 in the morning and only one in the afternoon at 17:30. Those who finish reasonably at about 14:00-15:00 are doomed to stay in the area. Admittedly, the area ain&rsquo;t bad and the beach is completely worth a visit. In case somebody doesn&rsquo;t make it to the ship there are plenty of rooms available for rent.</p>

<p>We chose to get to the park and back by taxi. The price is not unreasonable if staying near city of Chania. For us, the higher taxi price was worth extra hours in the morning and in the evening. A tourist bus takes longer because it needs to pick-up tourists from various hotels.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720065894"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7558/26720065894_49f0bc7d21_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re visiting Crete pack a pair of shoes &mdash; the gorge is worth a visit!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indoor cycling lab]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-28T18:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Around Christmas in 2015 I received doctor&rsquo;s diagnosis that my left tibia bone is fractured and that I can&rsquo;t run for the foreseeable future. Of course, I tried against all reason but the persisting pain made me realize it&rsquo;s in my own best interest to let it heal peacefully and not break it completely. Luckily, I discovered that cycling and swimming don&rsquo;t hurt at all. I suppose that&rsquo;s because the load spread is altered and tibia is not as stressed.</p>

<p>I decided not to lose any time and began training straight away. I have setup an indoor training &ldquo;lab&rdquo; and rigorously followed a training routine three times a week. Although I have been an avid cyclist my level of cycling fitness could have been ranked as &ldquo;beginner&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;ve had plenty of distance under my belt but insufficient endurance to sustain intensive effort necessary in competitive cycling. The training program has slowly come to a successful end and I would like to showcase my setup.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306868565"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7345/27306868565_5c29150c79_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I previously found the idea of indoor cycling trainers a boring pasture. However, training indoors has its merits. The biggest advantage I see is the possibility of structured training where the load of every training session is carefully chosen to stimulate improvement in the areas that need it the most. It is very difficult to go for a ride with friends and keep a specific tempo. With an indoor trainer it&rsquo;s possible to define fine-grained intervals with specific intensity. There are training programs for improving overall cycling fitness or, for example, improving climbs or sprints.</p>

<p>Of course, there is also the convenience factor. With an indoor trainer I have no excuse skipping a training session due to bad weather. It&rsquo;s always available and takes no time to get started with it.</p>

<p>But what really attracted me are the so-called smart trainers, like the <a href="http://eu.wahoofitness.com/devices/kickr.html">wahoo Kickr</a> that I purchased. The smart trainers are dynamically controlled by software so the resistance is continuously updated. Smart trainers can simulate changing terrain and most importantly let the user focus on cycling. With the regular &ldquo;dumb&rdquo; trainers the user must adjust resistance manually. I think I would get tired of it very quickly and would definitely cheat by not being timely in amping up the difficulty.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26700511863"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7605/26700511863_2f9435ffaf_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27236905401"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7352/27236905401_bf09f5907b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>There are various tools for controlling smart trainers. Some run on Android and iOS devices while others require full desktop OSes. Either bluetooth or ANT+ wireless protocols are used to interface with the trainers. I purchased an ANT+ adapter for my computer for the purpose of controlling the smart trainer and also for accessing data from a heart rate band and a power meter sensor on my bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27209876762"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7323/27209876762_5bafeb4735.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The &ldquo;killer app&rdquo; for me is surely <a href="http://zwift.com/">Zwift</a>. It&rsquo;s a well-implemented detailed immersive 3D virtual cycling world. Zwift is capable of controling smart trainers and simulating terrain. For all the user cares he is presented with a detailed simulation that brings variety and much needed distraction to otherwise boring workouts. Zwift is a open-world multiplayer game with other cyclists riding along. Zwift integrates nicely with Strava, here is a couple of my own workouts:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/554205363">https://www.strava.com/activities/554205363</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/536343127">https://www.strava.com/activities/536343127</a></p>

<p>Zwift also supports structured training. There are multiple training programs to choose from. It&rsquo;s also possible to create a custom one. I chose a 12-week program aimed at increasing overall cycling fitness and specifically improving the Functional Threshold Power (FTP). With ilnesses, travel and other commitments in place the program actually took me more than 4 months to complete.</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/tqf5dD-ofQg "></iframe></div>


<p>I have complemented the setup with a webcam mounted on a tripod and connected to my mobile computer. This allowed to see my posture and make continous corrections. A mirror would work even better but there is no place in my room for one and I already had all the components to make a &ldquo;high-tech mirror&rdquo; solution work.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26699661594"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7311/26699661594_317dc183ac_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>This is how I see myself during a typical workout (videos are not focused very well but the idea should be clear):</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/QnhQLFUJRjQ "></iframe></div>




<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/CntF-2F9kGc "></iframe></div>


<p>Speaking of complements I discovered a few additional pieces of technology I consider vital for training and worthy of an immediate purchase. First of all, a bicycle computer or a training watch equipped with GPS and ANT+/Bluetooth interfaces. I went for both, choosing a Garmin 920XT watch and a Garmin Edge 500 cycling computer. These gadgets track workouts and allow the user to see his progress and make corrections. Having these devices is a luxury that had been available only to professional athletes in the past. Basically, it&rsquo;s like having a personal coach watch over your shoulder every moment.</p>

<p>The reason I own both is because a cycling computer is convenient for glancing at many fields at a time, without taking the hand off the handlebar. I use the cycling computer exclusively for viewing data. In fact, I bought it used at a bargain price. I don&rsquo;t cosider fancier products worthwhile.</p>

<p>Finally, a power meter is becoming increasingly popular. I&rsquo;m going so far as to say that a power meter is a complete must, especially if the user is an amateur interested in racing. A power meter basically quantifies the effort the user is currently putting out. It takes guessing out of the training. With a power meter I can adjust my power output and effort during a ride. For example, in a race I could adjust power output depending on the course to avoid overstrain. I could immediately see if the current effort is sustainable or not based on past observations. Smart trainers come with built-in power meters but I&rsquo;ve added a relatively inexpensive <a href="http://stagescycling.com/us/products/">Stages power-meter</a> for upcoming outdoor rides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306885605"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7208/27306885605_5158cd1438_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26699671554"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7311/26699671554_64e405b1c0_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>With the program almost finished what do I plan to do next? My <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">tibia has recovered</a> and I&rsquo;m almost finished with a 4-month swimming training program. I am going to develop a new plan for the next 3-4 months. With the summer here I&rsquo;m definitely going outdoors but I&rsquo;ll combine the outdoor rides with more structured indoor training to hone some of the skills, like climbing. Training ain&rsquo;t easy but I get lots of satisfaction and joy out of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rigimarsch 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T20:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another year, another <a href="http://rigimarsch.ch/">Rigimarsch</a>! <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/">Last year</a> I&rsquo;ve participated in an annual night hike up to the Rigi mountain. It was a tough yet exhilerating experience. This year I&rsquo;ve repeated the challenge together with John.</p>

<p>The route was the same as always: 50 or so kilometers with a 1500m ascent in the last 10 kilometeres. However, the hike felt refreshingly different.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/566448675">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>For me personally the hike was a test for the healing Tibia bone that fractured during last year&rsquo;s <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals/">half-marathon in Lausanne</a> (I ran 1/3 of the marathon with a fractured bone).</p>

<p>John looks cheerful but everybody is cheerful at the start:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262027875"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7316/27262027875_338b6e78de_z.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>According to the official information a record 2363 people turned up for the event. Despite the crowd the registration went smoothly. We started walking at around 20:00.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655251944"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7278/26655251944_ef51583b8c.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262034825"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7542/27262034825_1b63a4dd46.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The Rigi mountain. It is intimidating to see the peak far ahead throughout the hike:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26656292463"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7482/26656292463_6e22257b37.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262042505"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7337/27262042505_5bd6972a41.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262043975"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7659/27262043975_f7ddbf3988.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>This year&rsquo;s Rigimarsch took place on May 4th which is relatively early, compared to previous and future years. The event date is tied to Ascension day. Thanks to the early start there was plenty of snow at the top and the night temperatures were quite cool. I wore every piece of clothing I brought along.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655268824"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7360/26655268824_c98e764931.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I felt energized and positive even in the last hours of the challenge. This is a huge departure from last year&rsquo;s impression. I still vividly recall just how difficult last few hours were. I think several factors are at play. First, I&rsquo;m in much better physical shape for aerobic activities because I switched from weight lifting to triathlon. Second, we brought trekking poles with us for the ascent. Finally, I came to the hike completely rested and fresh.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27192498811"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7539/27192498811_04efa1224b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>John is still smiling at the top, that&rsquo;s the way to do it:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655286494"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7711/26655286494_f43a8df2f0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Return train from Rigi to Arth-Goldau. There were enough places in the train for everyone to take a seat:</p>

<p><a href="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7443/27164821172_47541b80f6.jpg"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7443/27164821172_47541b80f6.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The hike took us about 12 hours to complete which is almost the same as last year. However, our moving time is a whole hour shorter which means we walked measurably faster but took longer breaks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bike fitting basics for triathlon and road cycling]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-19T16:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a complete triathlon newbie I benefit tremendously from the experience and knowledge of others. Just a few little steps save years, if not decades, of trial-and-error, not to mention decrease chances of injuries and increase enjoyment of the sport. My friend Ilya Nedbailo who has successfully completed his first 70.3 Ironman in Rapperswil this year generously shared a couple of tips.</p>

<p>The first of which is getting a professional bike fitting service. I strongly believe that money spent on professional advice is worth much more than any piece of gear one may buy. A lot of human knowledge cannot be easily encoded in articles or books. One really needs one-to-one contact and quick feedback to understand the nuances of physical movement.</p>

<p>Ideally, one should do bike fitting before buying a bike. But almost any existing bike will do just fine. It&rsquo;s not unheard of to see people competing in triathlon on rigid mountain bikes. An existing road bike is certainly sufficient.</p>

<p>Choosing the right professional could be tricky, especially when there are many options. I followed Ilya&rsquo;s recommendation and went to a triathlon-focused sport store <a href="https://www.tempo-sport.ch/">Tempo-Sport AG</a> in Thalwil. I&rsquo;m glad I did because René Kuster is an experienced and dedicated counsellor. As someone who participates in the sport himself he went above the mandatory adjustments and explained what is important in the bike position and why. I find such human experience and knowledge vastly superior to impressive computerized tech. Surely a computerized solution yields correct measurements consistently every time. But who will check your pedaling technique, advise on body posture and check that you are using the right muscles when the fancy system is operated by a disinterested or an inexperienced clerk?</p>

<p>Surprisingly, my bike fits me like a glove. Even the stem length is perfect. We got the handlebar height and saddle position adjusted and then installed clip-on aero-bars. Then René explained me how to pull the pedals and told me to utilize core muscles to stabilize the body. In the subsequent training sessions I could really tell the difference: I kept myself in a good position by engaging core (acknowledged by disappearing wrist pain) and I did the pedal pull movement correctly (acknowledged by feeling muscle pain in a previously unknown area).</p>

<p>René has also suggested an upgrade path when I&rsquo;ll get the itch to spend money on improving my cycling performance. His top 3:</p>

<ol>
<li>road-bike specific pedals and shoes (I&rsquo;m currently using a XC combination of Shimano M780 pedals along with Specialized Rime shoes)</li>
<li>tight aero clothing</li>
<li>deep rim racing carbon wheels</li>
<li>everything else</li>
</ol>


<p>Once I got the bike fitted I built myself a &ldquo;cycling training lab&rdquo; at home which I&rsquo;ll explain in a separate post. For the other two disciplines I&rsquo;m going through a similar phase of collecting advice and early error correction. I&rsquo;ll share more as soon as I learn!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A long new journey ahead]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T19:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Training for a half-marathon and then successfully finishing one (although not without an injury) hooked me on pursuing further challenges. I haven&rsquo;t run a half-marathon as a way to prove anything. Rather the competition had given me an opportunity to reassure myself that I&rsquo;m capable of carrying out longer undertakings. Ten weeks from zero to finish has been a fantastic learning experience so I am looking forward to the next step which is not only longer but also more challenging. I am committed to successfully finishing a complete Ironman triathlon (IM) race, that is: consecutively swimming 3.86Km, cycling 180.2Km and running 42.2Km while not dying in the process.</p>

<p>Just few months prior as a part of my life-changing course I have given up a lot of pseudo hobbies that I had never really enjoyed. I basically scrapped everything I did and started fresh. I found out that having just one hobby at a time is surprisingly satisfying. I doubt this is a widespread problem. For me, though, too many hobbies not only spread time and attention really thin but also take away joy. I feel happy to accept triathlon as my only hobby and to say &ldquo;no&rdquo; to anything else that comes my way. It&rsquo;s cheaper this way, too.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen variable amount of craziness across the web and in real life. Some Ironman participants set highly ambitious goals of preparing in shortest time possible. I am not one of them. I want to enjoy the whole process of training and the steady growth, just like I did with running. I had a belief I hate to run. With a little help from patience and discipline I followed a careful plan. And I enjoyed every single run. Not for a moment I thought about the upcoming marathon or what lies ahead. I focused on one and only moment &ndash; the present one.</p>

<p>I intend to piggy-back on the same mindset for IM. A chord of stress has already struck me when I realized that I must rush to prepare myself for the next step: completing a half Ironman next year. As soon as I noticed the fleeting feeling I stopped immediately. I&rsquo;m not going to rush which means I&rsquo;m likely falling out of the 2016 season. I&rsquo;m aiming for an entry into a full IM in 2018. There, I wrote it. I find it REALLY difficult to commit to something so far ahead. But I believe it&rsquo;s going to be yet another fantastic outlet for learning.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile I&rsquo;m going to train and the things get really interesting from here. Unsurprisingly, there is so much information and advice available on the topic that I can&rsquo;t put it in just one entry. So I&rsquo;m going to write semi-regular posts on my training progress and findings. I&rsquo;m completely unfit and unprepared for this challenge right now. I don&rsquo;t even know how to swim properly. But I&rsquo;m excited and looking forward to the long journey ahead!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The wonderful way of carabike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T20:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In September, following a <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/">Fargo rebuild</a> with s Rohloff Speedhub I have went to ride it in Italy. This time, though, I haven&rsquo;t ridden my bike from A to B. Instead, I cheated and went my wife on a car. The revelation that had followed I have succinctly nicknamed &ldquo;car-a-bike&rdquo;.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22802670766"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5719/22802670766_f754cb289e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In a very concrete sense this is a huge departure from self sufficiency that I strive to achieve. However, it&rsquo;s a fantastic motivation for traveling. Usually I don&rsquo;t like visiting cities that much. I consider most kinds of conventional travel unsatisfying. Yet after a difficult day in the saddle it is a joy to take a hot shower, take a nap on a comfy bed and then proceed for an evening stroll in the area followed by a nice dinner.</p>

<p>The car lets you focus on the most difficult and challenging roads. A cycling tour, however, requires careful planning to ensure the route is not too exhausting. Also, to get to the truly exciting parts one needs to cycle through relatively long stretches of uninspiring roads.</p>

<h2>The full cycling itinerary</h2>

<p>Most of the route planning was undertaken by my wife. There&rsquo;s an excellent resource <a href="http://italy-cycling-guide.info/">Italy Cycling Guide</a> which offers loads of routes and suggestions.</p>

<h3>Day 1 (aka Speedhub in Italy)</h3>

<p>I had zero problems with the bike. Test riding and debugging beforehand helped immensely. The gearing on Speedhub along with a 36t felt sufficient for the steepest climbs.</p>

<p>To fit everything into a rented Volvo V60 station wagon I had to disassemble pretty much everything. Having a bike with Rohloff makes it much easier: there&rsquo;s no derailleur sticking out and there&rsquo;s no cable adjustments necessary.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22622541430"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/612/22622541430_d5dacd5eac.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22828655905"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5799/22828655905_91b6e455a9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22797055442"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5762/22797055442_0d8bfc782c.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 77.1km, 1630m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/390769207">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day1.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day1.png" width="120"></a></p>

<h3>Day 2 (aka Riders on the storm)</h3>

<p>Raining cats and dogs for about 2-3 hours. I got completely soaked. Still, getting soaked in summer in Italy is way better than getting soaked along the Rhine river in early spring.</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 86.4km, 1822m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/391527939">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day2.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day2.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 3 (aka The easiest ride in life)</h3>

<p>What was anticipated as another 1800m+ climb day turned out to be a blazing fast descent. The route went from the hills all the way down to the beach. I averaged 26kmh on my Fargo which is a lot more than my usual touring speed of 13-18.</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 67.1km, 26.4kmh average speed (on a Fargo!), <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/392113290">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day3.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day3.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 4 (aka The best 60km of my life)</h3>

<p>Hills and mountains make cycling challenging and painful but so rewarding and addictive. Though I started cycling up mountain passes less than a year ago I can&rsquo;t get enough of it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22797085762"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5811/22797085762_b3dc567372.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22622584440"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/764/22622584440_5f695d6134.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 59.7km, 1954m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/392828417">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day4.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day4.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 5 (aka The final day of biking)</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22392234497"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5640/22392234497_9383cf387f.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 60.6km, 1864m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/393913583">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day5.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/elba/day5.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to more of these rides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22640701230"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5770/22640701230_435b7c0896.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22187841494"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/722/22187841494_e0683a1b83.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-31T18:26:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;<strong>I FUCKING DID IT</strong>&rdquo; keeps resonating in my head as I am crossing the finish line. I can already feel latent excruciating pain (amplified by an adrenaline-fueled last half-mile sprint) slowly setting in. Few minutes later I won&rsquo;t be able to walk but at this glorious energizing moment I feel that my whole life is coming together.</em></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how successfully finishing a half-marathon felt to me.</p>

<p>In addition, I hereby completely reverse my opinion of life goals. I used to believe that goals are a sick abomination propagated by clouded minds of semi-religious self-improvement cults. I had my reasons. For one, I couldn&rsquo;t see what&rsquo;s one supposed to do when goals are fulfilled. And most importantly, I couldn&rsquo;t come up with any (&hellip;that I didn&rsquo;t abandon few days/weeks later).</p>

<p>Well, on a sunny day roughly 11 weeks ago I was walking past an advertisement billboard for an upcoming marathon. My mind was clear of stress and worry, thanks to the elapsed three months of sabbatical. Right there, on the spot, I have decided to run it.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m generally fit and sportive I had never run before. Hell, I have always despised running and especially all kinds of competitive events. I used to repeat a cliché: &ldquo;running is wasted time that could otherwise be spent cycling&rdquo;. Successfully finishing a difficult undertaking like that couldn&rsquo;t be achieved in an instant and there was no way to cheat. The instant gratification was out. I knew it was a long path that required disciplined training.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025248504"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5699/22025248504_84a4c75689.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>For the next 10 weeks I adopted a simple training program with 4 runs per week (basically, one of the first results in web search). The distances increased progressively until they winded down few weeks before the race. My first training run was 5km long. I could barely finish it. Thoughts were storming through my mind: &ldquo;how am I supposed to run 21km if 5km is already so difficult&rdquo;. That was my first lesson: don&rsquo;t think about the goal and instead focus on the current step. Every time I trained I focused on finishing just that training, nothing else. Miraculously, I haven&rsquo;t given up once and completed every single training run.</p>

<p>Time went by and the d-day approached. While my mind was calm my body was having some doubts. I could feel an increased heart rate during the days leading to the race. The race took place in Lausanne, French part of Switzerland. The vibe at such events is extremely positive and supportive with both, runners and bystanders, cheering for you.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025252164"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/765/22025252164_58a0ba4662.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The first two thirds of the race went steady. I maintaned a sustainable pace by regularly double-checking my speed on a sports watch. I followed my breath, movements and hydration. Not much else was going through my mind. It was systematic and joyful. In fact, I smiled a lot.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22634485092"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5826/22634485092_9b94d001a9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22460088480"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/670/22460088480_499343801b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>On the 14th kilometer something happened to my left leg. I felt pain in the quad muscle area and began to slow down. The pain was so strong I had to change the way I ran to a very inefficient one. While I lost a minute or more on every kilometer I couldn&rsquo;t imagine facing the intense pain for the last 7 or so kilometers. Even with the new foot strike the pain slowly built up and intensified. I realized that if I stop just for a moment it would be the end of the race. Most likely the legs would swell and I wouldn&rsquo;t resume. So I kept on. Inefficient, painful but persistent. As I got closer to the finish line cheering crowds and music electrified me. Despite the pain I ran faster and faster, approaching a sprinting pace. The joy culminated as I crossed the line. The emotional spike came so strongly to me that I wanted to cry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22659237311"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/616/22659237311_8dd3c46841.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know what exactly happened to my legs. Almost a week later I am still limping but the pain has mostly subsided. I trained carefully and had plenty of long distance runs. I had sufficient nutrition and hydration. I suppose nobody is exempted from risk at such endurance events, even with the best preparation. Once the pain is fully absent I&rsquo;ll surely be back with new goals in mind.</p>

<p>The experience taught a me a couple of invaluable new lessons as well as cemented a few old ones. Like never before, I believe that lessons from sports are relevant to other areas of life.</p>

<p>First, I came to realize that it&rsquo;s important to strive for the difficult and challenging things. It became immediately obvious to me that in the last couple of years I haven&rsquo;t dreamed big enough and settled for things that were easy to imagine. I tended to favor problems for which I already had an idea in my mind. Half-marathon seemed initially impossible to me which made it a clear practical example of what scale of problems to go after. When something seems almost impossible it&rsquo;s worth going after!</p>

<p>Second, as I had already admitted in the opening, I understood the value of setting life goals. It does not matter what kind of goals to choose initially, as long as they are non-trivial. As life generally doesn&rsquo;t have meaning any arbitrary goal might get one going. The success in one area will prepare you for unrelated challenges. Competitive sports offer a great training opportunity.</p>

<p>Third, there&rsquo;s nothing confusing about what to do when goals are complete. In fact, the finite lifespan of goals is very motivating and energizing. Pain and hardship don&rsquo;t last forever. Once you complete the goal it&rsquo;s over. Enjoy the moment and have some rest. Then, choose and go after a new goal!</p>

<p>Finally, when it&rsquo;s too hard to come up with any good meaningful goals it might be a sign that you are purposefully ignoring and supressing your true interests. At least I found myself in such a situation. All the goals I was coming up with ignored my most prominent ambitions and genuine interests. It was hard to face the reality and acknowledge the potential price to pay. That&rsquo;s how comfort zones shrink. It&rsquo;s a slow but sure way to die inside.</p>

<p>Training for and then running a (half)-marathon is potentially a life changing experience but only when the success comes hard and the mind is fertile and open. It didn&rsquo;t come easy to me and I can&rsquo;t appreciate enough everything I have learned and realized.</p>

<p>I am also indebted for the success of my first race to my beloved wife. Without your support and understanding nothing would come out of it. You have a 20% stake in this achievement!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salsa Fargo Mk3 - now with Rohloff!]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-03T18:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I fell in love with a Salsa Fargo bicycle exactly one year ago. The bike made me newly excited about cycling. No wonder I&rsquo;ve put more than 4000 kilometers on it. I never rode the bike stock and rebuilt it with custom parts as soon as I received it by post (frames were out of stock in July last year).</p>

<p>Following the tour around France I decided to change a few things on the bike to better suit the kind of riding that I do:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>install the original rigid carbon fork instead of a suspended RockShox Reba: I did not feel very confident desceding from mountain passes on windy paved roads even with the lock-out engaged; plus, the original fork has bosses for mounting so-called &ldquo;Anything cages&rdquo; for holding drybags</p></li>
<li><p>remove Cane Creek Thudbuster seatpost: I feel annoyed by the occassional squeaking but it is possible I&rsquo;m going to reinstall it if I notice increased fatigue</p></li>
<li><p>install Rohloff Speedhub 14 IGH: while a derailleur system generally works pretty well internally geared hubs have certain advantages which pique my interest</p></li>
<li><p>change tires: 70-80% of riding I do on this bike are on paved surfaces and gravel, it does not make sense to wear out off-road tires and lose efficiency on the asphalt</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This resulted in the 3rd reincarnation of my favorite bike: Salsa Fargo make 3!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20497054903"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5802/20497054903_7e29d55136.jpg" width="333"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20497047673"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5777/20497047673_f30a77b4cf.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>It is often difficult to understand whether certain parts will work together. I hope this information helps you to (re)build your bike.</p>

<p>I filmed the process of breaking down and re-assembling the bike:</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/u7KHGC5LjJQ "></iframe></div>


<h2>Random pieces of wisdom</h2>

<h3>Chainline</h3>

<p>To achieve a completely straight chainline I&rsquo;m using Shimano XT M780 cranks with a Woolftooth 36t narrow-wide single chain ring. I know Middleburn RS8 X-Type Rohloff crank also works but is way too expensive and ugly for my taste. I couldn&rsquo;t confirm if any other (e.g. ethirteen, truvativ) cranks can be run with the right offset.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20931357759"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/747/20931357759_6128e45f3d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h3>Alternator dropout</h3>

<p>Salsa Rohloff alternator dropout works with Rohloff OEM mount. OEM2 plate is not needed. See photo below to understand how the hub/wheel is held in place:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21108031852"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/21108031852_fcaf00487d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h3>Rohloff cable routing</h3>

<p>The external Rohloff gear box can be rotated for the best placement. The Fargo frame has cable guides on the seatstays which allow for 3 cables: rear brake and 2 Rohloff cables.</p>

<h3>Rohloff installation</h3>

<p>The installation is simple. Follow the original instructions. Co-motion provides an excellent HOWTO video for their shifter:</p>

<div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/O3up1eZT3Pg "></iframe></div>


<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to put oil in! The hub is shipped without sufficient oil inside. A tube of oil is included in the package.</p>

<h3>Removing rear wheel</h3>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t find any information on how hard is to remove the rear wheel when using Rohloff. It is easier than with a derailleur system! First, remove the external gear box. Then, open the quick release axle and slide out the wheel. Done!</p>

<p>When re-installing the wheel put the chain on the rear sprocket and slide the wheel in like on any other bike. No need to break the chain or disengage the drop-outs. It&rsquo;s easier than a derailleur system because it&rsquo;s not necessary to fiddle with the chain to get it on the cassette.</p>

<h3>Mounting E3 tail light on the rear rack</h3>

<p>While the alternator rack does not have holes to install a rear tail light I attached the E3 tail light with a double-sided tape and a couple of plastic zip ties. The cable can be guided along the top tube of the rack.</p>

<h3>Salsa rear rack (non alternator version)</h3>

<p>Non-alternator Salsa rack does NOT fit an alternator-equipped Salsa frame.</p>

<h3>Cockpit housing routing</h3>

<p>It is not trivial to route the brake housing when using Co-Motion drop-bar shifter. It is especially tricky with Supernova handlebar extender. I used a staged approach:</p>

<ol>
<li>leave the stem bolts loose to allow handlebar movement left and right</li>
<li>move Co-Motion shifter onto the bar but don&rsquo;t tighten the bolt yet</li>
<li>install brake levers</li>
<li>install the first part of housing (to the barrel adjusters) and route the right one through Co-Motion shifter</li>
<li>slide the handlebar right and temporarily move Co-Motion shifter as left as possible</li>
<li>tape the right side of the handlebar up to the tapered point of the handlebar</li>
<li>slide Co-Motion shifter to the right; I moved it as far right as the wide diameter of the bar allows it</li>
<li>install Supernova handlebar extender (for mounting the front light on) and route the brake housing through openings</li>
<li>continue as usual</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20495491904"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5816/20495491904_32d8e3b11e_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20930242178"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5782/20930242178_5a68f88e78_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h2>First impressions</h2>

<p>The bike came together cleanly. Salsa designed the Fargo frame around possible Rohloff use. The frame has sufficient cable guides and the Rohloff Alternator dropout is easy to install and use. Adjusting chain tension is straightforward. No need for chain half-links or an eccentric bottom bracket.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21125844901"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/587/21125844901_1e84167b89_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20929989490"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5740/20929989490_1bb98c75c7_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The drivetrain is quiet. It is slightly unusual that shifting under load does not always work and can sometimes temporarily send the hub in the higher gear. The upside is that shifting works in a complete standstill. It will require some getting used to.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20495479424"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/20495479424_e8de8a8285_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The shifter is not indexed. Everything happens inside the hub. The upside is simplicity and higher reliability. The downside is reduced feedback in the shifter. The shifts are felt but are nowhere crisp as they were on the SRAM Red/X0 combination I had before.</p>

<p>All in all I&rsquo;m satisfied with the result. In fact I&rsquo;m going to put a Rohloff on my second adventure bike which is going to be a so-called 31er/29+ Surly ECR. I came back from the test ride with a huge smile on my face. I just fucking love bikes.</p>

<h2>Final build kit</h2>

<p>The full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/albums/72157658151072695">is available on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h3>Frame</h3>

<ul>
<li>Salsa Fargo 2 bomb pop blue 2014 frame</li>
<li>Salsa Carbon Firestarter through-axle</li>
</ul>


<h3>Drivetrain</h3>

<ul>
<li>Rohloff Speedhub 14</li>
<li>Co-Motion drop-bar Rohloff shifter</li>
<li>Shimano 10-speed chain</li>
<li>Chris King bottom bracket</li>
<li>Alternator dropout + single-speed driveside dropout</li>
<li>Shimano XT M780 crankset</li>
<li>Wolftooth 36t single narrow wide chainring</li>
<li>Shimano XT pedals</li>
</ul>


<h3>Wheels</h3>

<ul>
<li>Schwalbe Big Apple 2.35&#8221; tires</li>
<li>SON Schmidt 28 15 dynamo front hub</li>
<li>DT Swiss TK 540 disc rims</li>
</ul>


<h3>Seat</h3>

<ul>
<li>Brook Cambium C17 carved</li>
<li>Thomson Elite seatpost</li>
</ul>


<h3>Cockpit</h3>

<ul>
<li>Salsa Woodchipper handlebar</li>
<li>Salsa Guide stem</li>
<li>Chris King i7 headset</li>
<li>Salsa gel cork tape</li>
<li>Supernova handlebar extension</li>
</ul>


<h3>Brakes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Avid BB7s road brakes</li>
<li>SRAM S900 brake levers</li>
<li>200mm Avid G2CS front rotor</li>
<li>160mm Avid G2CS Rohloff-specific rear rotor</li>
</ul>


<h3>Electronics &amp; accessories</h3>

<ul>
<li>Supernova E3 Pro front light</li>
<li>Rack-mounted Supernova E3 tail light</li>
<li>Salsa Alternator rack</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trip report from bicycle tour across France]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-07T20:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Riding vs buying</h2>

<p>I am amused with the nontrivial amount of invented needs by the bicycle industry as well as the strength of its marketing departments. Each year brings new wheel/tire size standards, new drive-train groupsets and mass-produced lifestyles and attitudes. Suddenly, many enthusiasts desperately realize their need for full-suspension fat bikes with a certain kind of axles for &ldquo;backpacking&rdquo; &ldquo;adventure&rdquo; &ldquo;expeditions&rdquo;. I don&rsquo;t see how bicycle gear obsession is any different from the common consumerism. In the photography world it&rsquo;s called &ldquo;GAS&rdquo; &ndash; gear acquisition syndrome &ndash; which is known to be unconducive to original work.</p>

<p>I am not immune to the disease either. In fact, I have a very heavy case of it. I&rsquo;m obsessed with bikes and bike parts which doesn&rsquo;t land financial wellbeing a huge favor. But the solution is actually pretty simple: just ride the goddamned bike [you already have]!</p>

<p>When I have had photography GAS at one moment I had owned 4 digital cameras. My photographs were not amazing and most of the gear sat idle. Now I own 1 camera and 2 lenses: 35mm and 55mm. I appreciate the limitations and praise the amazing camera body every time I use it. I&rsquo;m definitely not doing any worse than before. If anything, I feel a bit more creative having just 2 prime lenses. It&rsquo;s the same with bikes. I recently caught another potentially expensive itch to get a new bike. And that meant one thing only: not enough saddle time!</p>

<h2>Putting the cranks where my mouth is</h2>

<p>With my diagnosis unambigously established, me and John decided to go for a cure cycling tour across France.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/france-tour.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/france-tour.png" width="1021"></a></p>

<p>Our actual route traced through the following places: <strong>Dijon</strong> &mdash; <strong>Morvan national park</strong> &mdash; <strong>Nevers</strong> &mdash; <strong>Bourges</strong> &mdash; <strong>Saint-Aignan</strong> &mdash; <strong>Tours</strong> &mdash; <strong>Saumur</strong> &mdash; <strong>Nantes</strong> &mdash; <strong>Noirmoutier</strong> &mdash; <strong>Jard-sur-Mer</strong> &mdash; <strong>La Rochelle</strong>. The route incorporated parts of Eurovelo 6 and Eurovelo 1. We rode for 8 days and totaled approximately 1100 Km. The distances across days were spread the following way: <strong>115</strong> &ndash; <strong>108</strong> &ndash; <strong>170</strong> &ndash; <strong>140</strong> &ndash; <strong>155</strong> &ndash; <strong>166</strong> &ndash; <strong>116</strong> &ndash; <strong>119</strong>. We allowed ourselves 8 days to complete it. However, we bought flexible return tickets and had 2 extra days just in case.</p>

<p>Originally, we were thinking of a much grander 2-3 week tour this year in a northern European country. But I&rsquo;m glad we decided against it because we weren&rsquo;t yet ready for potential adversity.</p>

<h2>Our story</h2>

<p>One early Sunday morning I woke-up at 3:55. I had a nice warm breakfast cooked by my dear and understanding wife. I then drove in a rented car to the train station and from there carried my packed bike and panniers across two train stations before meeting John. We then took a train to Basel where we ran with the ultra-uncomfortable heavy Tranzbags across our shoulders to the French part of the train station. I felt slightly nervous because of the french TGV train. Although SNCF (the French train company) clearly states that packed bikes are allowed on all trains I knew enough of the culture to realize we might still have trouble. Gladly we had zero issues and soon enough we arrived in Dijon and unpacked our bikes. I suppose traveling first class has its merits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190464608"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3807/20190464608_e6a225fdb3.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>We bought some snacks at the train station and then some groceries in a Thai shop along the way. We planned our first few days to be the hardest with the most elevation gains. It&rsquo;s better to plan for tough days first while you&rsquo;re still rested and fresh. We learned this the hard way in the last year&rsquo;s Rhine tour. Back then we rode for 30 or so kilometers the first day. And we had to ride until midnight the many days after to compensate for it.</p>

<p>From early on we joined local insignificant roads and cycling paths. We followed beautiful Canal de Bourgogne with its many boats. There were numerous recreational weekend cyclists on the paths close to nearby cities.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755784074"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/465/19755784074_decd610c30.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Once we departed from the canal the scenery abruptly changed into typical rural country-side France: lots and lots of fields and small run-down villages. The scenery reminded me of my home country Latvia. The weather was too perfect to be true: cloudy and around 17C.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190413600"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/261/20190413600_79cd562045_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Our first destination was the Morvan national park. As we got closer our path has led us into forests and unpaved roads. Parts of the roads were washed out. Others had huge trees lying across them so we had to lift our bikes. At times we had to walk. Frankly I didn&rsquo;t anticipate we would need to negotiate such terrain but these challenges set the right adventure spirit early on. Our average speed fell quickly and it was hard to imagine we would do the original 130km planned for the day.</p>

<p>I learned that &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; means different things to Swiss and French. In Switzerland &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; means a finely packed gravel you can ride with a road bike. In France &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; may mean a mud bath, a single-track or an alltogether abandoned path last driven on a grandfather&rsquo;s Land Rover 20 years ago.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20384617841"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/317/20384617841_6ee210343b_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I felt I should have changed my worn tires before this tour but I can only imagine how much worse it was for John who had touring tires without any knobs.</p>

<p>It is amazing how much the scenery changes during the day while cycling. At first the scenery appears to drag on forever. But once the day is over and you look back it&rsquo;s hard to comprehend it all happened in one day. That also presents a challenge for taking photos: nothing seems interesting enough until it&rsquo;s all over. And then you regret not taking enough of shots.</p>

<p>The weather started behaving and we had to wait out a couple of showers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20369920682"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/433/20369920682_26264c1d93.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>At about 18:30 we had to stop cycling because we were soaking wet and shivering from cold. Somehow my original plan of not taking rain-proof gear didn&rsquo;t account for 14C temperature in summer. We were lucky to find a small house and not camp the first night. It would have been a miserable experience. A nearby campsite had a working cafe so we downed a couple of burgers before settling down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352235486"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/448/20352235486_f92b3f8c0b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In the morning we had to wait out a couple of determined showers despite our ambition to leave early and make the most out of the day. This tour taught me patience as ambition in the wrong circumstances is foolish. We stopped at a local grocery store to stock up on food. After a couple of days shopping for groceries became routine. I learned that restaurants and cafes are far from necessary when it&rsquo;s possible to buy varied and fresh food from the local market.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20192163249"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/20192163249_0a62a831cb_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20192166779"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/554/20192166779_14b5d71f6a_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757883033"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19757883033_f5a418d2e9_m.jpg" width="240"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190673638"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/385/20190673638_1fb6dcd2b4_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>There were a couple of lakes along the way but the scenery appeared ominous because of the drizzling rain and gray skies. As the unpaved forest roads made their grand reapperance I became quite worried as you can read from my facial expression:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191863269"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/378/20191863269_a06f4cf6de.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190506138"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/20190506138_946012d336.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I felt anger and anxiety because we were crawling and I didn&rsquo;t plan for such extended terrain contingencies. I was counting on fast packed gravel speedways! Eventually, the skies cleared and we returned to the country-side. We made a decision to divert from the original route and stick to secondary asphalt roads to get to our next target.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378510665"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20378510665_0e62a9bb50.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755836414"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/434/19755836414_06bfcb25cb_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We arrived in a town Nevers and camped in the municipal camp site. We checked the weather forecast in advance to make sure it won&rsquo;t rain or else camping would be a suboptimal choice. It was our first camping night and I was pleasantly surprised it took us only about 20 minutes to set everything up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191886119"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/430/20191886119_3efc34e661_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Sleeping though was an entirely different story. I couldn&rsquo;t fall asleep and felt cold during the night. I was restless and half awake the whole night. I forgot to take ear plugs with me. At least I&rsquo;m glad we had decided to purchase summer sleeping bags. Our original plan was to use silk liners.</p>

<p>We woke up early at 5:20 to make the most of the day as we had seen the forecast predicting rain after 18:00. Something kept me going but sleep deprivation felt miserable. This can be judged by the amount of photos taken during the day: very few.</p>

<p>As we got to a big city Bourges by lunch time we couldn&rsquo;t find a working cycling store because everyone one of the four stores was prematurely closed for a lunch break. John forgot his helmet in the train and needed to get a new one. In the next two hours we purchased groceries and went to a posh burger place. Once we bought a helmet we made a decision to continue for an extra 80 kilometers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755853054"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/356/19755853054_8683722906_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Our progress seemed very slow. The roads were winding up and down slightly and we were going against the wind. In addition, we had taken a somewhat busy road with lots of truck traffic.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190478720"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/281/20190478720_4a234e170f_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>At about 17:00 it predictably started to rain. My spirits were really low because I knew the forecast. We refused to stay in Bourges because that would end the day too early. There were no places to stop between Bourges and our next target. It is a persistent challenge to find accommodation at the right time.</p>

<p>We had to continue despite the rain. The rain wouldn&rsquo;t go away. So we climbed our bikes, wore the wind-proof jackets and pushed on. We soon realized it wasn&rsquo;t so bad. The wind has subsided and the road radiated heat. We were wet but not cold. Our bodies eventually dried our clothes.</p>

<p>Few hours into the ride we called a couple of hotels to book a room so that we have a place to stay when we get to the town late in the evening. At 130-140 kilometer mark we felt energized. I realized it is a very common occurrence. The first 70-100 or so kilometers are the hardest. The first 70 are, in fact, torturous because progress appears too slow.</p>

<p>Admittedly, up to this point I felt similar to how we felt in our previous Rhine tour. Anxious and nervous we&rsquo;re not making enough progress among unexpected difficulties. The tables turned the next day when I felt, for the first time, confidence and freedom from the shackles of our original plan. Our goal is to enjoy the journey and we can alter and change the route in any way we like.</p>

<p>On the following days we got on to route EuroVelo 6 and from there traced the longest French river La Loire. To take the shortest path we used Google Maps directions and a micro SD slot on my phone to create a GPX track that can be swallowed by Garmin.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757620813"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19757620813_2a3a7ce575_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190496210"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3769/20190496210_a0ca74be9d_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>The scenery offered views on splendid bridges over La Loire and its many castles.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755932284"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/260/19755932284_5e72621630_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191955409"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/331/20191955409_25370d9e47_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20384749161"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/444/20384749161_cfa7653ddf_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The larger French cities, such as Bourges or Nantes appeared surprisingly industrial.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352310756"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/369/20352310756_b9f046df00_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352384086"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/468/20352384086_688f768bd1_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We got into a habit of arriving somewhat late to the campsites. Most of the receptions close at 18:00. We basically had to trespass, find empty pitch spots and then pay in the morning upon departure. This made the staff quite confused. But finishing our days at 18:00 or so seemed too early. As we didn&rsquo;t cook dinner there wasn&rsquo;t much to do. Why stay bored in the campsite when we can be enjoying the road?</p>

<p>We caught up with the planned schedule in Nantes. But once we have got there we decided to take a train to La Rochelle to make the last few days easier. I am so glad that the morning train was full and we decided against it! Instead, we continued EuroVelo 6 route to the coast of the Atlantic ocean and then continued South through EuroVelo 1. The road along the ocean has quickly overshadowed everything we cycled so far. To make the last few days easier we decided to take a train from La Rochelle to Bordeaux thinking that we&rsquo;ve seen enough of French country side roads.</p>

<p>Pine trees, the smell of open water and white sand reminded me of my home country once more: it was like a bigger and better version of Jurmala. Our first day along the coast stretched late into the evening because we have run into a few problems. Namely, the road to an island we hoped to take was flooded that time of the day, we have ridden into a dead end trying to take another road and we lost each other. The reward was one of the most beautiful sunsets I have ever seen.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19756050324"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/528/19756050324_a5a3a86ed8_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352477786"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3695/20352477786_c6ef2586f1_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19756058424"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/560/19756058424_566d9388f7_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352483906"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/407/20352483906_298bf3f6b0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Camping (unathorized, as usual) on the Noirmoutier island was fantastic. In the morning I discovered a flat rear tire which was promptly fixed:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190685130"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/305/20190685130_742f00a4e4_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378747705"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/468/20378747705_4307880bd4_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>We continued along the coast until we reached La Rochelle. There were a few resort towns along the way which made me panic. I don&rsquo;t like crowded places. We breezed through them quickly. On the weekend cycling paths were crawling with beachgoers. Cycling in the early hours of the day was much better. There are also annoying obstacles, such as gates, to slow the cyclists down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20370219732"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/437/20370219732_f34afd8105_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757824133"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/365/19757824133_b811dbda41_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757863073"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/384/19757863073_2f9ae1edbf_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190820048"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/348/20190820048_e660b17120.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757891663"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/371/19757891663_db6e7eeb50.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378822715"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/557/20378822715_5899351d4e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190768350"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/502/20190768350_bdd1a58d8b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Once we arrived in La Rochelle we cycled across an enormous bridge to the Isle of Rhé and bathed in the ocean.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190837468"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/434/20190837468_ddf9a1b4c5.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20370279592"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/449/20370279592_cd45c78dbc_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>The full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/sets/72157654009464044">is available on Flickr</a>. Links to the individual day tracks in strava: <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743564">8</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743578">7</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743583">6</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743582">5</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366746443">4</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743556">3</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743543">2</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743544">1</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Across France on a bicycle]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T19:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following numerous episodes of soul searching I finally came to realize that enjoy cycling more than an average person. While I enjoy many flavors of it, such as road cycling and mountain down-hill riding my absolute favorites are endurance and touring rides.</p>

<p>My dream is to visit as many places on a bicycle as I could. Somehow biking[1] feels to me just the right way to explore the world. Last year I joined my very first cycling tour along the river Rhine. That tour had its ups and downs. I learned a lot and wrote about the lessons in earlier posts. <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">post1</a> <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">post2</a></p>

<p>This year me and John are expanding our comfort zones. While we&rsquo;re still within the safe confines of Europe we&rsquo;re not going for hotel accommodation. Instead, we&rsquo;re going to camp. Hopefully, we will learn new lessons and don&rsquo;t repeat the previous mistakes. Step by step we make our tours more challenging and more exciting.</p>

<p>Our destination this year is Northern and Western France. We&rsquo;re starting off from city Dijon to which get by a high-speed train. French TGVs disallow  assembled bikes onboard so we had to purchase so-called TranZBags and partly disassemble our bikes (note that I leave the tent attached to the bike):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20008244211"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3673/20008244211_5f2ddde0f4_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>To fit the bike comfortably inside the bag I took extra steps and removed the seat-post and pedals. That should also minimize the risk of broken spokes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19380398634"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/294/19380398634_2e95a27719_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I hope we won&rsquo;t have problems. Just in case we purchased 1st class tickets expecting fewer passengers and fewer confrontations.</p>

<p>From the outset our gear list is much shorter than last year which is plenty remarkable as we haven&rsquo;t camped and instead stayed in hotels and hostels. Here&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m bringing:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19816344399"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/359/19816344399_5c8e06b5f9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<ul>
<li>bike repair kit (napkin, pump, spare tube, 2x multi tool, leatherman knife, tape, zip ties, plastic gloves, chain bits)</li>
<li>flexible bike lock</li>
<li>TranZBag (for transporting bicycle on trains)</li>
<li>2x 60g tubes of chamois cream</li>
<li>3x packs of hydration tables</li>
<li>swimming trunks</li>
<li>hiking towel</li>
<li>inflatable sleeping mat</li>
<li>compact summer sleeping bag</li>
<li>cash wallet</li>
<li>15000mah portable battery</li>
<li>passport</li>
<li>bank access code generator</li>
<li>head torch</li>
<li>notebook and pen</li>
<li>Garmin 62s and one set of spare batteries</li>
<li>credit card wallet</li>
<li>leg warmers</li>
<li>phone</li>
<li>one extra cycling shirt</li>
<li>ultra-light wind-proof jacket (packed into red sack)</li>
<li>one extra cycling bibs</li>
<li>arm warmers</li>
<li>one extra set of socks</li>
<li>medicine</li>
<li>compact digital camera (not shown)</li>
</ul>


<p>This is the stuff I&rsquo;m going to wear on me (helmet is not shown):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19815037210"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/396/19815037210_82c57f6492_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>This time I&rsquo;m not taking any kind of rain gear because it is pointless in summer heat. I&rsquo;m also not taking any food. Instead, we&rsquo;ll scout for grocery stores along the way.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t publish anything during the ride but I&rsquo;ll keep some notes for a report upon our return. Wish us good luck!</p>

<p>[1] walking, hiking, climbing are the other preferred means</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountaineering in Valais]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-10T15:42:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There comes a moment in a life of a dormant adventurer when the curtains of undesired comfort are torn away and the world is finally seen through wide-open eyes, fueled by challenge and gore, excitement and joy. In this very moment feelings of inadequacy and out-of-placeness give way to sincere enthusiasm and appreciation and beauty of the world. I am boundlessly joyful to cross that imaginary line and thirstily imbibe from the cup of mountaineering and alpine beauty.</p>

<p>Such life-changing shift of perception comes from just a single adventure that I have had the tremendous luck to be a part of. Last Saturday I joined company of JD, Samuel and Clément to trek for 5 days through a mountain range in the French canton Valais of Switzerland, through ice, snow and rock. In the best tradition of Sergey the journey has been one of the hardest things he has ever done in his life.</p>

<h2>Preparation (lack of thereof)</h2>

<p>An invitation to join the expedition came from my friend JD unexpectedly following the 420km bicycle challenge that I completed few weeks ago. I knew JD went on awesome mountaineering trips before so I had repeatedly pestered him to invite me next time he goes. Over a phone call he congratulated me on the achievement and casually mentioned that he&rsquo;s going on a 5-day mountaineering trip and wondered if I may be interested. I suspect he did not expect my overeager enthusiasm nor participation.</p>

<p>But contrary to my outer timidity I immediately lit up with excitement in my mind like a deranged gasoline-soaked martyr. Though I could satisfactory climb in the gym I knew very little about mountaineering: what to bring, what to wear, how to navigate glaciers and snow, how and why to use the rope, what to do with the ice axe and when to wear the crampons. Nor did I have much time to fill the gaps. Instead, I trusted experience of my companions and hesitated very little to ask stupid questions.</p>

<p>Since the invitiation was on a short notice there have been only a couple of available days between other trips. JD and me went to a climbing gym once to practice ropes and lead climbing so that I could demonstrate my satisfactory skill and both of us could get a warm-up.</p>

<p>While I already own a relatively impressive set of outdoor equipment I lacked essential items required for mountaineering. Specifically, my supposedly bad-ass high-cut hiking boots were unsuitable for crampons due to excessive flexibility. So I had to get a new pair of steel-stiff shoes. I also had to purchase: an ice axe (plus a blade protector so that I didn&rsquo;t accidentally murder a bystanding old lady in a train), crampons (plus a protector bag so I didn&rsquo;t rip my backpack open) and an ice screw (existence of which puzzled me at first). Initially I felt that all the stuff is excessive. However, as soon as we hit the high-altitude track usefulness of every piece of gear became readily apparent.</p>

<p>I am proud to not only have carried the required gear but also to not have brought too much unnecessary bits and bobs. I erred on the side of bringing too little. So I had only one set of everything which sounds slightly unhygienic and off-putting. The arguably good thing about mountains is that there are very few connoisseurs and, in general, people.</p>

<h2>Day 1: from Arolla to Cabane des Vignettes (3200m)</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653806"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-1.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 5.82km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 1101m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 57m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 4:01&#8217;45.1</p>

<p>We met 8 in the morning and went on a 4-hour car ride to the town of Arolla (2006m) from which we needed to climb to our first hut &ldquo;Cabane des Vignettes&rdquo; (3157m).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19396916240"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/454/19396916240_7204d49735.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558716196"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/288/19558716196_003a5f463e_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>After consulting with my experienced companions I have unloaded 10% of gear and learned how to correctly attach an ice axe to a backpack (the photo shows incorrect axe placement).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962326704"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3677/18962326704_eae7247a8c_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962368554"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/295/18962368554_034e6e971c_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18964030073"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/467/18964030073_73487bb76b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Most of the way on the first day was hiking. The first 300-400 vertical meters felt really tough and in my head I wondered whether I will ever make it. Fortunately, my experience from all other difficult activities told me to ignore the first steps. First steps are always hard. I don&rsquo;t know if the body adjusts or the mind changes perception. When it gets really hard I look one step ahead and keep my head down not to see just how high our destination is. At some point the moves got automatic: step, breathe, step, panic, step, breathe, step, ad nauseam. As little thinking as possible. These moments of utter concentration are a total blessing compared to anxiety-induced modern existence.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19584905205"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/339/19584905205_e10e6cb348_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398332399"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/364/19398332399_faebdd746a_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578027852"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3742/19578027852_3508a5344b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>After 600m of climbing the body adjusted sufficiently that I did not feel like I&rsquo;m going to faint. Relief. I felt surprisingly comfortable in the new stiff shoes though I held no illusions about upcoming blisters: new shoes are always a bad idea.</p>

<p>At some point we approached snow and I got my first taste of mountaineering. We got all roped together. The rope is a safety device against a risk of hidden crevasses (cracks in the ice). Crevasses themselves are not that dangerous because you can see them and avoid them (or jump over) but when crevasses are hidden underneath the snow you could accidentally fall through. That&rsquo;s when your buddies are going to pull you out. As the least experienced I was put second, the most experienced went to the front and the end of our life-saving connection. We kept about 10m of rope between each other. It&rsquo;s important to keep the rope sufficiently tight so that in an event of a fall the rope does not create a too strong of a jerk.</p>

<p>We then slogged through snow until we reached our first hut. Crampons (I much prefer the Russian word for it, &ldquo;kittens&rdquo;) were not necessary yet because the snow was slushy. Crampons are useful when the snow is hard or icy. I closely followed the footsteps of Clément because sliding sideways and falling wastes precious energy. I learned how to hold an ice axe and what is it for. An ice axe is mainly a stability and a braking device. An ice axe is held against the slope. It is also an effective brake when you&rsquo;re either sliding down a slope or your comrade is falling in a crevass. The lower part of an ice axe is used the most: an ice axe is like a hiking pole. You don&rsquo;t use an ice axe crazily swinging it around. So I was a bit disappointed because of that. I still had no idea what an ice screw was for.</p>

<p>On the way to the hut an ambitious Swiss duo accidentally injured JD by sticking an ice axe into his leg. I really can&rsquo;t think of a way you accidentally stick an ice axe into someone&rsquo;s leg but the person apologized at the top and gave his contact information so that he could pay for mending JD&rsquo;s brand new pair of mountaineering trousers. Fortunately, the damage to the leg was limited to a couple of nasty scratches.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558789636"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/354/19558789636_6bfe198ce6_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Reaching the hut rewarded us with splendid views on the surrounding peaks and glaciers though, as I learned later, the views are not what mountaineering and hiking are all about.</p>

<p>Views from the hut area, note The Bishop (l&#8217;évêque) peak close to the left edge &ndash; we ascended it on the second day:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398402569"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/523/19398402569_e05be53d23_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558817716"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/437/19558817716_6fe36b8686.jpg" width="500"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589304621"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/439/19589304621_cbfb9dc2a0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I have never stayed in a mountain hut before. Swiss mountain huts are impressively equipped. Some of the huts even offer microbrewery beers. Prices reflect the difficulty of bringing the stuff up to high altitudes. Normally, a hut provides a bunk bed, breakfast and dinner. The food was delicious: a thick minestrone soup followed by pasta bolognese. Mountain food is high on calories because climbing mountains ain&rsquo;t easy.</p>

<p>Overall, I found the experience of the first day highly reminiscent of any other challenge I had faced in my life. Looking back I am astonished at how transferable are the skills of sports to everyday adversities. I made a mental note to look back at physical challenges in search of answers and motivation next time I run up against a wall of life&rsquo;s conundrums.</p>

<h2>Day 2: The Bishop climb (3707m)</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653815"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-2.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 10.87km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 882m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 865m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 7:04&#8217;38.7</p>

<p>Mountains run on their own time. I coin this peculiar phenomenon &ldquo;mountain time&rdquo;. Normal people wake up at 7 or 8. Mountain people, though, finish with their breakfast at 4 and are all packed up ready to go at 4:30. And I used to think I am an early riser&hellip; The reasons have to do with weather conditions and snow. It&rsquo;s better to have extra time for unexpected adversity than to get stuck in the dark. I&rsquo;ve been told that if it&rsquo;s 6pm and you&rsquo;re still out there you are clearly red lining and in very real danger.</p>

<p>Actually the second day was a bit of luxury as we had breakfast at 4:30 and left the hut at 5:15. Our goal was a peak called &ldquo;The Bishop&rdquo; (l&#8217;évêque) which was clearly seen from the hut the day before. There is another mountain phenomenon I call &ldquo;mountain scale&rdquo;. Apparently, human brain cannot judge the sheer vastness of mountains and the perception of distance is seriously distorted. Mountains seem much closer than they really are and only with some points of reference can the real size be understood. For example, tiny humans (that seems more like ants) put things into perspective.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398433189"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3771/19398433189_e2ff6eb29d_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397041088"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3731/19397041088_fd6f06b0f6_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t grasp how far The Bishop was. The first part of the ascent was very difficult for me. My body still haven&rsquo;t fully adapted to walking up with a heavy backpack. At some point I felt taste of blood in my mouth (seems similar to taste of metal). It&rsquo;s a sign that I&rsquo;m doing an honest exercise. The second part was much steeper but felt easier due to short rhythmic movements. We wore crampons from the start as the snow was just in the right shape for them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398450589"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/539/19398450589_b30335ca48_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>The final part of the ascent involved an easy rock climbing section. Grabbing rock edges and moving above thousands of meters is breathtaking. At 09:00 we reached the top of The Bishop (3707m). At the top I learned another unusual fact about mountaineering and hiking. I thought we&rsquo;re going to marvel at the surroundings for hours so just to confirm my obvious expectation I asked Sam how long are we going to stay at the summit. He answered briefly: &ldquo;about 10 minutes&rdquo;. After an awkward pause I calmly said: &ldquo;So we had climbed for 4 hours up. We stay on the summit for 10 minutes. Then we climb down for another 3 hours. Is this a fair summary of what we&rsquo;re doing?&rdquo;. Obviously, there&rsquo;s a reason. It&rsquo;s better to go back as soon as possible because the weather is somewhat unpredictable and snow gets slushy quickly. Climbing, mountaineering, hiking are not about the summit (goal). It&rsquo;s more about the journey itself.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19585025825"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/401/19585025825_ddb4549644_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589341891"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3681/19589341891_59ba03ff6f_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578145332"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19578145332_180cb7d095_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Panorama from the top of The Bishop:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589363141"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3711/19589363141_dc2817975f_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>On the way back I ran out of water. I had 1.5L with me which was clearly not enough. That whole time I was dreaming of an ice cold bottle filled with sparkling water. On subsequent days I&rsquo;ve squeezed in 2.5L of water. As you imagine, on those days I had more than 1L left. And I finally earned two big blisters at the back of my heels. As I said, new shoes are always a bad idea.</p>

<p>We got back to the hut at about noon. Clément went down to Arolla with another group as he was joining us only for a weekend. We ordered a portion of Rösti which was served on a single plate and looked MASSIVE:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18964181283"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/540/18964181283_7d89bccb8c_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>Each of us took a shower that costs almost as much as a service of a prostitute (6CHF/minute). We then slept from about 14:00 till 16:30. It felt great. We played French scrabble with English words. It felt less great. At 18:30 we had dinner similar to the one the day before though it was complemented with Cordon Bleus. There were only 4 more guests besides us that night. The Vignettes hut has capacity for about a hundred.</p>

<p>Once again I was puzzled to observe that most mountaineers stayed indoors and slept pretty much the whole day. Why do you wake up at 4, climb non-stop for 7-10 hours (leaving no more than 10 minutes to awe at the scenery) and then recess inside from the sun feeling bored? I suppose I&rsquo;m too green to know the answer yet.</p>

<h2>Day 3: Pigne d&#8217;Arolla (3788m) and Cabane des Dix</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653818"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-3.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 8.88km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 791m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 1028m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 5:36&#8217;58.3</p>

<p>The day started a bit earlier. Our goal of the day was to climb peak Pigne d&#8217;Arolla and then get to the next hut Cabane des Dix. The third day felt markedly easier and I could enjoy the process and pay attention to the surroundings. Walking up became more natural. Rope and an axe became my perfect accomplices. The route was also slightly easier than on the days before.</p>

<p>Cabane des Vignettes seen from afar:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578208872"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/407/19578208872_86d6d197aa_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397137400"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/551/19397137400_d684f28ee1_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19558936076"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/525/19558936076_7c4b7b1802_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397145808"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19397145808_340b94e192_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962590944"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/343/18962590944_d6d60d0e13_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>On the way I couldn&rsquo;t stop noticing dormant insects in the snow and ice. How do the insects get there? What&rsquo;s their story? I also wondered what do the blackbirds feed on at such high altitudes. I suppose on those very insects.</p>

<p>I realized that 3 weeks have passed since I left my job. These 3 weeks felt like a year, full of adventure and new experiences. Despite the spike of energy and enthusiasm I felt that a short vacation cannot heal the damage from long-term stress. I am not yet ready to get back into the professional world. I am glad I had an opportunity to discuss my departure plans with a healthcare professional who shared valuable pieces of wisdom. One of the pearls is to plan at least a 6 month retreat. Otherwise you are almost guaranteed to run into the same issues that plagued you.</p>

<p>We finished our day quite early: at 10:45 we reached the hut. The rest of the day was spent either sleeping, reading or eating. I saw a massive serac separate from the mountain top and go down with a loud bang.</p>

<p>Admittedly, the food in Dix was worse than in Vignettes: blander and less of it. Though Dix offered a nice selection of Belgian-style beers and their paid lunch-time food offerings were delicious.</p>

<p>Cabane des Dix upclose:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962604874"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/450/18962604874_5e03521122_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<h2>Day 4: Mont Blanc Cheilon climb (3850m)</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653814"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-4.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 11.63km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 1189m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 1165m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 9:24&#8217;38.7</p>

<p>Dix served breakfast at 4 so we woke up at 3:40. By the fourth day I got used to waking up at 4 and going to bed at 8. I felt rested and fresh. I was also pretty certain that I handle altitude sickness pretty well. I felt no major headache and felt sufficiently energized.</p>

<p>We left the hut in the darkness, head torches illuminating our way. Far away in the distance I could see groups of alpine fireflies wrestling their way up. They must have left the hut even earlier. JD forgot to take water. Luckily he realized it soon enough.</p>

<p>The pre-dawn sky was illuminated by lightnings, another majestic spectacle of nature. The day started windy and cold. The wind on the north face of the mountain added fierceness and a hardcore atmosphere to our ascent. By all measures the longest and hardest day lay ahead.</p>

<p>Following a long stretch of snow lay an icy surface. I looked at Sam to see why did he stop and what he was doing. It was about the time I learn what an ice screw is for. Sam screwed the ice screw into the surface of the ice and attached a quick-draw to it and then routed his rope through the quick-draw. The edifice served as a stability and safety device. Basically, an ice screw serves a belaying purpose and protects a climber in a case of a fall. As the last person in the group, JD has undone the ice screw and put it into this backpack. Permanently leaving expensive equipment in the ice ain&rsquo;t cool.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589486631"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/524/19589486631_b2b4f9d0ea_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589511721"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/353/19589511721_b9bb748abb.jpg" width="333"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397268730"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/559/19397268730_228be73498.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>We approached the rock and took off crampons. The final 100 or so meters involved climbing up the rock ridge. The experience of climbing at almost 4000 meters is very different from climbing at the gym. For one, the mountaineering shoes are not as responsive and trustworthy as the climbing shoes. Second, the backpack is heavy and restricts some of the movements. There were a couple of moves when we had to take the backpacks off and pass them on.</p>

<p>I added a couple of scratches to my helmet as it saved my head from numerous concussions hitting the rock during some of the moves. What a fantastic piece of equipment a helmet is!</p>

<p>The climb felt like an eternity. I can&rsquo;t say I was afraid of the heights or falling down but there were a couple of really gnarly moves when I hesitated a little. At 9:24 we reached Mont Blanc de Cheilon (3850m). Sitting on the calm south face, I ate some gummy bears and nuts to replenish my energy reserves. I congratulated my companions on the successful ascent. Despite minor annoyances we have been extremely lucky to have almost the perfect weather conditions the whole 5 days.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19585219335"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3754/19585219335_2fe7b60b2c_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Going down proved to be harder than climbing up. My brain was really tired from finding paths between the untrustworthy rock. I could barely understand what I was doing. I felt anger and exhaustion building up. Hard moves were actually easier because my muscles had plenty of capacity. My mind was the real bottleneck. I was glad once the rock section was over. That moment I knew that it&rsquo;s all downhill from there.</p>

<p>On the way back Sam said it would be nice to practice slides on the slope to learn to properly use an ice axe for emergency braking. We were away from the dangerous parts and had our crampons packed. I made a false move and slipped on a patch of ice. Before I realized I was picking up speed and sliding down. Instinctively, I grabbed the axe and tried to stop. Miraculously, I stopped just a few meters short of a fall to a large piece of rock. Sam and JD thought I did that intentionally. They thought I&rsquo;m an impatient learner. The effective technique is to push the axe with both hands into the slope while trying to stand up. I accidentally slipped again so I had yet another opportunity to practice. I said, of course, that the second incident was absolutely intentional and totally controlled.</p>

<p>We were back in the hut at 14:00. I felt really tired and relieved. We had a delicious French crouton with cheese and egg. It was our last day in the mountains so we hoped to take night-time photos of the starlit sky. Unfortunately, thunderstorms came at 20:00 and we ran out of patience to wait for the skies to clear. Instead, we made the best use of the dusk-lit clouds and dramatic light.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19398682479"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/343/19398682479_98312e60f3_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Day 5: back to Arolla</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/341653828"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/arolla/day-5.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p><strong>Total distance:</strong> 8.11 km</p>

<p><strong>Total ascent:</strong> 168m</p>

<p><strong>Total descent:</strong> 1010m</p>

<p><strong>Total time:</strong> 3:24&#8217;19.3</p>

<p>On our final day we woke up at 7. The way back was a piece of cake compared to what we had done on the days before. We crossed small rivers and snow patches and climbed the Pas de Chèvres before trekking down to Arolla.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397321700"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/286/19397321700_470f7acc47_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18964367173"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/340/18964367173_08c9d2c877_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19589594251"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/368/19589594251_0994e0f921_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397321168"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/449/19397321168_fda2b71b93_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578416842"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/381/19578416842_e77c44ed23_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Panorama from <em>Pas de Chèvres</em> before we descend back to Arolla:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397352200"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/305/19397352200_8a7d5fb815_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Panorama on the way back to Arolla:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19578454902"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/542/19578454902_c9d1b3405e_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>A nice surprise at the parking lot, just in time for a zombie apocalypse:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962778214"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/463/18962778214_e357672b0c_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18962783654"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3819/18962783654_cebba175c2_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<h2>Conclusion and final thoughts</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say I had lived in a box. I can&rsquo;t say I hadn&rsquo;t traveled. I can&rsquo;t say I hadn&rsquo;t seen and hadn&rsquo;t been to mountains before. But nothing comes close to the feeling of utter completness and rightness of going through grueling icy and rocky treks up to the peaks and through open vastness of alpine space. Never before I felt so much satisfaction from traveling and exploring the world. For the first time in my life I felt I&rsquo;m doing the right thing and for the first time I felt I couldn&rsquo;t care less about what others are doing. It has been another hardest but greatest thing in my life. I feel infinitely grateful for such a wonderful opportunity to JD, Samuel and Clément. I found the perfect way to explore this beautiful world!</p>

<p>To see all pictures <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/sets/72157655293226359">head over to the Flickr album</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going to a first alpine tour]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T20:07:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m feeling excited because tomorrow I&rsquo;m going on my first alpine tour. It&rsquo;s a 5 day tour and we&rsquo;re going to walk on ice and snow. We&rsquo;re heading to region Valais which is not far from Mont Blanc that I had visited earlier this week.</p>

<p>Although I already have relatively lots of mountain/climbing gear I had to purchase new stiff boots and other stuff. Packing is in progress:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19388461925"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19388461925_fbfcdc2fa9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s hope for good weather and some nice shots!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - walk along the Mont Blanc massif]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-walk-along-the-mont-blanc-massif/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T19:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-walk-along-the-mont-blanc-massif</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Weather conditions in Mont Blanc, France, has been favorable this week. So we spontaneously decided to visit it. On a last year&rsquo;s visit we were unlucky as the region was covered in clouds and it was raining so we couldn&rsquo;t see a thing nor go for a walk.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/mini-rescue.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/mini-rescue.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>On the way to Mont Blanc we experienced what it feels like to have a car tire burst while going at highway speeds. Nothing exciting or dangerous. Our rental car did not have a spare wheel and the tire was torn to shreds so we had to call evacuation. All in all, only 1.5 hours lost on the incident.</p>

<p>View on the Chamonix valley from Le Brevent (2525m):
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19381644792"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/554/19381644792_64f9d222ac_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Sea of BMWs in front of a hotel in Chamonix:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19391942881"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3890/19391942881_7cac61d22f.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18765297154"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3721/18765297154_1e1ddf9b0f.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>View from Aiguille du Midi (3842m):
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19200252688"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/480/19200252688_f143f767da_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19201648069"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/333/19201648069_d1b9f7057a_c.jpg" width="534"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19200260208"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/279/19200260208_06439980f5_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18767235873"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/554/18767235873_925ba40e10_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We walked Grand Balcon Nord:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19201677669"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/291/19201677669_ea9a59f765_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Largest French glacier Mer de Glace:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19381717072"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/345/19381717072_138f99c95d_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - summer walk in Flumserberg]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-summer-walk-in-flumserberg/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T15:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-summer-walk-in-flumserberg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Flumserberg is a popular ski destination because it is close to Zürich. But it&rsquo;s also beautiful in summer. I&rsquo;ve visited Flumserberg last Sunday for an easy downhill walk.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s popular with paragliders:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19386191331"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/530/19386191331_9aef97c250.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>Mountain shed:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18759578714"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/450/18759578714_eb6e694879.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Panoramic view from the top:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19194506120"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/294/19194506120_ff4a69f39a_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Säschmoor peak (2196m):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19195944569"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/307/19195944569_9f62063cde_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Seebenalp hotel / restaurant:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18761495393"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/268/18761495393_5e8054afd9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Longest non-stop bicycle ride in my life]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T07:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After gruesome 27+ hours of cycling I feel elated to announce that I have successfully completed the challenge! I have cycled non-stop for 420.8 kilometers, climbing 4953 metres worth of hills and obstacles along the way. The ride has been the greatest physical challenge I&rsquo;ve done in my life. <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/">The longest non-stop hike goes to 2nd place now</a>.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a short summary of the ride:</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/400km_ride.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/400km_ride.png" width="500"></a></p>

<p><em>Total distance</em>: 420.8km</p>

<p><em>Total vertical ascent</em>: 4953m</p>

<p><em>Difficulty</em>: <strong>extreme</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/333204904">Strava</a> and direct <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/files/400km-ride.gpx">GPS track download</a></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s me before the ride, view from the balcony:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19173125451"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/260/19173125451_593fb0dee8_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<h2>Planning and preparation</h2>

<p>The idea to set a new personal cycling distance record came to me rather unexpectedly while me and my wife were visiting Rodos last week. You see, relaxing beach vacations are not my thing. I suppose a 400km ride is a complementary yan for the beach vacation yin.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t obsessed over planning the route. I consulted the Swiss national cycling network and picked the easiest (in terms of elevation changes) one that was long enough. I decided on route number 9. Since the route was 100 kilometers too long I left out the first two sections.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.veloland.ch/de/routen/route-09.html">Route 9</a></p>

<p>I studied the map and the elevation chart. I have split the whole route in three major sections to make it digestible to my fragile and wimpy mind:</p>

<ol>
<li>the hardest 170 kilometers, involving a fair amount of climbs at night</li>
<li>medium-difficulty 80 kilometers, mostly already familiar to me</li>
<li>the easiest and flattest remaining 170 kilometers</li>
</ol>


<p>A long ride requires sufficient nutrition. Strava has estimated that I have burned 16k calories. Insufficient hydration and nutrition guarantee failure and muscle cramps. Prior to departure I stuffed two large meals into myself. I also purchased plenty of sport bars and drink mixes. In addition, I carried few fruits and sausages:
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18547057214"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/395/18547057214_e599a9e733_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Finally, I asked for live support from my friends. You offered priceless cheering. Without your support I would have given up!</p>

<h2>Transit</h2>

<p>Getting to the starting point took me almost 4 hours, 3 trains and a bus. I had to leave home at about 18:15 to get to Gstaad at 22:30. I started the ride at night to tackle climbs while I was still fresh and unencumbered with sleep deprivation. I wish I could have slept more before the ride but the excitement prevented me from dozing off.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18981916410"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/440/18981916410_f34a47793b_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<h2>The first section</h2>

<p>First section of the route was meant to be difficult and involve a fair amount of hill climbing. Even though I knew the elevation chart the route felt more demanding than I expected. The first few kilometers were especially unpleasant and I had all sorts of negative thoughts in my head. Darkness, headaches and a slight nausea did little to improve the mood. To fool myself I pretended that I&rsquo;m going to go home once the first section is over.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18983445849"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/378/18983445849_e167a069a1_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19143425246"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/446/19143425246_60568cd5c2_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>At about 5 in the morning, as the sun was slowly rising behind mountains, I climbed Brünig pass. Getting over the pass broke a psychological barrier. I knew that the worst uphill is over even as the elapsed distance was still insignificant.</p>

<p>At some point I felt really sleepy and decided to take an hour nap on a bench in a forest. I&rsquo;ve managed to get 30 minutes of sleep as the body was all too excited to rest for too long.</p>

<h2>The second section</h2>

<p>By the time I finished the first section I realized that I am hopelessly behind the original optimistic estimates. I was already 2 hours behind. Making it on time for the last train back home quickly morphed into an unrealistic fantasy. Fantasies are better suited for sitting at home with a cup of warm tea in front of a fireplace.</p>

<p>Predictably, I could not imagine riding the remaining 250 kilometers. I fooled myself again into cycling to the end of second section where my wife met me for lunch in a cafe. To make up for the slow speed I pushed really hard to finish by 16:00.</p>

<p>At the top of the last hill before a speedy descent into Pfäffikon I met a Swiss couple who were leisurely cycling and appreciating the scenery. After a quick exchange of pleasantries the man asked whether I&rsquo;m &ldquo;genießen&rdquo; (enjoying) my ride. His tone and posture made me imagine him with a glass of fine whiskey and a cigar: &ldquo;Sir, are you enjoying the splendid surroundings of Schwyz?&rdquo;. &ldquo;Most certainly, what an exquisite enjoyment it is&rdquo;.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19169589025"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/357/19169589025_5e96b94d99_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Pushing hard payed off as I remarkably arrived at 16:00 sharp! I gulped down a few glasses of delicous lemonade and ordered a main course.</p>

<h2>The final section</h2>

<p>Less than a half remained and I spinned enthusiastically. I went fast for about 4 hours before breaking down again. A proper meal feels substantial compared to sugary drinks and sport bars that burn out quickly and leave a sore aftertaste. I stopped for a quick meal at McDonalds and continued to the final 6 hour stretch.</p>

<p>Surprisingly, my leg muscles did not show any signs of exhaustion. My ass, on the other hand, hurt as hell! I suppose no matter how great a bicycle seat is it&rsquo;s no match for 27 hour rides. The pain is unavoidable. Moving around just makes things worse.</p>

<p>I started to have hallucinations. I found a good solution: to focus on the road and avoid looking at any objects, especially if the objects seem interesting.</p>

<p>The final 10 kilometers felt like an eternity: so far no matter how close. Time perception gets really distorted in moments like these.</p>

<h2>Arrival and going home</h2>

<p>I arrived at 01:45 in the morning to the city of Rorschach. As most German or Swiss towns it was completely dead and quiet at night. The first train left at 05:40 and none of the hotels had a 24-hour reception. I went to the train station and parked my bike next to a bench and tried to stay warm. I was uncontrollably shaking because my clothing was too thin for sitting still. The good thing about sleep deprivation though is that it makes time fly. Every time I peaked on my wristwatch from waking up from cold the time advanced 30-40 minutes. Time flies when you&rsquo;re sleep deprived!</p>

<h2>Impressions</h2>

<p>It has been an extraordinary ride. I would have never completed it if I knew all the gory detail of the terrain or that 15-20% of roads were unpaved. More than anything, it has been a battle with the mind. My mind was endlessly coming up with excuses to make a stop to end the suffering. But there was only one good way to stop the suffering: get to the destination. At that is achieved by spinning faster and not by having stops every 5 minutes.</p>

<p>When I arrived in the middle of night at the destination shaking from hypothermia I was thinking of a warm bed, food and my beloved wife. In that moment I truly appreciated how much a place called home means to me. I wanted to go back to the beach vacation I berated so much&hellip;</p>

<p>But a good night sleep clears up even the muddiest minds. As soon as I woke up fresh and rested I dismissed the mumbo jumbo and started to plan another adventure. Challenge is an indispensable part of my identity and it&rsquo;s about time I finally learn it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Across Switzerland in one day]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/23/across-the-switzerland-in-one-day/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-23T09:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/23/across-the-switzerland-in-one-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/">Success! I&rsquo;ve managed to complete the ride, totaling 420.8 km and 4953m of vertical ascent in 27 hours of biking.</a></p>

<p>Last year I&rsquo;ve successfully completed a <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/200401002">300km bicycle day ride</a> and earned a new personal record for distance. On a wonderful day of today I&rsquo;m going to set a new personal record and ride for 400-or-so kilometers across Switzerland in less than 24 hours.</p>

<p>My route follows a slightly shortened version of the official Swiss route number 9:</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/400km_ride.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/400km_ride.png" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The preparations are off to a rocky start. After thoroughly cleaning the bike and relubing mechanical parts I couldn&rsquo;t get flat pedals off. I&rsquo;d like to ride this distance with clipless pedals for higher efficiency.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19079701705"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/368/19079701705_b4b79347b8.jpg" width="213"></a><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18459001303"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/497/18459001303_24d1ceb4e1_n.jpg" width="480"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to pay a visit to a local bike shop today and see if they can get them off. If not I&rsquo;ll have to keep using the flat pedals and possibly replace the whole crankset upon returning. That&rsquo;s an expensive way to learn to apply liberal amounts of anti-seize compound! Anyway, I&rsquo;ve somehow managed to ride 300km on the flats last year so perhaps it&rsquo;s not such a big problem after all.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve studied the route and divided it into 3 parts. The first 160km are the hardest: there are a couple of hills and one pass on the way. The second section is 80km and is of medium difficulty. The last part is almost as a flat as possible on this planet, starting with a fast descent.</p>

<p>As soon as I get over the first part I can make a deep breath. And once two sections are behind it&rsquo;s a piece of cake and I just need to make sure I don&rsquo;t fall of the bike due to sleep deprivation. I&rsquo;m also going to turn off any time-keeping and elapsed distance displays to keep my spirits going against the monstrous remaining distance.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m packing lots of high-calorie snacks and substances, such as protein and sport bars, sport drink mixtures and magnesium tablets. I plan to make one stop for lunch in Pfäffikon at about 14:00 in a cafe <a href="http://cellos-essbar.ch/">Cello&rsquo;s ESSBAR</a>. My wife plans to join me.</p>

<p>I am starting the ride today <strong>2015-06-23</strong> at <strong>22:30 CET</strong> (<strong>13:30 US/Pacific</strong>) from a town called Gstaad. I plan to arrive at the destination town Rorschach no later than <strong>2015-06-24</strong> at <strong>22:00 CET</strong> (<strong>13:00 US/Pacific</strong>). If I don&rsquo;t make it on time there is a risk there won&rsquo;t be any trains going and I will be stranded either in Rorscharh or Zürich Hauptbahnof.</p>

<p>I will be posting regular updates on my Facebook as I go and I will publish a full write-up once I come back and recover after a healthy amount of sleep. My dear friends, I need your full support to get through this!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Startlit silk factory]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/18/startlit-silk-factory/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T21:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/18/startlit-silk-factory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I always wanted to experiment with night photographs of the sky. A pre-requisite is a clear sky and as little light pollution as possible. The island of Rodos in Greece is a perfect contender.</p>

<p>Me and my wife took our little rental car and drove along the road while we searched for pitch black spots and possible places to stop. We found an ancient silk factory:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18314135863"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/starlit-rodos.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>The result seems okay for a first try. I admit it was a bit scary to stand alone in the darkness in a middle of nowhere.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I have quit an awesome job]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-16T19:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18863676532"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3716/18863676532_dd50531ca1_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>I woke up at five in the morning today and headed to the airport with my beloved wife to fly out to celebrate our wedding anniversary on one of the beautiful Greek islands. As I am typing this on my computer during the flight I do not yet fully comprehend that our vacation is not going to end like most vacations do: two weeks later at the office. That is because earlier in May I inked a decision to voluntarily resign from one of the best places to work in the world. Since I made the announcement I have been predominantly asked three questions:</p>

<ol>
<li>Why are you leaving?</li>
<li>What are you going to do next?</li>
<li>What are you going to do during your break?</li>
</ol>


<p>I would like to share what made me make such a difficult decision. Hopefully, this short reflection helps others in their search of meaning and happiness. Writing also helps me to make sense of my own life and turn ephemeral, and often confusing, thoughts into concrete insights.</p>

<p><strong>tldr;</strong> answers are as follows: to discover my true passion, I don&rsquo;t know for certain, nothing for a while and then prepare for whatever I choose next.</p>

<p>There was nothing rash or sudden in my actions. If anything, I thought about it beforehand obsessively for several years. The balance of scales was finally disturbed last year when I went on a four week motorcycle tour of Norway and Sweden. Time alone on the road did not give many opportunities to think as I was preoccupied with looking for the fun roads, food and places to stay. But reflections, insights and thoughts stormed their way into my mind in the aftermath, as I reached home. Despite the engine roar, the twists and various incidents I felt calm and free during my little adventure. I felt no worry. But upon returning to the daily work routine the contrast was so stark that my hands began to shake. Stress has quickly re-established its elevated residency which I had not ever noticed before the trip. The background stress is toxic to the body but it is difficult to detect, just like the frog can&rsquo;t notice increasingly hot water it&rsquo;s in until the poor creature boils to death.</p>

<p>It is then that it became obvious to me that I must change either my ways of living or my attitude if I want to exist harmoniously and happily. It something easier said in hindsight as there&rsquo;s rarely a clear unambiguous signal to act in our complex entangled lives. History does not exist while the events are still unfolding. Similarly, factors and reasons rarely come together as neatly as they seem in the retrospect. Furthermore, real decisions usually have a steep price to pay and require to give up something valuable in return. I value and cherish many things that my way of living has given me up to the pivotal moment. Few other have had such gifts from the lady fortune. I found it difficult to seek understanding and support as there are few people I know who wouldn&rsquo;t label me a self-entitled ungrateful and wasteful bastard.</p>

<p>Fear is the other force to hold back. Fear held me a prisoner for years. One expects fear to be pretty obvious though I found it anything but. I have some credentials to back up my stance. In the last couple of years I skydived AFF (which means I did the first jump solo, unlike being strapped to another skydiver in a tandem), rode down-hill mountain bike trails, rode a 200 horsepower motorbike around a race track and did some other feats considered scary and risky by (mostly incorrect) common sense. I know what the obvious fear feels like. The fear of change is different: it lies dormant like a crocodile that snaps its deadly claws upon the motion of potential prey. Only in the case of fear the prey is any kind of uncertainty and change. Human nature is soaked with the poison of fear and we don&rsquo;t realize it.</p>

<p>What was I in? By any objective measure I lived in a paradise: being part of one of the best companies in the world that has shaped humanity and will do so in the foreseeable decades. The compensation, perks, free food and amazing office facilities are nothing to complain about. Nor do humane bosses, tolerant atmosphere, intelligent colleagues, space for initiative and considerable freedom to choose what to work on. Yet something has been amiss from the head start: passion. From the moment I started I did not enjoy what I was doing. I struggled initially but over time I learned skills that made me adapt and grow tolerant. I even excelled by the prevailing performance standards. At times there were assignments that got me really excited but 80% of my work felt empty.</p>

<p>I have not spent the time lazily complaining about the circumstances. I used the opportunity to find meaning outside of profession. I tried out more hobbies than I have toes and fingers combined. I studied and worked on side projects and ideas. I devoured in an intimate relationship with my then-girlfriend wife. I traveled. I read ferociously. I went beyond the confines of my nature-given introversion to meet people and make friendships. I pursued spirituality. But there is only so much time in 24 hours. Dealing with work that does not excite saps you of energy and eventually shrinks the energy capacity. I had genuine opportunities at the company to change into a line of work that is closer to my interests but failed to seize them due to unfortunate combination of reasons. By now I have got very little energy left and I definitely couldn&rsquo;t pull two jobs at once which is somewhat a prerequisite for a successful transfer. I don&rsquo;t see how passion can be compensated. I feel that no amount of hobbies, relationships and interests can compensate an occupation that is out of line with one&rsquo;s values and passions.</p>

<p>Despite what the articles and books say discovering passion is not that obvious. The typical premise is to follow one&rsquo;s goals and values but if it was so simple there wouldn&rsquo;t be so many confused and lost souls. Personally, I find the discovery process the most difficult. I don&rsquo;t understand how anyone can know his values and passions without a serious deal of reflection work. I certainly don&rsquo;t believe that one can substitute the hard work with a half an hour exercise. Without trying out various things it&rsquo;s not possible to determine what one is really excited about. Discovering passion is a process of trial and error. Discovery is about exploring further what little we have experienced so far along with finding new turns. It is not unlike navigating a maze.</p>

<p>One serious obstacle to the process of self discovery is the denial of truth. While it&rsquo;s not possible to know what our passions are without trying we can seriously inhibit progress by refusing to pursue our callings. After graduating from university I chose to work outside of my field of interest. To be honest, I wasn&rsquo;t particularly sure what of the many specializations in my field I wanted to pursue either. But ever since I began to work I did not get closer to finding that out. Instead, I thought of hundreds of reasons why pursuing passion isn&rsquo;t worthwhile. With the right financial disincentives failure to ever return on the path of self actualization is almost guaranteed.</p>

<p>It is also puzzling to me why people living in a westernish modern world rarely ever consider taking a long break from work. We live in an era of unprecedented productivity and economic growth. Yet most of us sit chained to our desks for 8-14 hours a day as if we were coal miners of the bygone centuries. It is impossible to perform uninterrupted quality intellectual work for more than a few hours a day. Somehow we conveniently ignore the truth and let our minds rot while we make ourselves look busy and let the hours pass instead of perhaps lifting some weight to make our backs stronger or learning a new skill. Nobody benefits from the idle hours. It&rsquo;s the same with ridiculously short vacations. Two weeks of vacation cannot replenish an exhausted body and mind.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t wait to take a break for too long. If you&rsquo;re not feeling mostly passionate about what you do chances are you will eventually burn out. There&rsquo;s anxiety and depression around the corner and broken relationships and career prospects (who wants under-performers back?). Instead, plan ahead and do it gracefully: go out with a smile and respect, with friendships and good memories. I think I waited a tad too long but at least I did not experience a complete break down. I feel drained professionally but my inner drive is still alive and ready to kick in a high gear after some greasing.</p>

<p>With all of what I have that said, I don&rsquo;t regret the choice I had made years ago. If I had the opportunity to go back in time and make the choice again I would have picked the same option. I believe I made the right decision given the circumstances. I don&rsquo;t blame anyone for the final outcome. If anything, I&rsquo;m grateful to the company, to my bosses and to my colleagues. I strongly believe that the same job could be blissful and highly rewarding under the right mindset and circumstances. I believe life is not meant to be a perfect well rehearsed sequence of &ldquo;nexts&rdquo; and I have very few expectations about the future. Nobody but me has an obligation to make the most out of my life.</p>

<p>Quitting a great job and taking a long break is the most difficult decision I made in my life so far. There&rsquo;s so much I would like to change and to learn and to experience! It&rsquo;s time to recharge, instill new helpful habits and to prepare for whatever I choose as my next challenge.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twenty first CENTURY ride]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-11T18:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On a hot Sunday I have joined a couple of cycling enthusiasts to cover an imperial century in the vicinity of canton Zurich:</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/century-ride.png"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/century-ride.png" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I have not ridden a road bike for about a year. This was the first serious ride for the bike I had picked up on a sale last year:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18091049284"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/451/18091049284_e1861dc5f6_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>It is equipped with one of those fancy Di2 drive-trains which I &ldquo;hacked&rdquo; to extend the standard 10-speed casette to a 11-speed one.</p>

<p><em>Total distance</em>: 162.3km</p>

<p><em>Total vertical ascent</em>: 1182m</p>

<p><em>Difficulty</em>: easy</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/files/century-ride.gpx">Download GPS (direct)</a></p>

<p>The ride went much smoother and faster than I expected. I forgot just how much difference there is between a mountain bike and a road bike. Keeping a speed of 25-30kmh on flats is so much less effort than my trusted Salsa Fargo.</p>

<p>There is definitely less comfort on this bike. I could ride my Fargo for 300km per day and feel no pain or discomfort. My hands were definitely tired after a day of riding on the road bike. I couldn&rsquo;t imagine going on a tour on a bike like this.</p>

<p>A scenic view from a hill nearby Wetzikon:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18713735765"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/499/18713735765_5b30f14a0e_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
