<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-13T17:29:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-13T07:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the part 2 of cyclocross bicycle build series. <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1/">Jump to part 1</a>.</p>

<h2>Disassembly preparation</h2>

<p>With the bicycle, materials, tools and parts figured out I was ready to begin the disassembly process. Taking things apart is fun and bicycles are not exception to this rule. As a guide
I reversed the <a href="http://www.parktool.com/blog/repair-help/new-bike-assembly">bike assembly order from Parking Tool website</a>. The process starts with the chain removal and continue along the drive train until the levers and controls are taken off.</p>

<p>With the tools and parts laid before me I went into the process with ecstasy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817164744/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7409/13817164744_0587cab273.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>At first I hoped to borrow a bike stand from a friend or a colleague. Nobody replied so I purchased my own. It is a lot more convenient to work on bicycles on a proper bike stand. I used to rely on a kickstand or improvisation. With a task such as a whole bicycle assembly ad-hoc solutions become unwieldy and frustrating. I purchased Park Tool PRS-1 stand.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13816855625/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3755/13816855625_3af3d95b3a.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Cube Cross Disc bicycle looks good on its own. I really like the color scheme. I have purchased a couple of &ldquo;pimping&rdquo; parts to improve aesthetics even further. Things like blue bolts and cable housing, blue jockey wheels and quick release axles.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817174464/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3667/13817174464_b859ee38eb_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Getting down to it</h2>

<p>There is nothing inherently difficult in taking a bicycle apart when the right tools are at hand. It&rsquo;s actually a precise and highly satisfying work.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817191184/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3826/13817191184_85d1bbb951_c.jpg" width="800"></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817196104/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7102/13817196104_3f29842c79_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Part by part the bicycle was slowly dissolving until only a frame and wheels remained. A bicycle is a really good illusion. Initially, it appears complex, intricate and intimidating with all the seemingly difficult adjustments. However, once a bicycle is stripped of parts comes a realization of its simplicity and elegance.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13816877555/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7156/13816877555_c9bf7d2df7_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13816908133/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3735/13816908133_c7c1c33716_n.jpg" width="320"></a>
<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817212254/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7273/13817212254_04dbe440da_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817216684/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2864/13817216684_93c23682ac_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>The disassembly went on and on until the bicycle looked like this. Note that for the following shot I&rsquo;ve already put different wheels on. I&rsquo;ve left the old cables inside to guide the insertion of new ones.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817240244/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2890/13817240244_9fec281f8e_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Shimano 105 component groupset used to power this bike. Now it&rsquo;s going to be replaced with Shimano Ultegra 6800. I will have a bunch of parts that I need to sell. I don&rsquo;t fancy cluttering my place with too many random spare parts and pieces. Hopefully, there are enough bike enthusiasts at work to claim most of them.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13817220944/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3800/13817220944_263098d928_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Wheels</h2>

<p>I have never had tubeless road bicycle tires. The assembly process was a bit unusual. Putting road tires on the Stan&rsquo;s Alpha 340 wheelset was relatively painless. But I had typical problems putting cyclocross Raven tires on Alpha 400 even though I had installed the recommended additional rim strip. The problem was the tires did not seal and air went out. Tires would not inflate sufficiently to seal the gaps and air would get out. The solution was to unscrew the valve and let it move inside of the tire for initial setup. Then, I had to pump really hard to reach a critical pressure point. At the same time I was throwing the wheel up slightly so that the tire would fall into place. Still at the same time I screwed the valve back in. This maddening sequence went on until I&rsquo;ve noticed that the air is not escaping as fast as it did initially. An air compressor would come in handy because it would be much easier to reach critical inflation point. Some folks report success with CO2 cartridges.</p>

<p>My complete order from notubes.com contained the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Alpha 340 cyclocross wheelset, Shimano 11 speed</li>
<li>Alpha 400 cyclocross wheelset, Shimano 11 speed</li>
<li>Stan&rsquo;s quart of tire sealant</li>
<li>Stan&rsquo;s sealant injector</li>
<li>2x Hutchison 3 tubeless tire</li>
<li>2x Raven tubeless tire</li>
<li>Core remover (to inject sealant into tire without removing it)</li>
</ul>


<p>Stans Alpha 400 wheelset with Raven cyclocross tires (700x35). I&rsquo;ll use this wheelset mostly for winter commuting. I also want to try riding off road courses on this bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13816932095/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3714/13816932095_d87f572a38_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Stans Alpha 340 wheelset with Hutchison 3 road tires (700x23). Beautiful.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13816939075/in/set-72157643416319013"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5319/13816939075_c8885af847_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Did I mention that Stan&rsquo;s 3.30 hubs freewheel sound gorgeous?</p>

<h2>Newly discovered alternatives</h2>

<p>I discovered that it is possible to buy decent bicycle frames directly from Chinese manufacturers. Initially, I was skeptical but as I read people&rsquo;s reports it appears that the quality is acceptable. A carbon cyclocross frame costs 500-600$ &ndash; much lower than about 2000$ most manufacturers would ask for. It&rsquo;s also possible to slap a custom paint job on it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee experiment 2 months later]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-07T16:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After I had initially <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/">experimented with drinking enormous amounts of coffee per day</a> I abandoned coffee completely. The side effects were too bothersome. I slept too long, crashed too hard during the day and felt pronounced headaches unless I&rsquo;ve drank a cup a day. Two extremes got me thinking &ndash; could I perhaps find an optimal middle ground?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13697133974/"><img class="left" src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/13697133974_4624909376_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" title="'My favorite cup'" ></a></p>

<p>With that in mind I&rsquo;ve attempted a moderate approach. I have consumed at most 2 cups (or equivalent amount of caffeine-containing substances) a day. One cup almost immediately upon waking up and another one after lunch or in the afternoon. The morning coffee ritual became essential as I made a push away from evenings into early mornings. I have realized that with a full time job doing anything extra curricular in the evenings is difficult as there is little energy left. Now, I mostly use evenings for being with my wife, reading and relaxing. Of course, there are occasional activities so exciting that even low energy can&rsquo;t stop me. Mornings is a completely different story. When fully rested I feel energized to work on difficult yet fun stuff. For example, every morning for the past 2 months (with rare exceptions) I&rsquo;ve been studying German. I cannot imagine to study a foreign language in the evening. I feel tired, unmotivated and learning feels like a drag. In the long term I hope to gradually break into a habit of waking up at something like 5am while going to bed at 9pm or so. I&rsquo;ll leave the evenings for wine and cigars.</p>

<p>Do I notice any side effects? Not really. I don&rsquo;t feel too bad on days that I miss coffee. I don&rsquo;t get insomnia after drinking an espresso shot at 7pm. I don&rsquo;t feel particularly cranky. I don&rsquo;t crash at 3-5pm.</p>

<p>Moderate amount of caffeine gives a subtle but noticeable mental boost. I am pleased with the results. I will likely continue the practice indefinitely. Perhaps I am stating the obvious with this experiment. Most people consume 1-2 cups a day anyway. In everyday life I take a lot of things for granted. But sometimes, I like to take out a piece of my life-style and change it to see if the change makes a difference. More often than not I arrive at trite conclusions and revert to the old ways. In rare cases I change my habits significantly. But in either case I come out with a better understanding of myself.</p>

<p>I should insert a disclaimer that I don&rsquo;t pay much for coffee. It is free at work and at home I use an inexpensive capsule-based coffee maker. Occasionally (i.e. once every two months or so) I go for an extravagant drink at a coffee shop. If I had to pay for every coffee it costs in coffee shops I would abandon the practice very quickly. Sorry, but very few people realize just how expensive their coffee habit really is.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-03T16:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Prologue</h2>

<p>There is a trend I noticed myself going through. First, I tend to acquire lots of equipment and accessories for a hobby or an activity. Then I realize what my true needs are. At some point I get overwhelmed with the gear I don&rsquo;t use regularly and feel wasteful. Finally, I minimize possessions by trading them to fewer precious alternatives. I went through this process with <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/21/5-sold-gadgets-later-or-welcome-back-to-microsoft-windows/">PCs</a> and <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/08/28/impressions-from-freenas/">servers</a>, laptops, digital cameras, motorcycles and now I&rsquo;m going through the same with bicycles. I know it&rsquo;s extravagant and uneconomical. The upside is that I end up with a few possessions that I use extensively and which are satisfying to utilize. Also, once settled on fewer things I lose desire to upgrade or change them.</p>

<p>Until recently I used to own a 2011 Specialized Tarmac carbon road bike. However, I have ridden it only twice last year. I did most of my riding on a full suspension mountain bike and on a <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/">hybrid bike</a> that I also commute on. I don&rsquo;t like things lying around without use. So I made a decision to sell two of my bicycles and replace them with a single bike that performs satisfactory under most of my use cases.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675646804"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7341/11675646804_4d2d831b20.jpg" width="350"></a></p>

<p>Having gone through experience of upgrading many of the bike components on my bikes I realized that I actually want to have a go at my own build. I am not a mechanics wizard but I&rsquo;ve done many maintenance tasks that are considered difficult, like replacing entire drive-trains, adjusting gear systems and bleeding hydraulic disc brakes. It is generally more expensive to assemble a bike from parts than buying a complete brand new bicycle. With a good deal on a used bike/frame the total price could be manageable but I am jumping ahead of myself.</p>

<h2>The right bike type</h2>

<p>Before venturing into buying or building a bike I think it&rsquo;s useful to think about the use cases. How and where am I going to ride the bike? Am I going to do competitive racing? Am I going to commute on it? Am I going to stay on roads or do occasional gravel? Am I going to ride centuries? Am I going to tour on it? There is no such thing as a perfect bike for everything and there are compromises to be had.</p>

<p>I settled on a hybrid bike the first time I bought a bike. Since then I&rsquo;ve been riding a road bike and a full suspension mountain bike. In retrospective, a hybrid was a poor choice. I do most of riding on paved roads and a road bike is more efficient. Recently I got intrigued by cyclo-cross bicycles. Cyclo-cross bikes are road bikes converted for off-road riding. Cyclo-cross bikes have drop bars and their frame geometries look similar. However, the tires are threaded and often knobbed. Wheels are tougher. Brakes are better and designed for mud and dirt. The frames accommodate larger tires and are designed for maneuverability and often are less aggressive than regular road bikes.</p>

<p>Cyclo-cross seems like a great all-round choice. With tougher wheels and tires cyclo-cross could work well as a commuter. Some frames are outfitted with eyelets so installing a pannier rack is a breeze. In-line brake levers are found more often on cyclo-cross than on road bikes. These levers look like regular flat bar levers and are installed in addition to the default drop bar integrated levers.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/inline.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/inline.jpg" width="400"></a></p>

<p>With a second lightweight wheelset and narrow tires a cyclo-cross turns into a proper road cycle. Of course, a dedicated well engineered road bike is better fit for the job but unless it&rsquo;s about racing competitively the cyclo-cross disadvantages will not make a noticeable difference. An extra weight in a backpack of recreational riders defeats many efficiency gains allowed by lighter and more efficient rides.</p>

<p>Personally, I want to commute by this bike to work 15km every day all year round (even in snow and rain) with ortlieb panniers mounted in the back. Occasionally, I want to keep up with my road-biking friends on weekend rides. I am not a weight weenie (biking term) but I don&rsquo;t fancy heavy steel bikes either. Sometimes, I like to take an odd gravel road. And I want to do lightweight touring. Specifically, I am going on a 1200km ride across Europe in May. Does cyclo-cross fit the bill? I bet it does!</p>

<h2>Preparation</h2>

<p>Bike sizing is important. A bike that does not fit a rider well will cause discomfort and pain. Ultimately, nobody will ride a bike that&rsquo;s uncomfortable regardless of how great it is. Hence, it is a good idea to understand how bikes and frames are sized. I admit my knowledge of fitting had been spotty and my beliefs were wrong. The only bike in my stall that fits me like a glove is my mountain bike. And that&rsquo;s by pure chance! The hybrid is a size too small and the road bike had not been setup properly causing too much strain on the lower back. I&rsquo;ve been riding the hybrid for 3 years now. It&rsquo;s unbelievable how much more comfortable riding has become after I&rsquo;ve reconfigured it recently. Now, there are a lot of conflicting sizing techniques and practices. Some say that one must undergo professional computer laser controlled measuring. I think it&rsquo;s bullshit. The only importance is comfort. As long as you can ride comfortably according to your needs you&rsquo;re fine. It does not matter if you were measured with a laser or with a mirror or by a patient friend. Comfort needs could be different. A trained cyclist can stay lower (to be more efficient and aero dynamic) with higher thresholds for discomfort. A recreational cyclist will prefer a more upright position and a smaller difference between seat and handlebar heights.</p>

<p>Bike frames are generally sized according to cyclist&rsquo;s height assuming typical body proportions. In reality, people vary greatly. I am not going to repeat what others have written on the subject. I found a couple great sizing guides that also explain the different frame measurements. The <a href="http://bikedynamics.co.uk/bikesizingbd.htm">guide at BikeDynamics</a> is my favorite. My height is 6&#8217;2 and my body has typical proportions. According to the sizing charts I should be looking at frames sized 58-60cm. There is a chance that a bike won&rsquo;t be comfortable even if the numbers appear perfect. That&rsquo;s why I consider comfort and not the measuring precision of the utmost importance. With the correct frame size decided many finer adjustments could be made. The four popular adjustments I know are: saddle height, fore-aft position, handlebar height and stem length/angle. Again, I am no authority to give much advice so search YouTube for practical instructions. The one <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FAl_5e7bIHk">from Performance Bicycle</a> is my favorite.</p>

<p>How much experience is needed to put a bike together from scratch? I am not the one to judge because I have not assembled any yet. However, I fiddled with bicycles for as long as I remember. In the past couple of years I replaced entire drive trains, tuned gearing and blead hydraulic disc brakes. I did not find anything difficult in the process. There are lots of detailed instructions available on YouTube for almost any component. In addition, all bike component manufacturers provide service manuals for their components. I was able to replace a broken hydraulic brake lever for SRAM X0 system. Sure, I needed a couple of specialized tools from eBay and a bit of patience but that&rsquo;s about it! If I went to a bike shop I believe they would replace the whole component. For me, it&rsquo;s not about the money (though a complete SRAM X0 handlebar brake is certainly not cheap). I find that fixing things is fun. To fill in gaps in my bike maintenance knowledge a picked up a copy of <a href="http://www.parktool.com/product/big-blue-book-of-bicycle-repair-3rd-edition-BBB-3">Big Blue Book of Bicycle Repair</a>. The book is great and offers lots of advice that is neatly presented. I discovered subtleties that I was never aware of. Such knowledge makes for a proud and confident owner of a cycle because one knows how all the parts were put together!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13627957304/"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3814/13627957304_77572a176d_z.jpg" width="640" height="427" title="'So what is this chain whip for?'" ></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13627964604/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2940/13627964604_31bc8ae254_z.jpg" width="640" height="427" title="'Aaah, this blue book has all the answers!'" ></a></p>

<p>Working with bicycles requires tools. I&rsquo;ve been slowly acquiring them one by one whenever I had to do maintenance tasks. I don&rsquo;t like the idea of buying a kit because a kit usually contains several tools that are never used and a kit misses a few important ones. For example, a chain rivet tool (that disconnects/reconnects chain links) must be compatible with the chain. Older tools won&rsquo;t work with newer 11 speed chains. The bottom bracket tool depends on the kind of bottom bracket a bike has. I think it&rsquo;s better to know exactly what tools are needed by studying the components of the bike. A good complete tool set costs dearly. But if fiddling with bikes is a joy for you I think it&rsquo;s a healthy expense. Borrowing tools sounds great in theory but I personally would not borrow out my tools unless I have high regard for the person&rsquo;s practice. I revised the tools I already own and added the following ones to my collection:</p>

<ul>
<li>Park tool bike stand (building a bike without one sounds like hell to me)</li>
<li>set of allen keys</li>
<li>chain wear indicator</li>
<li>chain cleaner</li>
<li>chain whip</li>
<li>shimano cassette lockring tool</li>
<li>socket and bit set for a torque wrench (I already own two torque wrenches)</li>
<li>greaser, lubricants, degreaser and assembly paste</li>
</ul>


<p>With the preparation behind me comes the excitement of ordering the shiny new parts.</p>

<h2>I chose&hellip;</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned that building a bicycle from scratch is certainly not cheap. Next comes buying brand new followed by used and last-season bikes. The smartest thing is to buy used. In Switzerland, things on the secondary market are usually of great quality and had been cared for meticulously. The prices are at 30-50% of the original retail price. Sometimes, though, there is just no bike that really fits the bill. I found myself in a such situation. I knew I wanted a cyclo-cross so I went through dozens of bike manufacturers&#8217; websites to find the best match. I saw bikes which were expensive (e.g. 5k$ for certain Specialized Crux models) and bikes that did not have equipment or the gearing I wanted. Also, I did not fancy the idea of buying brand new knowing how fast these things depreciate. At some point I entertained the idea of starting a new build from scratch. So I went through another round of websites but this time looked at frames. Unfortunately, I could not find a reasonably priced frame (carbon or aluminium) with the features I needed (disc brakes, eyelets for panniers) and pleasing to the eye. The frame I liked the most is <a href="http://www.specialized.com/us/en/bikes/road/crux/crux-pro-frameset">Specialized Crux Pro Disc</a>. But after factoring in the price (even with a 15% discount) I decided to look for something else. <a href="http://www.specialized.com/us/en/bikes/road/crux/crux-e5-disc-frameset">Specialized Crux E5 Disc</a> would almost be it but it&rsquo;s not sold in Europe and I don&rsquo;t like the color.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/crux_pro_disc_frame.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/crux_pro_disc_frame.jpg" width="300"></a> <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/crux_e5_disc_frame.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/crux_e5_disc_frame.jpg" width="300"></a></p>

<p>As I was getting desperate to find a bicycle I looked at a local bike advertisement board velomarkt.ch. It is a great place for finding cycles. That&rsquo;s where I had found my mountain bike. After spreading the word a couple of my friends found their bikes there too. Miraculously, there was a used cyclo-cross bike for sale in the size I needed (59cm) not very far from where I live. The bike was an aluminum Cube Cross Disc cycle from last year. I have contacted the seller and after a short exchange and some bargaining I hopped on a train and went to Luzern to pick it up.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube0.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube0.jpg" width="400"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube1.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube1.jpg" width="400"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube2.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube2.jpg" width="400"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube3.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/cube3.jpg" width="400"></a></p>

<p>The bike was in great condition! Seller said he has put about 800km on it. The bike was fresh out of service and the recalled disc brake calipers (Shimano CX-75) had been already swapped with the improved CX-77 version.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve reviewed the specs of the bike thoroughly and went through many articles and photos. It&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.tour-magazin.de/technik/test_center/raeder/rennraeder/cube-cross-race-disc/a29109.html">not praised highly by reviewers</a> and it does not come with fancy components. However, I was not looking for paper figures &ndash; I was searching for something specific, something that would work well for me. And it appears this bike is very close to what I need! The bike has relaxed geometry &ndash; perfect for recreational riding. It even has eyelets for rack installation. I think the bike looks pleasing &ndash; black and white paint job with accentuated blue elements. I knowingly purchased this bike for its frame. I intend to replace most of its components.</p>

<p>Component-wise I have settled on 11 speed Ultegra 6800 groupset with 50/34 crankset and a 10-32 cassette. The combination is flexible enough to give me enough leverage to climb the hilly Swiss terrain and pace reasonably on pavements. I ordered a new handlebar with an ergonomic grip that is correct according to my shoulder width. In addition, I went slightly crazy and ordered a bunch of custom bits and pieces to customize the look, like blue cable housings, bolts and quick release axles. At no point did I consider going Ultegra Di2. I honestly see no purpose in making my bicycle so complicated. Ironically, when I was ten I was imagining that in future derailleurs would have motors in them. The future is apparently already here!</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/ultegra6800.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/ultegra6800.jpg" width="400"></a></p>

<p>Since I intend to ride the bike both on the road and off the road I decided to get two wheelsets. After a recommendation from a colleague I discovered Stan&rsquo;s tubeless wheels and bought Alpha 400 Disc as a cyclo-cross wheelset and Alpha 340 as a road wheelset. These wheels are lightweight around 1500 grams and accept 11 gear cassettes. Alpha 340 is lighter but has fewer spokes and supports less weight. The prices are reasonable at about 600$ for a set. I ordered matching tires (700x23 Hutchinson Fusion 3 and 700x35 Raven) and accessories for the tubeless wheels, like the sealant and the injector. I have never had tubeless road tires before.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/alpha340.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/alpha340.jpg" width="250"></a> <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/alpha400.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/alpha400.jpg" width="250"></a></p>

<p>I had started ordering parts and tools last Monday and it looks like by next Wednesday I&rsquo;ll have everything in! In total, about 2 weeks of choosing, ordering and waiting for the shipments to arrive.</p>

<h2>Ready-made alternatives</h2>

<p>Of course, once I&rsquo;ve bought the Cube Cross Disc and ordered all the bike parts I discovered that there is a bike that suits my needs almost too well! It&rsquo;s from UK and it&rsquo;s called <a href="http://www.rosebikes.co.uk/products/bikes/race/cross-bike/pro-dx-cross/">Rose Pro DX Cross</a>. The specifications are great and the website allows lots of customization. Best of all, the price is very reasonable. I would have went either with the SRAM Force or Ultegra configuration. Regardless, I don&rsquo;t regret anything and I think I&rsquo;ve made a reasonable decision given the information I had at the time. I&rsquo;ve since seen a couple of these bikes at our office and I am not impressed with their looks. Frankly, their owners outfitted them with ugly looking fenders. I&rsquo;m sure I would have a different opinion if I actually owned one of these.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/rose_dx_cross.jpg"><img src="http://drseergio.github.io/images/cube/rose_dx_cross.jpg" width="550"></a></p>

<p>As I had mentioned previously, going custom is not cheap. Even with a used bike the price of new components adds up to a significant amount. My initial temptation was to go with a SRAM Red groupset. After I&rsquo;ve calculated how much it would cost in total I decided to bail out.</p>

<h2>The journey ahead</h2>

<p>In about 5-6 days I will receive the remaining shipments with the wheels and parts. I am in no rush with this build. I intend to enjoy every bit of the building process. The joy is in the ride, it&rsquo;s not about getting somewhere! Otherwise, we would not be riding bicycles in the first place. When working I&rsquo;ve learned to let go of the goals and ambitions. For if I look forward to goals I lose the bliss of being present. When I think of a job as a means to a target I consider everything as a hindrance. Irritation sets in quickly and anxiety escalates. And when the goal is finally accomplished I feel empty and bored. Do I want to live in two extremes of anxiety and boredom? Hell no.</p>

<p>I look forward to the disassembly and assembly processes. Working with hands and mechanical devices is one of the most satisfying activities I&rsquo;ve learned as a human being. It feels creative and I forget about time. Yet I remember the hours of work as if the work took much longer. It is joyful and meditative. It feels as if I alter time and live longer.</p>

<p>On May 1 me and a couple of friends are going on a bicycle tour from Andermatt, Switzerland to Rotherdam, Netherlands. The route goes along the river Rhine and is about 1200km in length. We plan to finish this route in 10 days. I personally hope to finish this bike before the trip but as I have already made clear I won&rsquo;t rush. In the worst case, I&rsquo;ll go on my trusted hybrid.</p>

<p>This concludes the part 1 of my custom cyclo-cross bicycle build series. I don&rsquo;t know yet what I will write about in part 2 but I suspect it is going to be about the disassembly process of Cube Cross Disc.</p>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/">Continue to part 2</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investment portfolio update March 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/03/31/investment-portfolio-update-march-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-31T17:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/03/31/investment-portfolio-update-march-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>March update</h3>

<p>As of <strong>2014-03-31</strong> the best performing instruments are:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VTV      VBR      VBK
</span><span class='line'>9.185716 8.977934 6.721709</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>No changes to positions since last month.</p>

<p>We avoid investing if price is below 10 month SMA. Running through 10-month SMA check we get:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VTV  VBR  VBK
</span><span class='line'>TRUE TRUE TRUE</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This means portfolio should be fully invested in <strong>VBK</strong>, <strong>VBR</strong>, <strong>VTV</strong>.</p>

<p>As of <strong>2014-03-31</strong> the calculated returns for each instrument are presented below(*):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>symbol        1          3          6           12           avg
</span><span class='line'>VTV   1.73547200  1.855995788 12.2262509  20.9251446  9.18571581
</span><span class='line'>VBR  -0.34225891  1.694915254 11.7759964  22.7830832  8.97793399
</span><span class='line'>VBK  -3.79258793 -0.008177952  7.5184664  23.1691347  6.72170880
</span><span class='line'>MTUM -4.53819112 -0.483091787 11.2683926  18.6258936  6.21825082
</span><span class='line'>VEA  -0.91743119 -0.484966052  5.3658537  16.7235495  5.17175148
</span><span class='line'>VNQ  -0.34153978  9.183037106  8.2380216   3.4111045  5.12265588
</span><span class='line'>IGOV  0.20443925  2.971188475  3.1672848   4.6887714  2.75792096
</span><span class='line'>VGLT  0.88326218  7.666928515  4.0382572  -4.0599188  2.13213227
</span><span class='line'>VCIT -0.14120970  3.160709944  3.8169807   0.6881822  1.88116579
</span><span class='line'>GSG  -0.03031222  2.454178316  1.8529957   0.2431611  1.13000572
</span><span class='line'>VWO   3.84119618 -1.827930782  1.1806079  -3.2660903 -0.01805425
</span><span class='line'>VGIT -0.73737057  1.264404609  0.2058917  -1.7546584 -0.25543317
</span><span class='line'>IAU  -2.49027237  7.277397260 -2.7928627 -19.2654639 -4.31780043</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>* Instruments that have insufficient data are penalized with large negative returns.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/">Original post explaining this strategy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://investingforaliving.wordpress.com/">Investing for a living blog</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ai0xPgGdCts3dEhZVUVXTFQtOEdsRUYwSmRLN3M0NHc&amp;usp=sharing#gid=1">Alternative Ivy Portfolio tracking spreadsheet</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investment portfolio update February 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/03/01/investment-portfolio-update-february-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-01T07:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/03/01/investment-portfolio-update-february-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>February&rsquo;s update</h3>

<p>As of <strong>2014-02-28</strong> the best performing instruments are:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK      VBR      VTV
</span><span class='line'>16.14136 14.18598 10.67624</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>No changes to positions since last month.</p>

<p>We avoid investing if price is below 10 month SMA. Running through 10-month SMA check we get:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK  VBR  VTV
</span><span class='line'>TRUE TRUE TRUE</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This means portfolio should be fully invested in <strong>VBK</strong>, <strong>VBR</strong>, <strong>VTV</strong>.</p>

<p>As of <strong>2014-02-28</strong> the calculated returns for each instrument are presented below(*):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>symbol        1          3          6           12           avg
</span><span class='line'>VTV   1.73547200  1.855995788 12.2262509  20.9251446  9.18571581
</span><span class='line'>VBR  -0.34225891  1.694915254 11.7759964  22.7830832  8.97793399
</span><span class='line'>VBK  -3.79258793 -0.008177952  7.5184664  23.1691347  6.72170880
</span><span class='line'>MTUM -4.53819112 -0.483091787 11.2683926  18.6258936  6.21825082
</span><span class='line'>VEA  -0.91743119 -0.484966052  5.3658537  16.7235495  5.17175148
</span><span class='line'>VNQ  -0.34153978  9.183037106  8.2380216   3.4111045  5.12265588
</span><span class='line'>IGOV  0.20443925  2.971188475  3.1672848   4.6887714  2.75792096
</span><span class='line'>VGLT  0.88326218  7.666928515  4.0382572  -4.0599188  2.13213227
</span><span class='line'>VCIT -0.14120970  3.160709944  3.8169807   0.6881822  1.88116579
</span><span class='line'>GSG  -0.03031222  2.454178316  1.8529957   0.2431611  1.13000572
</span><span class='line'>VWO   3.84119618 -1.827930782  1.1806079  -3.2660903 -0.01805425
</span><span class='line'>VGIT -0.73737057  1.264404609  0.2058917  -1.7546584 -0.25543317
</span><span class='line'>IAU  -2.49027237  7.277397260 -2.7928627 -19.2654639 -4.31780043</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>* Instruments that have insufficient data are penalized with large negative returns.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/">Original post explaining this strategy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://investingforaliving.wordpress.com/">Investing for a living blog</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ai0xPgGdCts3dEhZVUVXTFQtOEdsRUYwSmRLN3M0NHc&amp;usp=sharing#gid=1">Alternative Ivy Portfolio tracking spreadsheet</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A sinister camper]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/sinister-camper/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T18:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/sinister-camper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This sinister camper is found terrorizing streets of Zürich:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/12368177534"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2848/12368177534_2be25b6943_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee is not my friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-07T17:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About 2 years ago I completely gave up on caffeine. I&rsquo;ve stopped drinking coffee, most kinds of tea and caffeinated beverages such as diet coke. Giving up was not that difficult. I&rsquo;ve never been a die hard fan of coffee though I savor a well prepared black tea and an occasional coke.</p>

<p>A negative consequence of completely giving up on caffeine is that even the tiniest bit disrupts a good night sleep. Feel like a having a cold bursting diet coke at 4pm? Face insomnia the following night! Same for tea or anything containing caffeine. I had adapted by finding valid substitutes. A cold highly carbonated water is as satisfying as a diet coke. Nothing trumps black tea but rooibos tea is enjoyable in its own way.</p>

<p>Back in the day I don&rsquo;t remember if giving up on caffeine had made any life improvements. A couple of months ago I started having difficulties falling asleep quickly so I decided to carry out a couple of experiments. One of the experiments was to consume caffeine in large quantities (5+ caffeinated beverages per day). The experiment handsomely reminded me of all the benefits of not being addicted to the mainstream drug of caffeine!</p>

<p>But I digress, there are observable benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>My heart rate has dropped. Increased heart rate was one of the factors that kept me up at night.</p></li>
<li><p>I feel energized and enthusiastic. I feel excited doing things that normally get postponed. Even mundane things get done with a spark of creativity.</p></li>
<li><p>I can sustain energized and enthusiastic performance for about 4-6 hours. This has to be supported by regular caffeine consumption.</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s a pronounced sharp productivity and energy crash in the evening at about 5-6pm. While the crash prevents me from doing creative work in the evening it allows me to disconnect quickly and relax. More on that later.</p></li>
<li><p>Surprisingly, I fall asleep much quicker! While I could have previously lied in bed for 15-45+ minutes now I lose grip on reality in a couple of minutes at most and less than a minute at best.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve continued with the experiment for about 4 weeks. I am abandoning it because I find the habit completely incompatible with my lifestyle and the following negative effects:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Headaches. I get headaches if I don&rsquo;t consume enough. When I wake up I have about one hour to drink a cup of coffee before strong headaches kick in. In the evenings the headaches are partially responsible for impairing any remaining productivity. I tried going without coffee one Saturday. I could not focus on anything. I vaguely recognize this feeling from the days when I had been a regular coffee drinker. It never occurred to me that coffee could be causing this.</p></li>
<li><p>Aggression, anxiety, impatience. In the moments when I don&rsquo;t get a caffeine &ldquo;fix&rdquo; I feel increased level of negative emotions and impatience. Even the most innocent behaviors drive me mad. Curiously, before I gave up coffee 2 years ago I never attributed caffeine as a source of anxiousness and irritability.</p></li>
<li><p>Longer sleep. Although I fall asleep much quicker now and subjectively have great sleep the objective quality must have deteriorated because I need more time to get to a rested state. Sleep is important for me (and should be for everyone in his right mind). I know I&rsquo;m rested when I wake up before the alarm clock goes off. With caffeine I need 2 extra hours to get there.</p></li>
<li><p>Productivity crash. I&rsquo;ve listed it as a benefit but it&rsquo;s also a curse. I find it next to impossible to work on anything in the evening. Evening time is sacred to me. It&rsquo;s when I can do something creative or engage in a side project or read or think. Frankly, I can do nothing now. I can&rsquo;t even read articles and news from my curated RSS feed. I can only imagine watching mindless TV but luckily I don&rsquo;t have one.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;m currently on track to reduce caffeine consumption to no more than 1 cup of coffee a day plus a couple of cups of tea. I&rsquo;m doing this to keep immunity from caffeine&rsquo;s effect on sleep while reaping some of the benefits like reduced heart rate. I don&rsquo;t know how useful such a compromise will be but in a couple of weeks I should have a realistic understanding.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t see a reason to ever come back to consuming as much caffeine as I did in the past and during the last 4 weeks. I imagine caffeine is one bad habit that keeps a lot of unaware people in a bad loop. No wonder that few ever want to do anything exciting in the evening when the crash makes you feel so devastated and you think that&rsquo;s normal.</p>

<p>I suppose caffeine has its place. I imagine coffee as a kind of &ldquo;turbo boost&rdquo; button in a critical situation when every extra bit of creativity and energy is needed. This &ldquo;turbo boost&rdquo; comes with sizable payback and so should be used sparingly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - intentionality]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-intentionality/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T13:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-intentionality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been lately practicing intentional photography &ndash; having a purpose and a general idea/plan in mind before making captures. The biggest change I&rsquo;ve noticed is that the number of keepers has risen from an average of 2-6% to 15-25%!</p>

<p>Below I present two projects that I undertook during a recent stay in Seattle, Washington.</p>

<h2>Trainspotting</h2>

<p>I love trains. It turns out that I love making pictures of them too! I suspect that together with landscapes and abandoned places trains are my favorite subjects.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248701365"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2862/12248701365_0cff763be3_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248668105"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7305/12248668105_ab33bde7be_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248850553"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5485/12248850553_2167955d74_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248671175"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3800/12248671175_349365dcb4_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248664195"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5506/12248664195_5d66f5709d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<p>I have asked a colleague to provide a map with markers to local trainspotting places. On a Saturday morning I packed the gear and went walking along one of the major lines.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248656935"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3738/12248656935_7a8f7bf725_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249263096"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3781/12249263096_f822922ec8_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249122624"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7344/12249122624_b9421dfc87_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>I did not feel safe. Everywhere I found signs saying that trespassing is illegal and that BNSF police is going to arrest me. I was careful not to cross any legal lines. I wish I could get closer.</p>

<h2>Chronos</h2>

<p>For the second project I took pictures of clocks I could find in our Seattle office. The building screams with interesting art objects and decorations.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249639094"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/12249639094_a5c66cc3f1_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249204355"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3712/12249204355_6ff341e06a_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249636794"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3788/12249636794_2551b0ca0f_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249643254"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2877/12249643254_7bdaa8e9f8_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249768446"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7340/12249768446_2c87c64358_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - essential Seattle]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-essential-seattle/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T13:09:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-essential-seattle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Visiting Seattle for the first time has been an unexpectedly pleasant experience.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253777934"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2872/12253777934_0750e120d5_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253417785"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7454/12253417785_76421992d7_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253405445"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3827/12253405445_43dab938b7_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253615903"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5544/12253615903_406075b80b_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253957076"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7290/12253957076_c1ef14bef8_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253774264"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3771/12253774264_64d3b09a4b_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<p>The city is walkable and has great infrastructure. I found bike lanes everywhere and public transport. It&rsquo;s the first US city that I find appealing.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253560863"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3683/12253560863_26b1f97b32_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12253790984"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5522/12253790984_1cac831c33_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investment portfolio update January 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/02/investment-portfolio-update-january-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T09:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/02/02/investment-portfolio-update-january-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>January&rsquo;s update</h3>

<p>As of <strong>2014-01-31</strong> the best performing instruments are:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK       VBR       VTV
</span><span class='line'>10.523511  8.138919  5.699153</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>No changes to positions since last month.</p>

<p>We avoid investing if price is below 10 month SMA. Running through 10-month SMA check we get:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK  VBR  VTV
</span><span class='line'>TRUE TRUE TRUE</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This means portfolio should be fully invested in <strong>VBK</strong>, <strong>VBR</strong>, <strong>VTV</strong>.</p>

<p>As of <strong>2014-01-31</strong> the calculated returns for each instrument are presented below(*):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>symbol        1          3          6           12           avg
</span><span class='line'>VBK  -1.144726  3.73230373 10.6838781   28.8225892   10.5235112
</span><span class='line'>VBR  -2.783198  2.81307701  7.8254927   24.7003030    8.1389186
</span><span class='line'>VTV  -3.691583  1.44787645  4.5325377   20.5077805    5.6991530
</span><span class='line'>VEA  -5.206334 -2.75658381  6.4959569   11.2018013    2.4337101
</span><span class='line'>VCIT  2.031439  1.41826923  2.8773470    0.7763048    1.7758400
</span><span class='line'>VGLT  6.186533  1.55386224  2.2258986   -4.3215090    1.4111963
</span><span class='line'>VNQ   4.275093 -1.10180696 -0.5025126    2.8257217    1.3741238
</span><span class='line'>VGIT  1.708174  0.04711055  1.0948905   -0.4997657    0.5876023
</span><span class='line'>IGOV  0.548957 -0.62148565  2.9009193   -0.9828976    0.4613733
</span><span class='line'>GSG  -2.205654 -1.34753996 -3.2575292   -8.1948090   -3.7513830
</span><span class='line'>VWO  -8.434614 -9.55582233 -2.2320270  -13.0223967   -8.3112149
</span><span class='line'>IAU   3.339041 -6.07003891 -6.1430793  -25.4938272   -8.5919761
</span><span class='line'>MTUM -2.315509  3.45800988  8.4921369 -999.0000000 -247.3413405</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>There&rsquo;s a drop in prices across invested instruments in January.</p>

<p>* Instruments that have insufficient data are penalized with large negative returns.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/">Original post explaining this strategy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://investingforaliving.wordpress.com/">Investing for a living blog</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ai0xPgGdCts3dEhZVUVXTFQtOEdsRUYwSmRLN3M0NHc&amp;usp=sharing#gid=1">Alternative Ivy Portfolio tracking spreadsheet</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dilbert cartoonist on goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-07T21:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have just finished reading Scott Adams&#8217; book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Fail-Almost-Everything-Still-ebook/dp/B00FHI0XK2">How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big: Kind of the Story of My Life</a>. In the book the cartoonist behind Dilbert comic shares his views on success in a witty and humorous way.</p>

<p>He talks about goals among other things. He finds goals to be inadequate for long-term personal success. Among the reasons is the perpetual feeling of failure. And what do you do after reaching a goal? Goals are not relevant for ongoing improvements, like staying fit and well rested. Instead, the author argues for the value of creating habits (or systems, as he calls them) to keep essential efforts going.</p>

<p>The idea struck a chord with me. <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/">As I&rsquo;ve written before</a> I had never found goals to be especially useful in life. Not only I can&rsquo;t find any motivation for reaching arbitrary targets I also don&rsquo;t understand what am I supposed to do when I reach them. Suppose I&rsquo;ve put a goal to lift a certain weight. Should I stop exercising once I can do it? Pushing goals further is not workable either. I can&rsquo;t increase my strength forever &ndash; there is a limit.</p>

<p>Forming habits has always worked for me. I had spent a considerable amount of willpower once to fall in love with exercising daily. Now I feel bad if I don&rsquo;t do it. I occasionally break out of the routine (e.g. when I travel for weeks at a time) but resuming is never a hassle. However, I find habits/systems to be out of place for things that are to be enjoyed sporadically. It is a lousy habit to go to the cinema every week because it won&rsquo;t be fun.</p>

<p>Also, the line between habits and goals is a fine one. A habit to meditate daily can be framed as a goal. I don&rsquo;t have a good enough grasp to put a clearly defined distinction. Goals are well defined targets with specific dates attached to them. Habits are a collection of embraced practices to continuously maintain and improve prioritized areas of life without excessively expending willpower. More generally, I can think of habits as processes that solve problems and dilemmas of life to get me closer to what I consider important.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve enjoyed the book. Although there&rsquo;s more circumstantial evidence than scientific proof I have discovered a couple of valuable ideas to evaluate and to experiment with. I suggest to read <a href="http://www.farnamstreetblog.com/2013/12/scott-adams-fail-at-everything/">Farnam Street Blog post about this book</a> for an expanded overview.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 months on a bike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-02T13:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like bicycles. I like riding them, I like fiddling with them. But for some reason I never consistently commuted by bicycle. 6 months ago I made a decision to commute by bicycle every single day regardless of the weather. Even if it rains or storms or snows.</p>

<p>As it turns out adverse weather conditions are conquerable with appropriate gear. I am lucky that I have an opportunity to change clothes and take a shower upon my arrival at work. Item by item I arrived at the following clothes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Gore-tex bike jacket</li>
<li>Wind/water proof trousers</li>
<li>2 synthetic shirts (depending on the temperature I either wear one or two)</li>
<li>Gore-tex bike gloves + undergloves</li>
<li>Gore-tex outdoor shoes + water shoe covers</li>
</ul>


<p>The coldest days are yet to come (so far the coldest has been -3C). I expect that I will need to wear underpants and possibly another shirt when the temperature drops to -7/-10C.</p>

<p>Bike pictures before cleaning and service:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11676075456"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7297/11676075456_873e4d0fcb.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675652254"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7334/11675652254_5f596474c0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675527263"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/11675527263_1105f146d6.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve made a lot of upgrades to my commuter/touring bike. It started as a <a href="http://www.bmc-racing.com/ch-en/bikes/2010/mountainroad/platform/mountainroad_series/alpenchallenge/ac01/standard/">BMC alpenchallenge AC01 from 2010</a>. Full list of upgrades:</p>

<ul>
<li>Shimano XT disc brakes (tried SRAM twice)</li>
<li>SRAM X.0 rear derailleur</li>
<li>SRAM X.0 shifters</li>
<li>Shimano 105 crankset</li>
<li>Wippermann Connex black chain</li>
<li>DMR V12 pedals</li>
<li>Ergon GP3 grips</li>
<li>Specialized toupe 143 saddle</li>
<li>Garmin 800 computer (shared with 2 other bikes)</li>
<li>2x Lenzyne superdrive front lights (shared with 2 other bikes)</li>
<li>Cateye TL-LD610 rear light</li>
<li>Topeak defender M2 rear fender</li>
<li>Racktime ADDit rear pannier rack</li>
<li>Ortlieb classic waterproof rear pannier bags</li>
</ul>


<p>This configuration suits me very well. Everything works smoothly and the bike is exceptionally quiet on the road.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675646804"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7341/11675646804_4d2d831b20.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - snowshoeing in Leukerbad]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-leukerbad/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-02T12:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-leukerbad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On one of the last weekends of December me and my wife went to a weekend trip to Leukerbad to enjoy the hot springs and do a little snowshoe tour around a mountain lake Daubensee.</p>

<p>Leaving from train station in Zurich:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675156726"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5501/11675156726_f2a46a740e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Arriving at the hotel in Leukerbad:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674144615"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/11674144615_7ab8639d70.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Downtown Leukerbad:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674519814"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5494/11674519814_43cee99fd0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Fooling around in the evening:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11672626495"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3750/11672626495_582b6d12ef.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11673004054"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5518/11673004054_f9394970c3.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Outdoor swimming pool with hot spring water:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674540723"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3743/11674540723_90a615bc53.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Going up and snowshoeing:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11673853326"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5519/11673853326_388807ef2f.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11673333583"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3761/11673333583_f61f4317c5.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11673865836"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5486/11673865836_5462f58cd3.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In the middle of the route my wife had a minor panic attack and was angry until we got back:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11673331123"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3738/11673331123_02cb800b4a.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Enjoying town:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11672899003"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5493/11672899003_32358a12be.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11673430976"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2814/11673430976_4a5c765e77.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674156605"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5518/11674156605_1b011324da.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674529694"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/11674529694_45ec755a2d.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<h2>GPS track</h2>

<p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/files/DAUBENSEE.gpx">Download route GPS track</a>. Take care if you&rsquo;re going to use it as we have walked on ice.</p>

<h3>Links to photo albums in Flickr</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/sets/72157639241867006/">Leukerbad</a>, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/sets/72157639244691934/">snowshoeing</a>, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/sets/72157639243887784/">portraits</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investment portfolio update - December 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/investment-portfolio-update-december-2013/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-02T10:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2014/01/02/investment-portfolio-update-december-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>December&rsquo;s update</h3>

<p>The R script does not work anymore! It turns out that Yahoo has disabled URL &ldquo;charts.yahoo.com&rdquo;. However, &ldquo;icharts.finance.yahoo.com&rdquo; works fine. The problem is that the URL is hard coded into <strong>quantmod</strong> package.</p>

<p>The quick solution is to check-out latest code and build the package from source. The alternative is to wait until CRAN includes quantmod with the fix applied. Here&rsquo;s how I fixed the problem:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'># check-out latest quantmod code using subversion
</span><span class='line'>$ svn checkout svn://svn.r-forge.r-project.org/svnroot/quantmod/
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'># build and install the package from a local folder
</span><span class='line'>$ R CMD INSTALL quantmod/pkg/</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>As of <strong>2013-12-31</strong> the best performing instruments are:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK      VBR      VTV
</span><span class='line'>16.97135 16.93180 14.93496</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>No changes in positions.</p>

<p>We avoid investing if price is below 10 month SMA. Running through 10-month SMA check we get:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK  VBR  VTV
</span><span class='line'>TRUE TRUE TRUE</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This means portfolio should be fully invested in <strong>VBK</strong>, <strong>VBR</strong>, <strong>VTV</strong>.</p>

<p>As of <strong>2013-12-31</strong> the calculated returns for each instrument are presented below(*):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>symbol        1          3          6           12           avg
</span><span class='line'>VBK   2.50607661  7.5353908 19.5737192   38.270209   16.97134895
</span><span class='line'>VBR   2.75432672  9.9108251 18.4982354   36.563815   16.93180053
</span><span class='line'>VTV   2.09836942 10.1672916 14.3905361   33.083624   14.93495520
</span><span class='line'>VEA   1.90709046  5.8674117 18.1740856   21.800117   11.93717618
</span><span class='line'>VWO  -0.29083858  3.0819344  7.5274438   -4.944547    1.34349811
</span><span class='line'>IGOV -0.07978458  0.1900000  4.9219814   -1.368380    0.91595429
</span><span class='line'>GSG   1.35390428 -0.5867820  4.5129870   -1.829826    0.86257079
</span><span class='line'>VCIT -0.48134777  0.6450043  1.9603008   -1.897983    0.05649348
</span><span class='line'>VNQ   0.10854396 -0.8599509 -3.7136465    2.297576   -0.54186944
</span><span class='line'>VGIT -1.43194335 -1.0426540 -0.5398539   -2.687587   -1.42550967
</span><span class='line'>VGLT -2.00551133 -3.3665459 -5.4505170  -12.458972   -5.82038644
</span><span class='line'>IAU  -3.70981039 -9.3871218 -2.5854879  -28.255528  -10.98448709
</span><span class='line'>MTUM  2.68559699 11.8085305 17.7058824 -999.000000 -241.69999755</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>* Instruments that have insufficient data are penalized with large negative returns.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/">Original post explaining this strategy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://investingforaliving.wordpress.com/">Investing for a living blog</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ai0xPgGdCts3dEhZVUVXTFQtOEdsRUYwSmRLN3M0NHc&amp;usp=sharing#gid=1">Alternative Ivy Portfolio tracking spreadsheet</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On goals and purpose]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-25T19:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Christmas and New Year&rsquo;s Eve evoke mass hysteria to reflect and to resolve to change unlike any other time of the year. People write down goals for themselves, think about their purpose in life. Planning and goal setting are praised important even outside of the festivities.</p>

<p>I believe it&rsquo;s mostly harmless but also pointless. I look back to the moment I first embraced the Western custom of goal setting and I don&rsquo;t have much to show for it. Most of the things I have written down for myself became either unimportant or neglected. Any remarkable moments and achievements have been unexpected, spontaneous or had very little to do with the planning.</p>

<p>For one, goals are thought to be an explicit expression of one&rsquo;s desires and life values. It follows that we are fully aware of what is truly important to us and that it&rsquo;s possible to translate our priorities into conscious plans. However, I personally find a significant disconnect between conscious thought and implicit life values. It&rsquo;s difficult to crystallize the  value &ldquo;compass&rdquo; in words. Plans that come out of a rational mind can be in conflict with  governing values.</p>

<p>I have a personal illustration. I have never put the relationship with my wife as a priority or in any of the goals. However, in moments of distress I have dropped everything to take care of her. None of the goals mattered in that instant. I realize now just how important she is for me. Consciously, I did not rank the relationship high in my list of priorities and goals. But subconsciously I knew what is going to rule my behavior, especially in times of difficulty.</p>

<p>Secondly, goals have costs. It is one thing to write goals down. It is another to accept sacrifices that might be required to make them happen. I&rsquo;ve heard complaints about lines of work that are not terribly exciting. Along the complaints came aspirations for entrepreneurship and exhilarating work at emerging start-ups. I confess that the thought is contagious. I entertained it myself. But then I realized that this change has a cost and that I highly value what I already have.</p>

<p>Taken together, these two factors are responsible for destroying many naive goal setting efforts. Symptoms may differ but at the core the problem is that goals simply don&rsquo;t truly matter to the person setting them. It won&rsquo;t help to break down a goal into smaller goals or to have regular progress reviews. It just doesn&rsquo;t work that way.</p>

<p>I often recall an episode when I was about 10 years old. Two of my friends were coached by their parents to think about their lives and set goals and do all sorts of ridiculous &ldquo;self development&rdquo; exercises. I haven&rsquo;t done any of that. Yet all of the things I appreciate this very day did not come out of any priority list.</p>

<p>I believe there is a place for planning but life is not one of them. I see goals useful when an issue is well understood. Setting goals to win a specific sports competition is a technical matter. On the other hand, setting a goal to enter a competition in the first place is an entirely different thing.</p>

<p>My resolution for this NY is to stop doing useless bullshit personal goal setting crap.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated news sources]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T22:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have added a couple of sites and online magazines to my subscription list. Check out the <a href="http://drseergio.github.io/news-sources">News sources</a> page for the full updated list:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://aeon.co/">Aeon magazine</a> &ndash; Aeon Magazine is an online magazine about nature, culture and ideas.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://aeon.co/film/">Aeon film</a> &ndash; Aeon Film screens contemporary and classic short documentaries, exploring the intersections between nature, culture and ideas.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://habrahabr.ru/">Habrahabr</a> &ndash; (Russian) an online tech-oriented community/aggregator. Most of the articles are written from scratch, rather than republished. I had to spend considerable amount of time unsubscribing from different channels to bring volume down to a manageable level. But apart from that inconvenince there is lots of interesting material that is not published anywhere else.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://digital-photography-school.com/">Digital Photography School</a> &ndash; regular tips and guides on digital photography. I like the amount of published material. Frequent enough to be intersting to follow but not as much to become overwhelming.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Matt and Jessica]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/matt-and-jessica/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T21:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/matt-and-jessica</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The title says it all. Matt:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11371591986/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7353/11371591986_4e05a91d8f.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>And Jessica:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11371555715/"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5516/11371555715_be88a80d8a.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Photo report - snowshoeing in Braunwald]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-braunwald/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T21:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/12/14/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-braunwald</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The weather on weekends has been excellent lately. On December 8th me and my friend John went for a snowshoe hike close to Braunwald.</p>

<p>It was so warm that we took off our jackets.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11372768584/in/set-72157638673432686/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3811/11372768584_33b3da0775.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11372707455/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3800/11372707455_ae6d4a135e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11372738856/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7433/11372738856_7c232818c5.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The hike took about 4 hours. There&rsquo;s plenty of snow and we got our snowshoes on in about 35 minutes after beginning the trek.</p>

<h2>GPS track</h2>

<p>The route we have followed was originally created by Kathleen from <a href="http://www.meetup.com/Zurich-Swiss-Trail-Club/">Swiss Trail Club</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/files/braunwald-snowshoe-route-part1.gpx">GPS track part 1</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/files/braunwald-snowshoe-route-part2.gpx">GPS track part 2</a></p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Links to photo albums in Flickr</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/sets/72157638673432686/">Braundwald snowshoe hike</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investment portfolio update - November 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/30/investment-portfolio-update-november-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-30T09:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/30/investment-portfolio-update-november-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Novembers&rsquo;s update**</h3>

<p>As of <strong>2013-11-30</strong> the best performing instruments are:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK      VBR      VTV
</span><span class='line'>16.93042 16.68999 14.38888</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Last month&rsquo;s VEA&rsquo;s position has been taken by VTV.</p>

<p>We avoid investing if price is below 10 month SMA. Running through 10-month SMA check we get:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>VBK  VBR  VTV
</span><span class='line'>TRUE TRUE TRUE</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This means portfolio should be fully invested in <strong>VBK</strong>, <strong>VBR</strong>, <strong>VTV</strong>.</p>

<p>As of <strong>2013-11-30</strong> the calculated returns for each instrument are presented below(*):</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>symbol        1          3          6           12           avg
</span><span class='line'>VBK   2.3614663  11.351201 15.5519199   38.4571033   16.93042264
</span><span class='line'>VBR   2.9323950  12.637106 13.8594008   37.3310570   16.68998975
</span><span class='line'>VTV   3.1785176  10.376667 10.8967751   33.1035702   14.38888252
</span><span class='line'>VEA   0.6609547  12.043597 12.7502056   24.6060606   12.51520442
</span><span class='line'>VWO  -0.9314545  10.879444  2.0418204    2.0669291    3.51418476
</span><span class='line'>IGOV -1.0908019   3.167282  2.6517083   -0.6808763    1.01182796
</span><span class='line'>VCIT -0.1190193   2.579147 -0.6275903   -1.5832063    0.06233274
</span><span class='line'>VGIT -0.2032838   1.672774 -0.5919003   -1.8153846   -0.23444878
</span><span class='line'>VNQ  -5.2509764   2.487874 -5.7146970    6.0042078   -0.61839801
</span><span class='line'>GSG  -0.4700721  -5.335320  3.0834145   -3.6407767   -1.59068868
</span><span class='line'>VGLT -2.3997615  -1.072670 -6.8165647  -12.6234321   -5.72810697
</span><span class='line'>IAU  -5.6031128 -10.347376 -9.8811293  -27.2781775  -13.27744894
</span><span class='line'>MTUM  3.1469761  12.179732 13.6795195 -999.0000000 -242.49844303</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>* Instruments that have insufficient data are penalized with large negative returns.</p>

<h3>Resources</h3>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/">Original post explaining this strategy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://investingforaliving.wordpress.com/">Investing for a living blog</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0Ai0xPgGdCts3dEhZVUVXTFQtOEdsRUYwSmRLN3M0NHc&amp;usp=sharing#gid=1">Alternative Ivy Portfolio tracking spreadsheet</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enigmatic encounter]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/27/enigmatic-encounter/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-27T19:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2013/11/27/enigmatic-encounter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A rising star of the division.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11089494096/"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5533/11089494096_116ed321d9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>And a man of thousand tales.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11089334325/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7406/11089334325_3ee405ef40.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
