<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Outdoor on Sergey Pisarenko</title>
    <link>http://pisarenko.net/tags/outdoor/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Outdoor on Sergey Pisarenko</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://pisarenko.net/tags/outdoor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - From First to Bussalp</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/03/photo-report-from-first-to-bussalp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/03/photo-report-from-first-to-bussalp/</guid>
      <description>This week we went to the Grindelwald area for hiking. Getting there wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy &amp;ndash; a relatively long 4-hour train journey each way plus additional delays due to an accident on the tracks. The accidents seem to become common as the same happened the week before. Anyhow, Grindelwald is vast with hiking routes. I&amp;rsquo;ve been to Grindelwald several times before and even stayed overnight once. Our hike wasn&amp;rsquo;t difficult but very pretty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - Silent Nanztal Valley Crossing</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/20/photo-report-silent-nanztal-valley-crossing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/20/photo-report-silent-nanztal-valley-crossing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday I hiked a fantastic route together with my wife. It&amp;rsquo;s the first real hike this year and given the busy times it&amp;rsquo;s unsurprising. But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just the first of a season. It was the most difficult hike my wife has ever completed and I was left totally impressed with her pace and endurance. Not only we walked for more than 15 kilometers but we also climbed almost a thousand vertical meters. For my wife, who normally prefers flat walks along ridges or lakes, it is a considerable accomplishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27778716403&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8896/27778716403_ef72bbbe0e.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First 4000m climb</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/16/first-4000m-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/16/first-4000m-climb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am not a peak collector by any stretch of imagination. Indeed I avoid &amp;ldquo;the best&amp;rdquo; like plague. I leave &amp;ldquo;the best&amp;rdquo; for the unsuspecting tourist crowds and boastful blabbers. But the fact is that I&amp;rsquo;ve climbed to the highest altitude in my life. And I&amp;rsquo;ve already paid my dues by feeling the wrath of Gods &amp;ndash; reaching the peak left me untouched and the corresponding up-and-down motions were anything but mindful. Yet the purpose of this 2-day mountaineering trip has been fulfilled &amp;ndash; I am now &lt;em&gt;formally&lt;/em&gt; skilled in the basic skills of alpine walking and climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28288171755&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8862/28288171755_3c9cc512a8_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samaria Gorge hike</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exactly two weeks ago I thought I was exhausted from preparing for job interviews (I will write a separate post explaining my study strategy). After all, I have been averaging 6-8 hours of algorithms and Java study almost every day for 2 months (I am switching careers and going full-time in software engineering). In reality, it was a virus that caused physical break-down, an eye infection and fever. In what can be described as the most spontaneous decision of my life I decided we need to take a short break and go to the sea. How spontaneous? I felt debilitating headache Monday morning and we flew out on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720077554&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7444/26720077554_8d954f1239_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rigimarsch 2016</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another year, another &lt;a href=&#34;http://rigimarsch.ch/&#34;&gt;Rigimarsch&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;Last year&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve participated in an annual night hike up to the Rigi mountain. It was a tough yet exhilerating experience. This year I&amp;rsquo;ve repeated the challenge together with John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262027875&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7316/27262027875_338b6e78de_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountaineering in Valais</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There comes a moment in a life of a dormant adventurer when the curtains of undesired comfort are torn away and the world is finally seen through wide-open eyes, fueled by challenge and gore, excitement and joy. In this very moment feelings of inadequacy and out-of-placeness give way to sincere enthusiasm and appreciation and beauty of the world. I am boundlessly joyful to cross that imaginary line and thirstily imbibe from the cup of mountaineering and alpine beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397145808&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19397145808_340b94e192_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such life-changing shift of perception comes from just a single adventure that I have had the tremendous luck to be a part of. Last Saturday I joined company of JD, Samuel and Clément to trek for 5 days through a mountain range in the French canton Valais of Switzerland, through ice, snow and rock. In the best tradition of Sergey the journey has been one of the hardest things he has ever done in his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going to a first alpine tour</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m feeling excited because tomorrow I&amp;rsquo;m going on my first alpine tour. It&amp;rsquo;s a 5 day tour and we&amp;rsquo;re going to walk on ice and snow. We&amp;rsquo;re heading to region Valais which is not far from Mont Blanc that I had visited earlier this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I already have relatively lots of mountain/climbing gear I had to purchase new stiff boots and other stuff. Packing is in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19388461925&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19388461925_fbfcdc2fa9_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s hope for good weather and some nice shots!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - summer walk in Flumserberg</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-summer-walk-in-flumserberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-summer-walk-in-flumserberg/</guid>
      <description>Flumserberg is a popular ski destination because it is close to Zürich. But it&amp;rsquo;s also beautiful in summer. I&amp;rsquo;ve visited Flumserberg last Sunday for an easy downhill walk.
It&amp;rsquo;s popular with paragliders:

Mountain shed:

Panoramic view from the top:

Säschmoor peak (2196m):

Seebenalp hotel / restaurant:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - walk along the Mont Blanc massif</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-walk-along-the-mont-blanc-massif/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-walk-along-the-mont-blanc-massif/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Weather conditions in Mont Blanc, France, has been favorable this week. So we spontaneously decided to visit it. On a last year&amp;rsquo;s visit we were unlucky as the region was covered in clouds and it was raining so we couldn&amp;rsquo;t see a thing nor go for a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/mini-rescue.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/mini-rescue.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to Mont Blanc we experienced what it feels like to have a car tire burst while going at highway speeds. Nothing exciting or dangerous. Our rental car did not have a spare wheel and the tire was torn to shreds so we had to call evacuation. All in all, only 1.5 hours lost on the incident.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longest non-stop hike in my life</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 13th I established a new personal record for the longest non-stop hike in my life. Not only it involved 52km and 12 hours of walking but also an ascent of 1500m up to Rigi mountain at the very end of the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and my friend Ilya have participated in an annual Swiss event called Rigimarsch. It is a night time hike from a town called Bremgarten all the way up to the Rigi mountain. This year the event attracted 2112 participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note how uplifted we were in the beginning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18037115871&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7734/18037115871_4bd103eb54.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycle adventure in Norway</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In May 2014 I embarked on a motorcycle journey through many European countries with Norway as the destination. The round-trip tour from Zürich, Switzerland was about 8000 Km long and took about 4 unrushed weeks to complete. It was a first ride of such length for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/16169221988/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/16169221988_f3d234f1fd_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To the north</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/29/to-the-north/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/29/to-the-north/</guid>
      <description>Switzerland-Germany-Denmark-Sweden-Norway-Latvia-Lithuania-Poland-Czech-Germany-Switzerland, day T-1!
Phew, that was a mouthful. Tomorrow I am leaving for a 4 week motorcycle tour across Europe heading to the North. Every summer for the past couple of years I was swearing that next year I am going to be somewhere North, rather than elbowing annoying tourists in the Southern honeypot tourist traps. Finally, I am doing it!
I have been dreaming of this trip for years. I am not going to lie and say that I planned this trip in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycle tour: days T-414 and T-64, California Superbike School and BMW Enduro Park Hechlingen</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/25/bmw-enduro-park-hechlingen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/25/bmw-enduro-park-hechlingen/</guid>
      <description>I always had passion for motorbikes, especially so because everyone around me tried to prevent me from riding as I was growing up. I have started riding motorcycles just 3 years ago not knowing what to expect. I was not sure about whether I want to ride sport bikes or off-road monsters or touring rigs or choppers. Last year I went to a 2 day training camp at California Superbike School to their Las Vegas Motor Speedway offering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - snowshoeing in Leukerbad</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-leukerbad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-leukerbad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On one of the last weekends of December me and my wife went to a weekend trip to Leukerbad to enjoy the hot springs and do a little snowshoe tour around a mountain lake Daubensee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving from train station in Zurich:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675156726&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5501/11675156726_f2a46a740e.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the hotel in Leukerbad:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674144615&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/11674144615_7ab8639d70.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - snowshoeing in Braunwald</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-braunwald/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-braunwald/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The weather on weekends has been excellent lately. On December 8th me and my friend John went for a snowshoe hike close to Braunwald.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11372768584/in/set-72157638673432686/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3811/11372768584_33b3da0775.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - snowshoeing in Arosa</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/21/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-arosa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/21/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-arosa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been sick in and out with all kinds of cold during past several weeks. I had a lucky break last weekend and went for a snowshoe hike in Arosa, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10984441523&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/10984441523_6bb5bff50f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve taken the snowshoes on. I had a misconception that snowshoes will let you float on the surface. They won&amp;rsquo;t. After a couple of hours I got a hang of it and could even run. I know I&amp;rsquo;ll be spending time outdoors so I splurged on luxurious MSR ascent snowshoes. These snowshoes have good grip - I could not slide even if I wanted to.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - climbing up via ferrata Feurenwand</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/03/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-feurenwand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/03/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-feurenwand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Via ferratas come in different difficulty levels. Last week I&amp;rsquo;ve done a K2 climb. Yesterday I went to Fuerenalp along with two friends and did a K4 climb. The route is a lot more exciting. Wet and slippery stones and supports presented an additional challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10650891073/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5471/10650891073_9c9d90e8e9.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - climbing up via ferrata in Pinut</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-in-pinut/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-in-pinut/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This Saturday I had a pleasure to do my first &amp;ldquo;via ferrata&amp;rdquo; climb in Switzerland, in Pinut to be precise. Via ferrata routes do not require climbing experience. The idea is to climb up a mountain and various obstacles while being hooked-up to a metal cable that runs along the whole route. Equipment-wise prospective climbers need a harness, a via ferrata set (a Y-shaped lanyard with an energy absorber) and a helmet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10517919016/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3742/10517919016_c7b5b061bb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>