<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: triathlon | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/triathlon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-02T20:01:55+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Triathlon progress update]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-23T20:34:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I enjoy training for triathlon immensely. The sport attracts me with multidimensionality and the numerous skills involved. There is so much room for growth. It&rsquo;s an art really. I will regularly share some of my observations as I progress towards my next triathlon goal &ndash; <a href="/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/">completing a half Ironman</a>.</p>

<h2>Cycling</h2>

<p>After <a href="/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/">raving about Zwift</a> and following its 4 month training program I chose to continue my training using <a href="https://www.trainerroad.com/">TrainerRoad</a> software instead. These two programs cannot be directly compared because they serve completely different purposes. While Zwift provides a 3D virtual world to make indoor rides exciting TrainerRoad focuses instead on a quality selection of training programs and virtual coaching.</p>

<p>What do I mean by virtual coaching? During each session TrainerRoad guides you with advice regarding correct technique and the training session itself. The implementation is very simple &ndash; just regular text messages. But for a newbie like myself getting bite-sized pieces of fundamental cycling wisdom is invaluable.</p>

<p>For example, I had a bit of a toe-numbing problem. My toes would get numb by the middle of the training session. I have partially solved the problem by sliding my feet forward in relation to the pedal spindles and also by moving the saddle slightly forward. However, numbing did not disappear completely. Out of despair I contemplated buying road-specific shoes and pedals. But during one of the first sessions TrainerRoad addressed the issue by explaining the correct kick-and-pull pedaling technique. The idea was reinforced by the single-leg cycling intervals. Numbing went away once and for all!</p>

<p>Same goes for other basics, like breathing and body position. Explanations are brief and to the point. The ideas are regularly reminded and reinforced through practice.</p>

<p>Initially, I chose a medium-volume training program and sticked to the assessed FTP value of 204 watts. After a couple of training sessions I realized this is above my level so I reset my FTP at 190 watts and chose the most basic training program. There&rsquo;s no point trying to jump ahead of myself. Overtraining leads to exhaustion and loss of motivation. I&rsquo;m in this sport for the long-haul so I must not torture myself if I want to go on.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m all set with cycling for the next 3-4 weeks. Afterwards I&rsquo;ll choose a training program that builds on top of the current one. I feel TrainerRoad will provide me with sufficient training material for the next couple of months.</p>

<h2>Swimming</h2>

<p>I started with swimming in October 2015. I went for a week worth of private coaching. I never trained so my form was as bad as it gets. At the time I had no idea how front-crawl works but I knew an efficient swimming form is vital for competition. Following that session I made a habit to visit a local swimming pool 3 times a week. I alternated sessions between doing crawl-related exercises and longish 2k breast-stroke swims. The latter also improved my breathing and endurance.</p>

<p>In March 2016 I signed-up for a front-crawl course. At the moment I can swim crawl 50 metres non-stop and actually feel relaxed and enjoy it! The next step is to do 200-300m stretches without any rest. During a typical training session I combine exercises (e.g. kickboard) and training intervals, typically 200m long. In a few months I&rsquo;ll need further coach input to improve my form but at the moment I have plenty of practice to complete on my own.</p>

<h2>Running</h2>

<p>This is the saddest part. While my <a href="/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">fractured tibia seemed to be completely recovered</a> it started to act up again. About two weeks ago I started with 4 short runs per week (each 3km long). After the 5th session I felt my tibia again. It&rsquo;s nowhere close to the <a href="/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">pain I experienced during the half-marathon when it actually fractured</a> but I must be careful not to make it worse. I wouldn&rsquo;t even call it pain. It&rsquo;s more of a whining feeling.</p>

<p>I have decided to space out the runs until there&rsquo;s no pain remaining. I&rsquo;m looking at a run every two weeks right now. I definitely won&rsquo;t make any aerobic advancements with such a tempo but my primary target is to get the bone strong again. I also consider incorporating intervals into the sessions. And by intervals I mean interleaving walking with running.</p>

<h2>Gear</h2>

<p>As I mentioned in the cycling section I <em>wanted</em> (already a wrong attitude) to buy road-specific shoes (likely black SIDIs) and road-specific pedals (likely Shimano 105). Better pedaling technique solved the problem so for now I can keep my trusted Shimano XT pedals and Specialized Rime shoes (which are walkable off the bike).</p>

<p>Despite previous discomfort I re-installed a proper racing seat &mdash; Brooks C13. Turns out I had incorrectly kept my body on the seat. The correct posture keeps both siting bones in contact with seat wings. Instead, I had been leaning my hips too much forward, causing too much stress on the pubic bone. Once I changed my posture comfort issues went out of the window!</p>

<h2>Misc</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve done a first pass through &ldquo;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Triathletes-Training-Bible-Joe-Friel/dp/1934030198">The Triathlete&rsquo;s Training Bible</a>&rdquo; &mdash; an excellent book for anyone who&rsquo;s seriously interested in the sport. It&rsquo;s much better than a few titles I had previously laid my eyes on. The book is ripe with subtance and with experience distilled from a career of coaching. I feel I&rsquo;m getting a little bit ahead of myself. Most of the advice in the book applies to experienced athletes with at least a couple of years of experience who are aiming at improving performance. My current goals are far less ambitious. I want to gracefully finish a half Ironman. But I figure there&rsquo;s no harm knowing what lies ahead and avoiding common pitfalls.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;ve started regular triathlon training (roughly January 2016) I&rsquo;ve lost 5 kg. The current weight seems to be stable at about 74kg. I&rsquo;m not yet doing anything special in regards to nutrition yet but I&rsquo;m planning to introduce a post-training recovery drink next month.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s about it for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Indoor cycling lab]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-28T18:02:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Around Christmas in 2015 I received doctor&rsquo;s diagnosis that my left tibia bone is fractured and that I can&rsquo;t run for the foreseeable future. Of course, I tried against all reason but the persisting pain made me realize it&rsquo;s in my own best interest to let it heal peacefully and not break it completely. Luckily, I discovered that cycling and swimming don&rsquo;t hurt at all. I suppose that&rsquo;s because the load spread is altered and tibia is not as stressed.</p>

<p>I decided not to lose any time and began training straight away. I have setup an indoor training &ldquo;lab&rdquo; and rigorously followed a training routine three times a week. Although I have been an avid cyclist my level of cycling fitness could have been ranked as &ldquo;beginner&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;ve had plenty of distance under my belt but insufficient endurance to sustain intensive effort necessary in competitive cycling. The training program has slowly come to a successful end and I would like to showcase my setup.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306868565"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7345/27306868565_5c29150c79_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I previously found the idea of indoor cycling trainers a boring pasture. However, training indoors has its merits. The biggest advantage I see is the possibility of structured training where the load of every training session is carefully chosen to stimulate improvement in the areas that need it the most. It is very difficult to go for a ride with friends and keep a specific tempo. With an indoor trainer it&rsquo;s possible to define fine-grained intervals with specific intensity. There are training programs for improving overall cycling fitness or, for example, improving climbs or sprints.</p>

<p>Of course, there is also the convenience factor. With an indoor trainer I have no excuse skipping a training session due to bad weather. It&rsquo;s always available and takes no time to get started with it.</p>

<p>But what really attracted me are the so-called smart trainers, like the <a href="http://eu.wahoofitness.com/devices/kickr.html">wahoo Kickr</a> that I purchased. The smart trainers are dynamically controlled by software so the resistance is continuously updated. Smart trainers can simulate changing terrain and most importantly let the user focus on cycling. With the regular &ldquo;dumb&rdquo; trainers the user must adjust resistance manually. I think I would get tired of it very quickly and would definitely cheat by not being timely in amping up the difficulty.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26700511863"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7605/26700511863_2f9435ffaf_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27236905401"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7352/27236905401_bf09f5907b_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>There are various tools for controlling smart trainers. Some run on Android and iOS devices while others require full desktop OSes. Either bluetooth or ANT+ wireless protocols are used to interface with the trainers. I purchased an ANT+ adapter for my computer for the purpose of controlling the smart trainer and also for accessing data from a heart rate band and a power meter sensor on my bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27209876762"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7323/27209876762_5bafeb4735.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The &ldquo;killer app&rdquo; for me is surely <a href="http://zwift.com/">Zwift</a>. It&rsquo;s a well-implemented detailed immersive 3D virtual cycling world. Zwift is capable of controling smart trainers and simulating terrain. For all the user cares he is presented with a detailed simulation that brings variety and much needed distraction to otherwise boring workouts. Zwift is a open-world multiplayer game with other cyclists riding along. Zwift integrates nicely with Strava, here is a couple of my own workouts:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/554205363">https://www.strava.com/activities/554205363</a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/536343127">https://www.strava.com/activities/536343127</a></p>

<p>Zwift also supports structured training. There are multiple training programs to choose from. It&rsquo;s also possible to create a custom one. I chose a 12-week program aimed at increasing overall cycling fitness and specifically improving the Functional Threshold Power (FTP). With ilnesses, travel and other commitments in place the program actually took me more than 4 months to complete.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/tqf5dD-ofQg "></iframe></div></p>

<p>I have complemented the setup with a webcam mounted on a tripod and connected to my mobile computer. This allowed to see my posture and make continous corrections. A mirror would work even better but there is no place in my room for one and I already had all the components to make a &ldquo;high-tech mirror&rdquo; solution work.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26699661594"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7311/26699661594_317dc183ac_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>This is how I see myself during a typical workout (videos are not focused very well but the idea should be clear):</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/QnhQLFUJRjQ "></iframe></div></p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/CntF-2F9kGc "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Speaking of complements I discovered a few additional pieces of technology I consider vital for training and worthy of an immediate purchase. First of all, a bicycle computer or a training watch equipped with GPS and ANT+/Bluetooth interfaces. I went for both, choosing a Garmin 920XT watch and a Garmin Edge 500 cycling computer. These gadgets track workouts and allow the user to see his progress and make corrections. Having these devices is a luxury that had been available only to professional athletes in the past. Basically, it&rsquo;s like having a personal coach watch over your shoulder every moment.</p>

<p>The reason I own both is because a cycling computer is convenient for glancing at many fields at a time, without taking the hand off the handlebar. I use the cycling computer exclusively for viewing data. In fact, I bought it used at a bargain price. I don&rsquo;t cosider fancier products worthwhile.</p>

<p>Finally, a power meter is becoming increasingly popular. I&rsquo;m going so far as to say that a power meter is a complete must, especially if the user is an amateur interested in racing. A power meter basically quantifies the effort the user is currently putting out. It takes guessing out of the training. With a power meter I can adjust my power output and effort during a ride. For example, in a race I could adjust power output depending on the course to avoid overstrain. I could immediately see if the current effort is sustainable or not based on past observations. Smart trainers come with built-in power meters but I&rsquo;ve added a relatively inexpensive <a href="http://stagescycling.com/us/products/">Stages power-meter</a> for upcoming outdoor rides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306885605"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7208/27306885605_5158cd1438_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26699671554"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7311/26699671554_64e405b1c0_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>With the program almost finished what do I plan to do next? My <a href="/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/">tibia has recovered</a> and I&rsquo;m almost finished with a 4-month swimming training program. I am going to develop a new plan for the next 3-4 months. With the summer here I&rsquo;m definitely going outdoors but I&rsquo;ll combine the outdoor rides with more structured indoor training to hone some of the skills, like climbing. Training ain&rsquo;t easy but I get lots of satisfaction and joy out of it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bike fitting basics for triathlon and road cycling]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-19T16:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a complete triathlon newbie I benefit tremendously from the experience and knowledge of others. Just a few little steps save years, if not decades, of trial-and-error, not to mention decrease chances of injuries and increase enjoyment of the sport. My friend Ilya Nedbailo who has successfully completed his first 70.3 Ironman in Rapperswil this year generously shared a couple of tips.</p>

<p>The first of which is getting a professional bike fitting service. I strongly believe that money spent on professional advice is worth much more than any piece of gear one may buy. A lot of human knowledge cannot be easily encoded in articles or books. One really needs one-to-one contact and quick feedback to understand the nuances of physical movement.</p>

<p>Ideally, one should do bike fitting before buying a bike. But almost any existing bike will do just fine. It&rsquo;s not unheard of to see people competing in triathlon on rigid mountain bikes. An existing road bike is certainly sufficient.</p>

<p>Choosing the right professional could be tricky, especially when there are many options. I followed Ilya&rsquo;s recommendation and went to a triathlon-focused sport store <a href="https://www.tempo-sport.ch/">Tempo-Sport AG</a> in Thalwil. I&rsquo;m glad I did because René Kuster is an experienced and dedicated counsellor. As someone who participates in the sport himself he went above the mandatory adjustments and explained what is important in the bike position and why. I find such human experience and knowledge vastly superior to impressive computerized tech. Surely a computerized solution yields correct measurements consistently every time. But who will check your pedaling technique, advise on body posture and check that you are using the right muscles when the fancy system is operated by a disinterested or an inexperienced clerk?</p>

<p>Surprisingly, my bike fits me like a glove. Even the stem length is perfect. We got the handlebar height and saddle position adjusted and then installed clip-on aero-bars. Then René explained me how to pull the pedals and told me to utilize core muscles to stabilize the body. In the subsequent training sessions I could really tell the difference: I kept myself in a good position by engaging core (acknowledged by disappearing wrist pain) and I did the pedal pull movement correctly (acknowledged by feeling muscle pain in a previously unknown area).</p>

<p>René has also suggested an upgrade path when I&rsquo;ll get the itch to spend money on improving my cycling performance. His top 3:</p>

<ol>
<li>road-bike specific pedals and shoes (I&rsquo;m currently using a XC combination of Shimano M780 pedals along with Specialized Rime shoes)</li>
<li>tight aero clothing</li>
<li>deep rim racing carbon wheels</li>
<li>everything else</li>
</ol>


<p>Once I got the bike fitted I built myself a &ldquo;cycling training lab&rdquo; at home which I&rsquo;ll explain in a separate post. For the other two disciplines I&rsquo;m going through a similar phase of collecting advice and early error correction. I&rsquo;ll share more as soon as I learn!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A long new journey ahead]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T19:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Training for a half-marathon and then successfully finishing one (although not without an injury) hooked me on pursuing further challenges. I haven&rsquo;t run a half-marathon as a way to prove anything. Rather the competition had given me an opportunity to reassure myself that I&rsquo;m capable of carrying out longer undertakings. Ten weeks from zero to finish has been a fantastic learning experience so I am looking forward to the next step which is not only longer but also more challenging. I am committed to successfully finishing a complete Ironman triathlon (IM) race, that is: consecutively swimming 3.86Km, cycling 180.2Km and running 42.2Km while not dying in the process.</p>

<p>Just few months prior as a part of my life-changing course I have given up a lot of pseudo hobbies that I had never really enjoyed. I basically scrapped everything I did and started fresh. I found out that having just one hobby at a time is surprisingly satisfying. I doubt this is a widespread problem. For me, though, too many hobbies not only spread time and attention really thin but also take away joy. I feel happy to accept triathlon as my only hobby and to say &ldquo;no&rdquo; to anything else that comes my way. It&rsquo;s cheaper this way, too.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen variable amount of craziness across the web and in real life. Some Ironman participants set highly ambitious goals of preparing in shortest time possible. I am not one of them. I want to enjoy the whole process of training and the steady growth, just like I did with running. I had a belief I hate to run. With a little help from patience and discipline I followed a careful plan. And I enjoyed every single run. Not for a moment I thought about the upcoming marathon or what lies ahead. I focused on one and only moment &ndash; the present one.</p>

<p>I intend to piggy-back on the same mindset for IM. A chord of stress has already struck me when I realized that I must rush to prepare myself for the next step: completing a half Ironman next year. As soon as I noticed the fleeting feeling I stopped immediately. I&rsquo;m not going to rush which means I&rsquo;m likely falling out of the 2016 season. I&rsquo;m aiming for an entry into a full IM in 2018. There, I wrote it. I find it REALLY difficult to commit to something so far ahead. But I believe it&rsquo;s going to be yet another fantastic outlet for learning.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile I&rsquo;m going to train and the things get really interesting from here. Unsurprisingly, there is so much information and advice available on the topic that I can&rsquo;t put it in just one entry. So I&rsquo;m going to write semi-regular posts on my training progress and findings. I&rsquo;m completely unfit and unprepared for this challenge right now. I don&rsquo;t even know how to swim properly. But I&rsquo;m excited and looking forward to the long journey ahead!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goals]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-31T18:26:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/10/31/goals</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;<strong>I FUCKING DID IT</strong>&rdquo; keeps resonating in my head as I am crossing the finish line. I can already feel latent excruciating pain (amplified by an adrenaline-fueled last half-mile sprint) slowly setting in. Few minutes later I won&rsquo;t be able to walk but at this glorious energizing moment I feel that my whole life is coming together.</em></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how successfully finishing a half-marathon felt to me.</p>

<p>In addition, I hereby completely reverse my opinion of life goals. I used to believe that goals are a sick abomination propagated by clouded minds of semi-religious self-improvement cults. I had my reasons. For one, I couldn&rsquo;t see what&rsquo;s one supposed to do when goals are fulfilled. And most importantly, I couldn&rsquo;t come up with any (&hellip;that I didn&rsquo;t abandon few days/weeks later).</p>

<p>Well, on a sunny day roughly 11 weeks ago I was walking past an advertisement billboard for an upcoming marathon. My mind was clear of stress and worry, thanks to the elapsed three months of sabbatical. Right there, on the spot, I have decided to run it.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;m generally fit and sportive I had never run before. Hell, I have always despised running and especially all kinds of competitive events. I used to repeat a cliché: &ldquo;running is wasted time that could otherwise be spent cycling&rdquo;. Successfully finishing a difficult undertaking like that couldn&rsquo;t be achieved in an instant and there was no way to cheat. The instant gratification was out. I knew it was a long path that required disciplined training.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025248504"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5699/22025248504_84a4c75689.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>For the next 10 weeks I adopted a simple training program with 4 runs per week (basically, one of the first results in web search). The distances increased progressively until they winded down few weeks before the race. My first training run was 5km long. I could barely finish it. Thoughts were storming through my mind: &ldquo;how am I supposed to run 21km if 5km is already so difficult&rdquo;. That was my first lesson: don&rsquo;t think about the goal and instead focus on the current step. Every time I trained I focused on finishing just that training, nothing else. Miraculously, I haven&rsquo;t given up once and completed every single training run.</p>

<p>Time went by and the d-day approached. While my mind was calm my body was having some doubts. I could feel an increased heart rate during the days leading to the race. The race took place in Lausanne, French part of Switzerland. The vibe at such events is extremely positive and supportive with both, runners and bystanders, cheering for you.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025252164"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/765/22025252164_58a0ba4662.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The first two thirds of the race went steady. I maintaned a sustainable pace by regularly double-checking my speed on a sports watch. I followed my breath, movements and hydration. Not much else was going through my mind. It was systematic and joyful. In fact, I smiled a lot.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22634485092"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5826/22634485092_9b94d001a9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22460088480"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/670/22460088480_499343801b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>On the 14th kilometer something happened to my left leg. I felt pain in the quad muscle area and began to slow down. The pain was so strong I had to change the way I ran to a very inefficient one. While I lost a minute or more on every kilometer I couldn&rsquo;t imagine facing the intense pain for the last 7 or so kilometers. Even with the new foot strike the pain slowly built up and intensified. I realized that if I stop just for a moment it would be the end of the race. Most likely the legs would swell and I wouldn&rsquo;t resume. So I kept on. Inefficient, painful but persistent. As I got closer to the finish line cheering crowds and music electrified me. Despite the pain I ran faster and faster, approaching a sprinting pace. The joy culminated as I crossed the line. The emotional spike came so strongly to me that I wanted to cry.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22659237311"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/616/22659237311_8dd3c46841.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t know what exactly happened to my legs. Almost a week later I am still limping but the pain has mostly subsided. I trained carefully and had plenty of long distance runs. I had sufficient nutrition and hydration. I suppose nobody is exempted from risk at such endurance events, even with the best preparation. Once the pain is fully absent I&rsquo;ll surely be back with new goals in mind.</p>

<p>The experience taught a me a couple of invaluable new lessons as well as cemented a few old ones. Like never before, I believe that lessons from sports are relevant to other areas of life.</p>

<p>First, I came to realize that it&rsquo;s important to strive for the difficult and challenging things. It became immediately obvious to me that in the last couple of years I haven&rsquo;t dreamed big enough and settled for things that were easy to imagine. I tended to favor problems for which I already had an idea in my mind. Half-marathon seemed initially impossible to me which made it a clear practical example of what scale of problems to go after. When something seems almost impossible it&rsquo;s worth going after!</p>

<p>Second, as I had already admitted in the opening, I understood the value of setting life goals. It does not matter what kind of goals to choose initially, as long as they are non-trivial. As life generally doesn&rsquo;t have meaning any arbitrary goal might get one going. The success in one area will prepare you for unrelated challenges. Competitive sports offer a great training opportunity.</p>

<p>Third, there&rsquo;s nothing confusing about what to do when goals are complete. In fact, the finite lifespan of goals is very motivating and energizing. Pain and hardship don&rsquo;t last forever. Once you complete the goal it&rsquo;s over. Enjoy the moment and have some rest. Then, choose and go after a new goal!</p>

<p>Finally, when it&rsquo;s too hard to come up with any good meaningful goals it might be a sign that you are purposefully ignoring and supressing your true interests. At least I found myself in such a situation. All the goals I was coming up with ignored my most prominent ambitions and genuine interests. It was hard to face the reality and acknowledge the potential price to pay. That&rsquo;s how comfort zones shrink. It&rsquo;s a slow but sure way to die inside.</p>

<p>Training for and then running a (half)-marathon is potentially a life changing experience but only when the success comes hard and the mind is fertile and open. It didn&rsquo;t come easy to me and I can&rsquo;t appreciate enough everything I have learned and realized.</p>

<p>I am also indebted for the success of my first race to my beloved wife. Without your support and understanding nothing would come out of it. You have a 20% stake in this achievement!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
