<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: triathlon | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/triathlon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-05-27T22:04:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bike fitting basics for triathlon and road cycling]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-19T16:29:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a complete triathlon newbie I benefit tremendously from the experience and knowledge of others. Just a few little steps save years, if not decades, of trial-and-error, not to mention decrease chances of injuries and increase enjoyment of the sport. My friend Ilya Nedbailo who has successfully completed his first 70.3 Ironman in Rapperswil this year generously shared a couple of tips.</p>

<p>The first of which is getting a professional bike fitting service. I strongly believe that money spent on professional advice is worth much more than any piece of gear one may buy. A lot of human knowledge cannot be easily encoded in articles or books. One really needs one-to-one contact and quick feedback to understand the nuances of physical movement.</p>

<p>Ideally, one should do bike fitting before buying a bike. But almost any existing bike will do just fine. It&rsquo;s not unheard of to see people competing in triathlon on rigid mountain bikes. An existing road bike is certainly sufficient.</p>

<p>Choosing the right professional could be tricky, especially when there are many options. I followed Ilya&rsquo;s recommendation and went to a triathlon-focused sport store <a href="https://www.tempo-sport.ch/">Tempo-Sport AG</a> in Thalwil. I&rsquo;m glad I did because René Kuster is an experienced and dedicated counsellor. As someone who participates in the sport himself he went above the mandatory adjustments and explained what is important in the bike position and why. I find such human experience and knowledge vastly superior to impressive computerized tech. Surely a computerized solution yields correct measurements consistently every time. But who will check your pedaling technique, advise on body posture and check that you are using the right muscles when the fancy system is operated by a disinterested or an inexperienced clerk?</p>

<p>Surprisingly, my bike fits me like a glove. Even the stem length is perfect. We got the handlebar height and saddle position adjusted and then installed clip-on aero-bars. Then René explained me how to pull the pedals and told me to utilize core muscles to stabilize the body. In the subsequent training sessions I could really tell the difference: I kept myself in a good position by engaging core (acknowledged by disappearing wrist pain) and I did the pedal pull movement correctly (acknowledged by feeling muscle pain in a previously unknown area).</p>

<p>René has also suggested an upgrade path when I&rsquo;ll get the itch to spend money on improving my cycling performance. His top 3:</p>

<ol>
<li>road-bike specific pedals and shoes (I&rsquo;m currently using a XC combination of Shimano M780 pedals along with Specialized Rime shoes)</li>
<li>tight aero clothing</li>
<li>deep rim racing carbon wheels</li>
<li>everything else</li>
</ol>


<p>Once I got the bike fitted I built myself a &ldquo;cycling training lab&rdquo; at home which I&rsquo;ll explain in a separate post. For the other two disciplines I&rsquo;m going through a similar phase of collecting advice and early error correction. I&rsquo;ll share more as soon as I learn!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A long new journey ahead]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T19:53:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Training for a half-marathon and then successfully finishing one (although not without an injury) hooked me on pursuing further challenges. I haven&rsquo;t run a half-marathon as a way to prove anything. Rather the competition had given me an opportunity to reassure myself that I&rsquo;m capable of carrying out longer undertakings. Ten weeks from zero to finish has been a fantastic learning experience so I am looking forward to the next step which is not only longer but also more challenging. I am committed to successfully finishing a complete Ironman triathlon (IM) race, that is: consecutively swimming 3.86Km, cycling 180.2Km and running 42.2Km while not dying in the process.</p>

<p>Just few months prior as a part of my life-changing course I have given up a lot of pseudo hobbies that I had never really enjoyed. I basically scrapped everything I did and started fresh. I found out that having just one hobby at a time is surprisingly satisfying. I doubt this is a widespread problem. For me, though, too many hobbies not only spread time and attention really thin but also take away joy. I feel happy to accept triathlon as my only hobby and to say &ldquo;no&rdquo; to anything else that comes my way. It&rsquo;s cheaper this way, too.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve seen variable amount of craziness across the web and in real life. Some Ironman participants set highly ambitious goals of preparing in shortest time possible. I am not one of them. I want to enjoy the whole process of training and the steady growth, just like I did with running. I had a belief I hate to run. With a little help from patience and discipline I followed a careful plan. And I enjoyed every single run. Not for a moment I thought about the upcoming marathon or what lies ahead. I focused on one and only moment &ndash; the present one.</p>

<p>I intend to piggy-back on the same mindset for IM. A chord of stress has already struck me when I realized that I must rush to prepare myself for the next step: completing a half Ironman next year. As soon as I noticed the fleeting feeling I stopped immediately. I&rsquo;m not going to rush which means I&rsquo;m likely falling out of the 2016 season. I&rsquo;m aiming for an entry into a full IM in 2018. There, I wrote it. I find it REALLY difficult to commit to something so far ahead. But I believe it&rsquo;s going to be yet another fantastic outlet for learning.</p>

<p>In the meanwhile I&rsquo;m going to train and the things get really interesting from here. Unsurprisingly, there is so much information and advice available on the topic that I can&rsquo;t put it in just one entry. So I&rsquo;m going to write semi-regular posts on my training progress and findings. I&rsquo;m completely unfit and unprepared for this challenge right now. I don&rsquo;t even know how to swim properly. But I&rsquo;m excited and looking forward to the long journey ahead!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
