<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bicycle | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/bicycle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-20T10:10:48+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cube Cross Disc Mk3]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-19T21:40:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have purchased the Cube Cross Disc bicycle second-hand back in 2014 as an ultimate do-it-all machine to replace somewhat petite <a href="/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/">BMC hybrid bike</a> I had started cycling on. No other bike in my stable went through as many alterations as the venerable Cube, transitioning from an object of admiration to almost scrap and most recently getting resurrected to fulfill a pragmatic new purpose. It was the bike I rode during the <a href="/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">legendary Rhine tour</a>. Perhaps it is also the bike I&rsquo;ve learned most of the bike mechanic skills on.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27799786284"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8682/27799786284_5b8f05055e_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27800895753"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8268/27800895753_4dabb15424_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Originally intended as a noble cause to minimize the number of bikes I own the project turned into an ugly obsession to combine the most exotic parts in a wild chase to build the perfect bike. Following the purchase I stripped the bike to the frame and <a href="/blog/2014/05/26/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-3/">rebuilt it with custom chosen components</a>. Barely finishing the Rhine tour I went into another frenzy, adding and replacing a good chunk of parts again. A disaster happened one evening when I was fiddling with the bottom bracket. Being distracted by a conversation I have inadvertendly destroyed the thread where the bottom bracket is screwed in. Very often that&rsquo;s the death of the bike frame. And at the time I assumed the bike was gone. I took it apart and, eschewing the faux minimalism, purchased the marvelous <a href="/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/">Fargo</a> touring bike and the <a href="/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/">BMC road bike</a> I&rsquo;m currently training on. The experience taught me a good lesson about minimalism. It is not always rational, nor cost effective, nor even meaningful. In pursuit of a do-it-all bike I&rsquo;ve ruined the bike by squeezing too much into it. There were panniers&hellip; and aerobars. A lot of parts were installed simply because of hype. Months later, when I brought the destroyed frame to a local bike shop I didn&rsquo;t expect the fatal mistake to get fixed. But it was! The mechanics were able to get the threads rechased. Not knowing what to do with the sudden fortune I left the frame to marinate in the cellar.</p>

<p>Until one day it occurred to me that I have accumulated so many spare bike parts from all the upgrades and replacements that I could probably rebuild the Cube without purchasing much. I also didn&rsquo;t have a city bike that could be left at train stations and public places without too much worry. With the priorities clear I decided to move forward with the rebuild. The priorities were: cheap (as few new parts as possible), disposable (no high-end components) and safe to leave. I am happy to report that I&rsquo;ve been riding this workhorse for more than half a year. It is not sleek nor glitzy but it&rsquo;s a pleasure to use everytime I&rsquo;m off to the swimming pool or to run an errand. I would like to share a couple technical challenges along the way as well as few cool things I came across when putting it all together.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28134119330"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8462/28134119330_605b8e76be.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Guided by the cost I built the drivetrain with a combination of Shimano Zee and Shimano XT components. This being an errand bike I chose to forego the front derailleur and use 10 speeds in the rear for simplicity&rsquo;s sake. The gear range was nicely extended by a spare Wolf Tooth Components 42t sprocket I had. That&rsquo;s how many of the components ended up on the bike &ndash; I simply had them already. The 1x10 system didn&rsquo;t work flawlessly though and I have done lots of small changes to make the chain slide smoothly. The underlying issue was the chainline &mdash; the chain was too skewed in the largest rear sprocket. One could feel the tension. The front sprocket sat too far from the middle, relative to the cassette. That meant that smallest sprockets worked well but anything in the upper middle didn&rsquo;t. Getting the chainline right took many iterations.</p>

<p>At first I moved the bottom bracket spacers from the drive side to non-drive side. A free and noticeable improvement. Next, I have replaced a part of the Shimano XT derailleur with something called a <a href="http://www.wolftoothcomponents.com/products/goatlink">GoatLink</a>. I am not completely sure it made a big difference. The derailleur itself is quite important for the 1x10 drivetrains &mdash; it should be equipped with a clutch mechanism. I&rsquo;m personally using Shimano RD-M786. The final step was to install chainring spacers. That required longer chainring bolts and appropriate spacers. I found it somewhat difficult to track these parts. I found the fitting bolts on CRC although their original purpose seems different: <a href="http://www.chainreactioncycles.com/ch/en/race-face-poly-bashguard-fastener-bolt-kit/rp-prod46947">Race Face Poly Bashguard Fastener Bolt Kit</a>. The spacers must have inner diameter of 10mm. I found those at <a href="http://www.oneupcomponents.com/products/spacer-chainring-10mm-id-4-pack">OneUp</a>. Most recently I replaced the stock 36t Zee chainring with a 38t one. All in all, it works well enough now. I look forward to a time when internal gearboxes, such as the brilliant <a href="http://pinion.eu/en/">pinion</a>, become more widespread and affordable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28383845426"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8619/28383845426_bb078fb0da.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The rest of the bike was put together similarly. The wheels are the cheapest 29" wheelset I could find on the market at 120 eur for a pair. Similarly, the saddle was only 20 eur. When any of these cheap parts gets stolen I&rsquo;ll just replace them with equally inexpensive alternatives. Knowing that I&rsquo;m going to leave the bike in public spaces I equipped the bike with a few theft deterrents. The first obvious deterrent was a heavy lock. I didn&rsquo;t spare cash on the lock. In fact, it might be the most expensive part of the bike. Secondly, I splurged for a set of Pitlock parts: skewers, stem bolt and the seat post collar bolt. Basically, Pitlock replaces standard skewers and bolts with specially shaped ones that require one of 256 individually-shaped locking tools, called &ldquo;Pits&rdquo;. Here&rsquo;s a visual demonstration how these Pitlock parts look like (front skewer, rear skewer, stem cap):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27799822554"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8834/27799822554_4ef7630a54_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28383884506"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8620/28383884506_ee0db673a1_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27800915953"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8618/27800915953_3472fd2b3e_m.jpg" width="240"></a></p>

<p>At the moment the bike has no original parts left except the frame and the headset. It may be the only Cube Cross Disc in the world with such a long history. Here&rsquo;s the complete list of parts from the build:</p>

<ul>
<li>Frameset: Cube Cross Disc 2013 59cm (stock)</li>
<li>Wheelset: Mavic Crossone 29" (new part)</li>
<li>Headset: FSA Orbit Z-t, top 1 1/8", 44mm, bottom 1 &frac12;" (stock)</li>
<li>Tires: Specialized Trigger Sport 33-622 (left over from an abandoned project)</li>
<li>Brakes: Shimano Deore BR505, 180mm rotors (left over from an upgrade)</li>
<li>Stem: Ritchey WCS C260 25° 31.8 (left over from Mk1)</li>
<li>Handlebar: Ritchey 580mm (new part, added recently)</li>
<li>Grips: ACROS Bike24 (new part)</li>
<li>Chain: Deore XT 10 speed (spare part)</li>
<li>Derailleur (rear only): Shimano XT RD-M786 (new part) + Wolf Tooth Components GoatLink (new part)</li>
<li>Crankset: Shimano Zee 68/73mm w/ Bottom Bracket (new part) + Wolf Tooth Components 38t (new part, added recently) + <a href="http://www.oneupcomponents.com/products/spacer-chainring-10mm-id-4-pack">OneUp chainring spacer ID 10mm kit</a> + <a href="http://www.chainreactioncycles.com/ch/en/race-face-poly-bashguard-fastener-bolt-kit/rp-prod46947">Race Face Poly Bashguard Fastener Bolt Kit</a></li>
<li>Cassette: Shimano XT CS-M771-10 (left over from an abandoned project) + Wolf Tooth Components GC 42 (left over from an upgrade)</li>
<li>Gear lever (rear only): Shimano Zee SL-M640 (new part)</li>
<li>Saddle: Selle Italia X2 (new part)</li>
<li>Seat post: Cane Creek Thudbuster ST (left over from an upgrade)</li>
<li>Extras: Pitlock set (skewers, stem cap, seat post clamp), ABUS Granit CityChain X-Plus lock (new parts)</li>
</ul>


<p>Head past to the <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/albums/72157671282205005">photo gallery</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The wonderful way of carabike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-05T20:31:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In September, following a <a href="/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/">Fargo rebuild</a> with s Rohloff Speedhub I have went to ride it in Italy. This time, though, I haven&rsquo;t ridden my bike from A to B. Instead, I cheated and went my wife on a car. The revelation that had followed I have succinctly nicknamed &ldquo;car-a-bike&rdquo;.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22802670766"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5719/22802670766_f754cb289e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In a very concrete sense this is a huge departure from self sufficiency that I strive to achieve. However, it&rsquo;s a fantastic motivation for traveling. Usually I don&rsquo;t like visiting cities that much. I consider most kinds of conventional travel unsatisfying. Yet after a difficult day in the saddle it is a joy to take a hot shower, take a nap on a comfy bed and then proceed for an evening stroll in the area followed by a nice dinner.</p>

<p>The car lets you focus on the most difficult and challenging roads. A cycling tour, however, requires careful planning to ensure the route is not too exhausting. Also, to get to the truly exciting parts one needs to cycle through relatively long stretches of uninspiring roads.</p>

<h2>The full cycling itinerary</h2>

<p>Most of the route planning was undertaken by my wife. There&rsquo;s an excellent resource <a href="http://italy-cycling-guide.info/">Italy Cycling Guide</a> which offers loads of routes and suggestions.</p>

<h3>Day 1 (aka Speedhub in Italy)</h3>

<p>I had zero problems with the bike. Test riding and debugging beforehand helped immensely. The gearing on Speedhub along with a 36t felt sufficient for the steepest climbs.</p>

<p>To fit everything into a rented Volvo V60 station wagon I had to disassemble pretty much everything. Having a bike with Rohloff makes it much easier: there&rsquo;s no derailleur sticking out and there&rsquo;s no cable adjustments necessary.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22622541430"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/612/22622541430_d5dacd5eac.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22828655905"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5799/22828655905_91b6e455a9.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22797055442"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5762/22797055442_0d8bfc782c.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 77.1km, 1630m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/390769207">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="/images/elba/day1.png"><img src="/images/elba/day1.png" width="120"></a></p>

<h3>Day 2 (aka Riders on the storm)</h3>

<p>Raining cats and dogs for about 2-3 hours. I got completely soaked. Still, getting soaked in summer in Italy is way better than getting soaked along the Rhine river in early spring.</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 86.4km, 1822m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/391527939">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="/images/elba/day2.png"><img src="/images/elba/day2.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 3 (aka The easiest ride in life)</h3>

<p>What was anticipated as another 1800m+ climb day turned out to be a blazing fast descent. The route went from the hills all the way down to the beach. I averaged 26kmh on my Fargo which is a lot more than my usual touring speed of 13-18.</p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 67.1km, 26.4kmh average speed (on a Fargo!), <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/392113290">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="/images/elba/day3.png"><img src="/images/elba/day3.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 4 (aka The best 60km of my life)</h3>

<p>Hills and mountains make cycling challenging and painful but so rewarding and addictive. Though I started cycling up mountain passes less than a year ago I can&rsquo;t get enough of it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22797085762"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5811/22797085762_b3dc567372.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22622584440"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/764/22622584440_5f695d6134.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 59.7km, 1954m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/392828417">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="/images/elba/day4.png"><img src="/images/elba/day4.png" width="300"></a></p>

<h3>Day 5 (aka The final day of biking)</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22392234497"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5640/22392234497_9383cf387f.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> 60.6km, 1864m vertical ascent, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/393913583">GPS track</a></p>

<p><a href="/images/elba/day5.png"><img src="/images/elba/day5.png" width="300"></a></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m looking forward to more of these rides.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22640701230"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5770/22640701230_435b7c0896.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22187841494"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/722/22187841494_e0683a1b83.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Salsa Fargo Mk3 - now with Rohloff!]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-03T18:32:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I fell in love with a Salsa Fargo bicycle exactly one year ago. The bike made me newly excited about cycling. No wonder I&rsquo;ve put more than 4000 kilometers on it. I never rode the bike stock and rebuilt it with custom parts as soon as I received it by post (frames were out of stock in July last year).</p>

<p>Following the tour around France I decided to change a few things on the bike to better suit the kind of riding that I do:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>install the original rigid carbon fork instead of a suspended RockShox Reba: I did not feel very confident desceding from mountain passes on windy paved roads even with the lock-out engaged; plus, the original fork has bosses for mounting so-called &ldquo;Anything cages&rdquo; for holding drybags</p></li>
<li><p>remove Cane Creek Thudbuster seatpost: I feel annoyed by the occassional squeaking but it is possible I&rsquo;m going to reinstall it if I notice increased fatigue</p></li>
<li><p>install Rohloff Speedhub 14 IGH: while a derailleur system generally works pretty well internally geared hubs have certain advantages which pique my interest</p></li>
<li><p>change tires: 70-80% of riding I do on this bike are on paved surfaces and gravel, it does not make sense to wear out off-road tires and lose efficiency on the asphalt</p></li>
</ul>


<p>This resulted in the 3rd reincarnation of my favorite bike: Salsa Fargo make 3!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20497054903"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5802/20497054903_7e29d55136.jpg" width="333"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20497047673"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5777/20497047673_f30a77b4cf.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>It is often difficult to understand whether certain parts will work together. I hope this information helps you to (re)build your bike.</p>

<p>I filmed the process of breaking down and re-assembling the bike:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/u7KHGC5LjJQ "></iframe></div></p>

<h2>Random pieces of wisdom</h2>

<h3>Chainline</h3>

<p>To achieve a completely straight chainline I&rsquo;m using Shimano XT M780 cranks with a Woolftooth 36t narrow-wide single chain ring. I know Middleburn RS8 X-Type Rohloff crank also works but is way too expensive and ugly for my taste. I couldn&rsquo;t confirm if any other (e.g. ethirteen, truvativ) cranks can be run with the right offset.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20931357759"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/747/20931357759_6128e45f3d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h3>Alternator dropout</h3>

<p>Salsa Rohloff alternator dropout works with Rohloff OEM mount. OEM2 plate is not needed. See photo below to understand how the hub/wheel is held in place:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21108031852"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5798/21108031852_fcaf00487d_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h3>Rohloff cable routing</h3>

<p>The external Rohloff gear box can be rotated for the best placement. The Fargo frame has cable guides on the seatstays which allow for 3 cables: rear brake and 2 Rohloff cables.</p>

<h3>Rohloff installation</h3>

<p>The installation is simple. Follow the original instructions. Co-motion provides an excellent HOWTO video for their shifter:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/O3up1eZT3Pg "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to put oil in! The hub is shipped without sufficient oil inside. A tube of oil is included in the package.</p>

<h3>Removing rear wheel</h3>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t find any information on how hard is to remove the rear wheel when using Rohloff. It is easier than with a derailleur system! First, remove the external gear box. Then, open the quick release axle and slide out the wheel. Done!</p>

<p>When re-installing the wheel put the chain on the rear sprocket and slide the wheel in like on any other bike. No need to break the chain or disengage the drop-outs. It&rsquo;s easier than a derailleur system because it&rsquo;s not necessary to fiddle with the chain to get it on the cassette.</p>

<h3>Mounting E3 tail light on the rear rack</h3>

<p>While the alternator rack does not have holes to install a rear tail light I attached the E3 tail light with a double-sided tape and a couple of plastic zip ties. The cable can be guided along the top tube of the rack.</p>

<h3>Salsa rear rack (non alternator version)</h3>

<p>Non-alternator Salsa rack does NOT fit an alternator-equipped Salsa frame.</p>

<h3>Cockpit housing routing</h3>

<p>It is not trivial to route the brake housing when using Co-Motion drop-bar shifter. It is especially tricky with Supernova handlebar extender. I used a staged approach:</p>

<ol>
<li>leave the stem bolts loose to allow handlebar movement left and right</li>
<li>move Co-Motion shifter onto the bar but don&rsquo;t tighten the bolt yet</li>
<li>install brake levers</li>
<li>install the first part of housing (to the barrel adjusters) and route the right one through Co-Motion shifter</li>
<li>slide the handlebar right and temporarily move Co-Motion shifter as left as possible</li>
<li>tape the right side of the handlebar up to the tapered point of the handlebar</li>
<li>slide Co-Motion shifter to the right; I moved it as far right as the wide diameter of the bar allows it</li>
<li>install Supernova handlebar extender (for mounting the front light on) and route the brake housing through openings</li>
<li>continue as usual</li>
</ol>


<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20495491904"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5816/20495491904_32d8e3b11e_q.jpg" width="150"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20930242178"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5782/20930242178_5a68f88e78_q.jpg" width="150"></a></p>

<h2>First impressions</h2>

<p>The bike came together cleanly. Salsa designed the Fargo frame around possible Rohloff use. The frame has sufficient cable guides and the Rohloff Alternator dropout is easy to install and use. Adjusting chain tension is straightforward. No need for chain half-links or an eccentric bottom bracket.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21125844901"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/587/21125844901_1e84167b89_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20929989490"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5740/20929989490_1bb98c75c7_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The drivetrain is quiet. It is slightly unusual that shifting under load does not always work and can sometimes temporarily send the hub in the higher gear. The upside is that shifting works in a complete standstill. It will require some getting used to.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20495479424"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/757/20495479424_e8de8a8285_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The shifter is not indexed. Everything happens inside the hub. The upside is simplicity and higher reliability. The downside is reduced feedback in the shifter. The shifts are felt but are nowhere crisp as they were on the SRAM Red/X0 combination I had before.</p>

<p>All in all I&rsquo;m satisfied with the result. In fact I&rsquo;m going to put a Rohloff on my second adventure bike which is going to be a so-called 31er/29+ Surly ECR. I came back from the test ride with a huge smile on my face. I just fucking love bikes.</p>

<h2>Final build kit</h2>

<p>The full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/albums/72157658151072695">is available on Flickr</a>.</p>

<h3>Frame</h3>

<ul>
<li>Salsa Fargo 2 bomb pop blue 2014 frame</li>
<li>Salsa Carbon Firestarter through-axle</li>
</ul>


<h3>Drivetrain</h3>

<ul>
<li>Rohloff Speedhub 14</li>
<li>Co-Motion drop-bar Rohloff shifter</li>
<li>Shimano 10-speed chain</li>
<li>Chris King bottom bracket</li>
<li>Alternator dropout + single-speed driveside dropout</li>
<li>Shimano XT M780 crankset</li>
<li>Wolftooth 36t single narrow wide chainring</li>
<li>Shimano XT pedals</li>
</ul>


<h3>Wheels</h3>

<ul>
<li>Schwalbe Big Apple 2.35" tires</li>
<li>SON Schmidt 28 15 dynamo front hub</li>
<li>DT Swiss TK 540 disc rims</li>
</ul>


<h3>Seat</h3>

<ul>
<li>Brook Cambium C17 carved</li>
<li>Thomson Elite seatpost</li>
</ul>


<h3>Cockpit</h3>

<ul>
<li>Salsa Woodchipper handlebar</li>
<li>Salsa Guide stem</li>
<li>Chris King i7 headset</li>
<li>Salsa gel cork tape</li>
<li>Supernova handlebar extension</li>
</ul>


<h3>Brakes</h3>

<ul>
<li>Avid BB7s road brakes</li>
<li>SRAM S900 brake levers</li>
<li>200mm Avid G2CS front rotor</li>
<li>160mm Avid G2CS Rohloff-specific rear rotor</li>
</ul>


<h3>Electronics &amp; accessories</h3>

<ul>
<li>Supernova E3 Pro front light</li>
<li>Rack-mounted Supernova E3 tail light</li>
<li>Salsa Alternator rack</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trip report from bicycle tour across France]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-07T20:11:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Riding vs buying</h2>

<p>I am amused with the nontrivial amount of invented needs by the bicycle industry as well as the strength of its marketing departments. Each year brings new wheel/tire size standards, new drive-train groupsets and mass-produced lifestyles and attitudes. Suddenly, many enthusiasts desperately realize their need for full-suspension fat bikes with a certain kind of axles for &ldquo;backpacking&rdquo; &ldquo;adventure&rdquo; &ldquo;expeditions&rdquo;. I don&rsquo;t see how bicycle gear obsession is any different from the common consumerism. In the photography world it&rsquo;s called &ldquo;GAS&rdquo; &ndash; gear acquisition syndrome &ndash; which is known to be unconducive to original work.</p>

<p>I am not immune to the disease either. In fact, I have a very heavy case of it. I&rsquo;m obsessed with bikes and bike parts which doesn&rsquo;t land financial wellbeing a huge favor. But the solution is actually pretty simple: just ride the goddamned bike [you already have]!</p>

<p>When I have had photography GAS at one moment I had owned 4 digital cameras. My photographs were not amazing and most of the gear sat idle. Now I own 1 camera and 2 lenses: 35mm and 55mm. I appreciate the limitations and praise the amazing camera body every time I use it. I&rsquo;m definitely not doing any worse than before. If anything, I feel a bit more creative having just 2 prime lenses. It&rsquo;s the same with bikes. I recently caught another potentially expensive itch to get a new bike. And that meant one thing only: not enough saddle time!</p>

<h2>Putting the cranks where my mouth is</h2>

<p>With my diagnosis unambigously established, me and John decided to go for a cure cycling tour across France.</p>

<p><a href="/images/france-tour.png"><img src="/images/france-tour.png" width="1021"></a></p>

<p>Our actual route traced through the following places: <strong>Dijon</strong> &mdash; <strong>Morvan national park</strong> &mdash; <strong>Nevers</strong> &mdash; <strong>Bourges</strong> &mdash; <strong>Saint-Aignan</strong> &mdash; <strong>Tours</strong> &mdash; <strong>Saumur</strong> &mdash; <strong>Nantes</strong> &mdash; <strong>Noirmoutier</strong> &mdash; <strong>Jard-sur-Mer</strong> &mdash; <strong>La Rochelle</strong>. The route incorporated parts of Eurovelo 6 and Eurovelo 1. We rode for 8 days and totaled approximately 1100 Km. The distances across days were spread the following way: <strong>115</strong> &ndash; <strong>108</strong> &ndash; <strong>170</strong> &ndash; <strong>140</strong> &ndash; <strong>155</strong> &ndash; <strong>166</strong> &ndash; <strong>116</strong> &ndash; <strong>119</strong>. We allowed ourselves 8 days to complete it. However, we bought flexible return tickets and had 2 extra days just in case.</p>

<p>Originally, we were thinking of a much grander 2-3 week tour this year in a northern European country. But I&rsquo;m glad we decided against it because we weren&rsquo;t yet ready for potential adversity.</p>

<h2>Our story</h2>

<p>One early Sunday morning I woke-up at 3:55. I had a nice warm breakfast cooked by my dear and understanding wife. I then drove in a rented car to the train station and from there carried my packed bike and panniers across two train stations before meeting John. We then took a train to Basel where we ran with the ultra-uncomfortable heavy Tranzbags across our shoulders to the French part of the train station. I felt slightly nervous because of the french TGV train. Although SNCF (the French train company) clearly states that packed bikes are allowed on all trains I knew enough of the culture to realize we might still have trouble. Gladly we had zero issues and soon enough we arrived in Dijon and unpacked our bikes. I suppose traveling first class has its merits.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190464608"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3807/20190464608_e6a225fdb3.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>We bought some snacks at the train station and then some groceries in a Thai shop along the way. We planned our first few days to be the hardest with the most elevation gains. It&rsquo;s better to plan for tough days first while you&rsquo;re still rested and fresh. We learned this the hard way in the last year&rsquo;s Rhine tour. Back then we rode for 30 or so kilometers the first day. And we had to ride until midnight the many days after to compensate for it.</p>

<p>From early on we joined local insignificant roads and cycling paths. We followed beautiful Canal de Bourgogne with its many boats. There were numerous recreational weekend cyclists on the paths close to nearby cities.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755784074"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/465/19755784074_decd610c30.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Once we departed from the canal the scenery abruptly changed into typical rural country-side France: lots and lots of fields and small run-down villages. The scenery reminded me of my home country Latvia. The weather was too perfect to be true: cloudy and around 17C.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190413600"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/261/20190413600_79cd562045_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Our first destination was the Morvan national park. As we got closer our path has led us into forests and unpaved roads. Parts of the roads were washed out. Others had huge trees lying across them so we had to lift our bikes. At times we had to walk. Frankly I didn&rsquo;t anticipate we would need to negotiate such terrain but these challenges set the right adventure spirit early on. Our average speed fell quickly and it was hard to imagine we would do the original 130km planned for the day.</p>

<p>I learned that &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; means different things to Swiss and French. In Switzerland &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; means a finely packed gravel you can ride with a road bike. In France &ldquo;unpaved&rdquo; may mean a mud bath, a single-track or an alltogether abandoned path last driven on a grandfather&rsquo;s Land Rover 20 years ago.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20384617841"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/317/20384617841_6ee210343b_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I felt I should have changed my worn tires before this tour but I can only imagine how much worse it was for John who had touring tires without any knobs.</p>

<p>It is amazing how much the scenery changes during the day while cycling. At first the scenery appears to drag on forever. But once the day is over and you look back it&rsquo;s hard to comprehend it all happened in one day. That also presents a challenge for taking photos: nothing seems interesting enough until it&rsquo;s all over. And then you regret not taking enough of shots.</p>

<p>The weather started behaving and we had to wait out a couple of showers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20369920682"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/433/20369920682_26264c1d93.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p>At about 18:30 we had to stop cycling because we were soaking wet and shivering from cold. Somehow my original plan of not taking rain-proof gear didn&rsquo;t account for 14C temperature in summer. We were lucky to find a small house and not camp the first night. It would have been a miserable experience. A nearby campsite had a working cafe so we downed a couple of burgers before settling down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352235486"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/448/20352235486_f92b3f8c0b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>In the morning we had to wait out a couple of determined showers despite our ambition to leave early and make the most out of the day. This tour taught me patience as ambition in the wrong circumstances is foolish. We stopped at a local grocery store to stock up on food. After a couple of days shopping for groceries became routine. I learned that restaurants and cafes are far from necessary when it&rsquo;s possible to buy varied and fresh food from the local market.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20192163249"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/298/20192163249_0a62a831cb_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20192166779"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/554/20192166779_14b5d71f6a_m.jpg" width="240"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757883033"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/319/19757883033_f5a418d2e9_m.jpg" width="240"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190673638"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/385/20190673638_1fb6dcd2b4_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>There were a couple of lakes along the way but the scenery appeared ominous because of the drizzling rain and gray skies. As the unpaved forest roads made their grand reapperance I became quite worried as you can read from my facial expression:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191863269"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/378/20191863269_a06f4cf6de.jpg" width="333"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190506138"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/20190506138_946012d336.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I felt anger and anxiety because we were crawling and I didn&rsquo;t plan for such extended terrain contingencies. I was counting on fast packed gravel speedways! Eventually, the skies cleared and we returned to the country-side. We made a decision to divert from the original route and stick to secondary asphalt roads to get to our next target.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378510665"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/520/20378510665_0e62a9bb50.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755836414"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/434/19755836414_06bfcb25cb_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We arrived in a town Nevers and camped in the municipal camp site. We checked the weather forecast in advance to make sure it won&rsquo;t rain or else camping would be a suboptimal choice. It was our first camping night and I was pleasantly surprised it took us only about 20 minutes to set everything up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191886119"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/430/20191886119_3efc34e661_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>Sleeping though was an entirely different story. I couldn&rsquo;t fall asleep and felt cold during the night. I was restless and half awake the whole night. I forgot to take ear plugs with me. At least I&rsquo;m glad we had decided to purchase summer sleeping bags. Our original plan was to use silk liners.</p>

<p>We woke up early at 5:20 to make the most of the day as we had seen the forecast predicting rain after 18:00. Something kept me going but sleep deprivation felt miserable. This can be judged by the amount of photos taken during the day: very few.</p>

<p>As we got to a big city Bourges by lunch time we couldn&rsquo;t find a working cycling store because everyone one of the four stores was prematurely closed for a lunch break. John forgot his helmet in the train and needed to get a new one. In the next two hours we purchased groceries and went to a posh burger place. Once we bought a helmet we made a decision to continue for an extra 80 kilometers.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755853054"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/356/19755853054_8683722906_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>Our progress seemed very slow. The roads were winding up and down slightly and we were going against the wind. In addition, we had taken a somewhat busy road with lots of truck traffic.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190478720"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/281/20190478720_4a234e170f_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>At about 17:00 it predictably started to rain. My spirits were really low because I knew the forecast. We refused to stay in Bourges because that would end the day too early. There were no places to stop between Bourges and our next target. It is a persistent challenge to find accommodation at the right time.</p>

<p>We had to continue despite the rain. The rain wouldn&rsquo;t go away. So we climbed our bikes, wore the wind-proof jackets and pushed on. We soon realized it wasn&rsquo;t so bad. The wind has subsided and the road radiated heat. We were wet but not cold. Our bodies eventually dried our clothes.</p>

<p>Few hours into the ride we called a couple of hotels to book a room so that we have a place to stay when we get to the town late in the evening. At 130-140 kilometer mark we felt energized. I realized it is a very common occurrence. The first 70-100 or so kilometers are the hardest. The first 70 are, in fact, torturous because progress appears too slow.</p>

<p>Admittedly, up to this point I felt similar to how we felt in our previous Rhine tour. Anxious and nervous we&rsquo;re not making enough progress among unexpected difficulties. The tables turned the next day when I felt, for the first time, confidence and freedom from the shackles of our original plan. Our goal is to enjoy the journey and we can alter and change the route in any way we like.</p>

<p>On the following days we got on to route EuroVelo 6 and from there traced the longest French river La Loire. To take the shortest path we used Google Maps directions and a micro SD slot on my phone to create a GPX track that can be swallowed by Garmin.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757620813"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/398/19757620813_2a3a7ce575_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190496210"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3769/20190496210_a0ca74be9d_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p>The scenery offered views on splendid bridges over La Loire and its many castles.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19755932284"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/260/19755932284_5e72621630_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20191955409"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/331/20191955409_25370d9e47_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20384749161"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/444/20384749161_cfa7653ddf_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>The larger French cities, such as Bourges or Nantes appeared surprisingly industrial.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352310756"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/369/20352310756_b9f046df00_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352384086"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/468/20352384086_688f768bd1_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>We got into a habit of arriving somewhat late to the campsites. Most of the receptions close at 18:00. We basically had to trespass, find empty pitch spots and then pay in the morning upon departure. This made the staff quite confused. But finishing our days at 18:00 or so seemed too early. As we didn&rsquo;t cook dinner there wasn&rsquo;t much to do. Why stay bored in the campsite when we can be enjoying the road?</p>

<p>We caught up with the planned schedule in Nantes. But once we have got there we decided to take a train to La Rochelle to make the last few days easier. I am so glad that the morning train was full and we decided against it! Instead, we continued EuroVelo 6 route to the coast of the Atlantic ocean and then continued South through EuroVelo 1. The road along the ocean has quickly overshadowed everything we cycled so far. To make the last few days easier we decided to take a train from La Rochelle to Bordeaux thinking that we&rsquo;ve seen enough of French country side roads.</p>

<p>Pine trees, the smell of open water and white sand reminded me of my home country once more: it was like a bigger and better version of Jurmala. Our first day along the coast stretched late into the evening because we have run into a few problems. Namely, the road to an island we hoped to take was flooded that time of the day, we have ridden into a dead end trying to take another road and we lost each other. The reward was one of the most beautiful sunsets I have ever seen.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19756050324"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/528/19756050324_a5a3a86ed8_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352477786"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3695/20352477786_c6ef2586f1_n.jpg" width="320"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19756058424"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/560/19756058424_566d9388f7_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20352483906"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/407/20352483906_298bf3f6b0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Camping (unathorized, as usual) on the Noirmoutier island was fantastic. In the morning I discovered a flat rear tire which was promptly fixed:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190685130"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/305/20190685130_742f00a4e4_z.jpg" width="640"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378747705"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/468/20378747705_4307880bd4_n.jpg" width="320"></a></p>

<p>We continued along the coast until we reached La Rochelle. There were a few resort towns along the way which made me panic. I don&rsquo;t like crowded places. We breezed through them quickly. On the weekend cycling paths were crawling with beachgoers. Cycling in the early hours of the day was much better. There are also annoying obstacles, such as gates, to slow the cyclists down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20370219732"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/437/20370219732_f34afd8105_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757824133"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/365/19757824133_b811dbda41_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757863073"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/384/19757863073_2f9ae1edbf_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190820048"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/348/20190820048_e660b17120.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19757891663"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/371/19757891663_db6e7eeb50.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20378822715"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/557/20378822715_5899351d4e.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190768350"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/502/20190768350_bdd1a58d8b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Once we arrived in La Rochelle we cycled across an enormous bridge to the Isle of Rhé and bathed in the ocean.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20190837468"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/434/20190837468_ddf9a1b4c5.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20370279592"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/449/20370279592_cd45c78dbc_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>The full photo album <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/sets/72157654009464044">is available on Flickr</a>. Links to the individual day tracks in strava: <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743564">8</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743578">7</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743583">6</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743582">5</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366746443">4</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743556">3</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743543">2</a>, <a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/366743544">1</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Across France on a bicycle]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-25T19:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following numerous episodes of soul searching I finally came to realize that enjoy cycling more than an average person. While I enjoy many flavors of it, such as road cycling and mountain down-hill riding my absolute favorites are endurance and touring rides.</p>

<p>My dream is to visit as many places on a bicycle as I could. Somehow biking[1] feels to me just the right way to explore the world. Last year I joined my very first cycling tour along the river Rhine. That tour had its ups and downs. I learned a lot and wrote about the lessons in earlier posts. <a href="/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">post1</a> <a href="/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/">post2</a></p>

<p>This year me and John are expanding our comfort zones. While we&rsquo;re still within the safe confines of Europe we&rsquo;re not going for hotel accommodation. Instead, we&rsquo;re going to camp. Hopefully, we will learn new lessons and don&rsquo;t repeat the previous mistakes. Step by step we make our tours more challenging and more exciting.</p>

<p>Our destination this year is Northern and Western France. We&rsquo;re starting off from city Dijon to which get by a high-speed train. French TGVs disallow  assembled bikes onboard so we had to purchase so-called TranZBags and partly disassemble our bikes (note that I leave the tent attached to the bike):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/20008244211"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3673/20008244211_5f2ddde0f4_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>To fit the bike comfortably inside the bag I took extra steps and removed the seat-post and pedals. That should also minimize the risk of broken spokes.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19380398634"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/294/19380398634_2e95a27719_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I hope we won&rsquo;t have problems. Just in case we purchased 1st class tickets expecting fewer passengers and fewer confrontations.</p>

<p>From the outset our gear list is much shorter than last year which is plenty remarkable as we haven&rsquo;t camped and instead stayed in hotels and hostels. Here&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m bringing:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19816344399"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/359/19816344399_5c8e06b5f9_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<ul>
<li>bike repair kit (napkin, pump, spare tube, 2x multi tool, leatherman knife, tape, zip ties, plastic gloves, chain bits)</li>
<li>flexible bike lock</li>
<li>TranZBag (for transporting bicycle on trains)</li>
<li>2x 60g tubes of chamois cream</li>
<li>3x packs of hydration tables</li>
<li>swimming trunks</li>
<li>hiking towel</li>
<li>inflatable sleeping mat</li>
<li>compact summer sleeping bag</li>
<li>cash wallet</li>
<li>15000mah portable battery</li>
<li>passport</li>
<li>bank access code generator</li>
<li>head torch</li>
<li>notebook and pen</li>
<li>Garmin 62s and one set of spare batteries</li>
<li>credit card wallet</li>
<li>leg warmers</li>
<li>phone</li>
<li>one extra cycling shirt</li>
<li>ultra-light wind-proof jacket (packed into red sack)</li>
<li>one extra cycling bibs</li>
<li>arm warmers</li>
<li>one extra set of socks</li>
<li>medicine</li>
<li>compact digital camera (not shown)</li>
</ul>


<p>This is the stuff I&rsquo;m going to wear on me (helmet is not shown):</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19815037210"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/396/19815037210_82c57f6492_z.jpg" width="427"></a></p>

<p>This time I&rsquo;m not taking any kind of rain gear because it is pointless in summer heat. I&rsquo;m also not taking any food. Instead, we&rsquo;ll scout for grocery stores along the way.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t publish anything during the ride but I&rsquo;ll keep some notes for a report upon our return. Wish us good luck!</p>

<p>[1] walking, hiking, climbing are the other preferred means</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
