<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: outdoor | Sergey Pisarenko]]></title>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/categories/outdoor/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-08T19:08:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://drseergio.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sergey Pisarenko]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Samaria Gorge hike]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-30T21:29:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exactly two weeks ago I thought I was exhausted from preparing for job interviews (I will write a separate post explaining my study strategy). After all, I have been averaging 6-8 hours of algorithms and Java study almost every day for 2 months (I am switching careers and going full-time in software engineering). In reality, it was a virus that caused physical break-down, an eye infection and fever. In what can be described as the most spontaneous decision of my life I decided we need to take a short break and go to the sea. How spontaneous? I felt debilitating headache Monday morning and we flew out on Wednesday.</p>

<p>So we chose a destination we could fly to ASAP that had decent weather and warm sea. In the end we went to Crete. I had previously visited Crete 10 years ago. Crete left an impression not only with the warm Mediterranean climate and usual resort-world bells and whistles but also with a natural wonder I couldn&rsquo;t visit at the time. I&rsquo;m talking about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samari%C3%A1_Gorge">Samaria Gorge</a>. It was time to finally hike it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720077554"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7444/26720077554_8d954f1239_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>I am amazed at how the local businesses managed to market and sell Samaria Gorge and lull even the most unprepared unfit tourists, making it a must-visit attraction. In the high season, which unsurprisingly is the worst time of the year to visit it, Samaria Gorge attracts 30,000-40,000 tourists per month. Some of those tourists later write horror stories as to how difficult and extreme the whole experience was. Legends get born and rumors get spread.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here to bust some myths. First of all, it is not the largest Gorge in Europe. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verdon_Gorge">Verdon Gorge</a> is. Second, it is not an extremely difficult adventure. It&rsquo;s best described as a hike of medium-easy difficulty. Most of the time the route descends which is admittedly not my favorite (I prefer ascents or mixed terrain). While the terrain is rocky there is nothing extreme about it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720813773"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7251/26720813773_bb58db0b87_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27052274170"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7653/27052274170_654d0d72a3_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27257029391"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7006/27257029391_246c4a35bb_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>In terms of gear the hike requires mostly decent shoes. I brought the most minimal and lightweight shoes I own and they were just fine. Apparently the overly successful marketing attracts unsuspecting couch potatoes in flip-flops but I haven&rsquo;t spotted a single person whose clothing stood out as outlandlishly inadequate.</p>

<p>Without any strain we completed the walk in 5:45. We took lots of pictures and made one stop for packed breakfast in the old Samaria village which is in the middle of the route. My watch counted 20Km but I suspect that&rsquo;s due to errors due to poor sky visibility in the gorge. Officially, the total distance from the park entrance to the beach is approximately 17Km. Sounds realistic.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/590696789">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>End of May is a fantastic time to visit it because the gorge is full of life: vegetation and flowers. Most importantly, it is not scorching hot. I find that the scenery becomes interesting after the Samaria village, roughly 8-10Km into the hike. The first half is similar to a walk in a park and it&rsquo;s not possible to see much of the gorge. But the actual gorge looks breathtaking.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27230250722"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7349/27230250722_01d870f748_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>In fact, I would consider visiting the park in the opposite direction: arriving by ship at the end of the route in the morning, exploring the gorge area up to the Samaria village and taking the ship back. It&rsquo;s possible to pull this off with a rental car by keeping it in the town from where the ship departs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27257075871"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7001/27257075871_daabee70cf_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27230278702"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7370/27230278702_2a68bc4ed6_n.jpg" width="213"></a> <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27052293150"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7439/27052293150_bf9f47ae31_n.jpg" width="213"></a></p>

<p>Speaking of transportation it&rsquo;s not great. There are only 3 ships per day: 2 in the morning and only one in the afternoon at 17:30. Those who finish reasonably at about 14:00-15:00 are doomed to stay in the area. Admittedly, the area ain&rsquo;t bad and the beach is completely worth a visit. In case somebody doesn&rsquo;t make it to the ship there are plenty of rooms available for rent.</p>

<p>We chose to get to the park and back by taxi. The price is not unreasonable if staying near city of Chania. For us, the higher taxi price was worth extra hours in the morning and in the evening. A tourist bus takes longer because it needs to pick-up tourists from various hotels.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720065894"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7558/26720065894_49f0bc7d21_c.jpg" width="800"></a></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re visiting Crete pack a pair of shoes &mdash; the gorge is worth a visit!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rigimarsch 2016]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-27T20:10:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another year, another <a href="http://rigimarsch.ch/">Rigimarsch</a>! <a href="/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/">Last year</a> I&rsquo;ve participated in an annual night hike up to the Rigi mountain. It was a tough yet exhilerating experience. This year I&rsquo;ve repeated the challenge together with John.</p>

<p>The route was the same as always: 50 or so kilometers with a 1500m ascent in the last 10 kilometeres. However, the hike felt refreshingly different.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/566448675">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>For me personally the hike was a test for the healing Tibia bone that fractured during last year&rsquo;s <a href="/blog/2015/10/31/goals/">half-marathon in Lausanne</a> (I ran 1/3 of the marathon with a fractured bone).</p>

<p>John looks cheerful but everybody is cheerful at the start:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262027875"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7316/27262027875_338b6e78de_z.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>According to the official information a record 2363 people turned up for the event. Despite the crowd the registration went smoothly. We started walking at around 20:00.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655251944"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7278/26655251944_ef51583b8c.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262034825"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7542/27262034825_1b63a4dd46.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The Rigi mountain. It is intimidating to see the peak far ahead throughout the hike:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26656292463"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7482/26656292463_6e22257b37.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262042505"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7337/27262042505_5bd6972a41.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262043975"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7659/27262043975_f7ddbf3988.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>This year&rsquo;s Rigimarsch took place on May 4th which is relatively early, compared to previous and future years. The event date is tied to Ascension day. Thanks to the early start there was plenty of snow at the top and the night temperatures were quite cool. I wore every piece of clothing I brought along.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655268824"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7360/26655268824_c98e764931.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>I felt energized and positive even in the last hours of the challenge. This is a huge departure from last year&rsquo;s impression. I still vividly recall just how difficult last few hours were. I think several factors are at play. First, I&rsquo;m in much better physical shape for aerobic activities because I switched from weight lifting to triathlon. Second, we brought trekking poles with us for the ascent. Finally, I came to the hike completely rested and fresh.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27192498811"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7539/27192498811_04efa1224b.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>John is still smiling at the top, that&rsquo;s the way to do it:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26655286494"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7711/26655286494_f43a8df2f0.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Return train from Rigi to Arth-Goldau. There were enough places in the train for everyone to take a seat:</p>

<p><a href="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7443/27164821172_47541b80f6.jpg"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7443/27164821172_47541b80f6.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The hike took us about 12 hours to complete which is almost the same as last year. However, our moving time is a whole hour shorter which means we walked measurably faster but took longer breaks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Longest non-stop hike in my life]]></title>
    <link href="http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-24T10:45:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://drseergio.github.io/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On May 13th I established a new personal record for the longest non-stop hike in my life. Not only it involved 52km and 12 hours of walking but also an ascent of 1500m up to Rigi mountain at the very end of the hike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.strava.com/activities/307842580">View our GPS track on Strava</a></p>

<p>Me and my friend Ilya have participated in an annual Swiss event called Rigimarsch. It is a night time hike from a town called Bremgarten all the way up to the Rigi mountain. This year the event attracted 2112 participants.</p>

<p>Note how uplifted we were in the beginning:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18037115871"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7734/18037115871_4bd103eb54.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The registration normally starts at 19:30. It took us about 40 minutes to go through the queue. Despite a lot people the queue was handled efficiently and everyone was friendly. I was surprised to see so many young people as well as older folks and 12 year olds. The biggest surprise was to see them finish!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/17848376818"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5343/17848376818_ea621aca86.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>The weather conditions were perfect. The air was warm during the whole night and we felt comfortable in t-shirts. The first 2 hours of the hike were accompanied by a spectacle of lightnings. Luckily for us it never rained.</p>

<p>The event was exceptionally well executed. There were people regulating the traffic on every intersection of the hiking path with public roads. The route was well indicated with small flags and lamps. It was impossible to get lost. Also, the line of hikers never broke so there were always people in front and ahead of us.</p>

<p>In case someone got tired there were 5 stops where you could take a break, have a snack and take a bus back.</p>

<p>From the 25th kilometer onwards we could see the mountain ahead in the distance. The peak slowly crept closer and closer as our elapsed distance accumulated roughly 40 relatively flat kilometeres. At that point I realized that we still have a mountain to climb. It was gruesome. I could only look at my feet and make one step at a time. I couldn&rsquo;t dare to look up and see just how high we need to go.</p>

<p>The views were fantastic but I felt so tired I could barely continue. I recall feeling really sick and close to throwing up. The last 200 metres up to the summit seemed like eternity.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/17415755603"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8833/17415755603_72136af0a1.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/17848390028"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5321/17848390028_67a6b6f15d.jpg" width="500"></a></p>

<p>Note how tired we looked at the end:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/17415768303"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7686/17415768303_b87de9e979.jpg" width="500"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
