<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Sergey Pisarenko</title>
    <link>http://pisarenko.net/categories/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Sergey Pisarenko</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 19:35:21 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://pisarenko.net/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mantiz Titan Dock</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/06/16/mantiz-titan-dock/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 19:35:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/06/16/mantiz-titan-dock/</guid>
      <description>Although I&amp;rsquo;m working with technology everyday I&amp;rsquo;m a big proponent of using the least amount of tech possible, especially when it comes to my personal life. It&amp;rsquo;s great when a piece of technology fits organically and disappears from sight, causing as little friction as possible. I don&amp;rsquo;t always succeed in my quest but sometimes I stumble upon pure gems!
Just like with this Thundebolt 3 docking station from a lesser known company Mantiz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Santis Classic 2018</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/06/16/santis-classic-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 17:45:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/06/16/santis-classic-2018/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I rode Santis Classic &amp;ndash; an annual bike sportive in the Eastern part of Switzerland, with the start near a town Weinfelden. Getting there from Zurich area takes just an hour by car so I borrowed a fancy Audi A5 from our local car sharing pool in the morning. A bike race is a special occasion, after all.
Santis Classic is an explicitly non-competitive and very inclusive event. For that reason there was no timing provided.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sergey&#39;s Bikeporn &#39;18: May Issue</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/05/01/sergeys-bikeporn-18-may-issue/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 13:40:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/05/01/sergeys-bikeporn-18-may-issue/</guid>
      <description>It is time for some bike photos! Last year I purchased a used foldable bike through an on-line auction for what seemed like a bargain price. Despite being in a deeply sad and abused state that bike looked cheerfully yellow. The bike also came with a bull-horn handlebar and road-bike STI shifters.
It&amp;rsquo;s not difficult to come up with an excuse to buy a new bike. For that reason I could easily justify a foldable bike as means to do quick errands, like getting to the closest car sharing station.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third time&#39;s a charm</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/04/24/third-times-a-charm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 21:08:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/04/24/third-times-a-charm/</guid>
      <description>Three years ago in 2015 I started a sabbatical with a couple of commitments, among which was to run a half marathon. The challenge felt invigorating and extremely exciting. For two and a half months I&amp;rsquo;ve trained hard and got to the finish line. Sadly, in the race I broke my left leg due to what is known as a stress fracture.
I never gave up on the challenge and that single episode motivated me to make sports an important part of everyday life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three wonderful bike rides</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/11/05/three-wonderful-bike-rides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2017 16:31:34 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/11/05/three-wonderful-bike-rides/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2017 has been a wonderful year for cycling: regular club rides, a bike tour along Rhone river and to Cannes (to be shared later), riding in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/07/02/cycling-in-gran-canaria/&#34;&gt;Gran Canaria&lt;/a&gt; and many worthwhile local rides in Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/3rides/gs/05.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The fall has been a scenic gift. No other season is as attractive as the fall in Switzerland. It&amp;rsquo;s full of colors and the dry weather is pleasant for riding.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two-day three-pass bike tour</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/09/17/two-day-three-pass-bike-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Sep 2017 17:59:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/09/17/two-day-three-pass-bike-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m steadily increasing my coverage of Swiss landscapes by cycling through its most distinct features and national cycling routes. Last week I took Friday off and went on a 2-day adventure up a few iconic mountain passes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cycling in Gran Canaria</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/07/02/cycling-in-gran-canaria/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2017 09:39:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/07/02/cycling-in-gran-canaria/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/21/30th-anniversary-bike-tour/&#34;&gt;I said I&amp;rsquo;ll ride somewhere exotic&lt;/a&gt; so I did. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last week with my DW on the Gran Canaria island. It was another attempt at a sport holiday (the last one &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/04/fail/&#34;&gt;failed spectacularly&lt;/a&gt;). Gran Canaria enjoys a pleasant climate that&amp;rsquo;s conducive to both, doing sports and relaxing at the hotel almost the whole year round. So it&amp;rsquo;s not a surprise both of us had a great time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/34855557173&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/5/4266/34855557173_70630e7929_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The sorrows of high-paid work</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/26/the-sorrows-of-high-paid-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 17:00:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/26/the-sorrows-of-high-paid-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What to do when you&amp;rsquo;re in a handsomely paid position but feel dreadful of most working days? When you feel like you&amp;rsquo;re not challenged, your mind rotting away while others are excited about their work? What to do when you&amp;rsquo;re paid a fortune to do the work you hate or even abhor? I wish I have come across a post like this 2, 3, maybe 4 years ago. I probably won&amp;rsquo;t open anyone&amp;rsquo;s eyes but if just one person in the same pair of shoes finds this post encouraging and gets provoked to think further I consider my mission complete. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>30th anniversary bike tour</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/21/30th-anniversary-bike-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 17:00:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/21/30th-anniversary-bike-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not even a week has passed since the Ironman bike race but I was already on two wheels cycling across Switzerland. I&amp;rsquo;ve crossed Switzerland &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;once from West to East in just one go&lt;/a&gt; but last week I turned 30 so I looked for something less challenging and more relaxing to celebrate the moment. I took a Friday off and went off on a 2-day bike tour across the country. This time from North to South&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/route3.jpg&#34; width=&#34;645&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first ever bike race</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/20/my-first-ever-bike-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 17:28:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/20/my-first-ever-bike-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/im703.jpg&#34; class=&#34;noborder&#34; width=&#34;740&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;On June 11th I have entered and completed my first bike race! About 4 months ago, as I climbed off my bike after a training session, a surge of endorphins pushed me to call Ilya to sign-up for a team race. The race consisted of 1km swim, 90km bike and 21km run. I have regretted the decision shortly thereafter but it was already too late to bail out&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike tour in canton Jura</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/05/bike-tour-in-canton-jura/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 19:36:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/05/bike-tour-in-canton-jura/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Summer 2017 is off to a great start! I&amp;rsquo;ve been using every opportunity to get out and ride. Over the past few weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to squeeze in 3 Uetliberg ascents / descents (with one over-the-handlebars crash), regular rides with the Zurich/Zug peloton group as well as other local rides. Last Thursday was a holiday so I took Friday off and made a long weekend to make the best out of the great weather. I cycled through canton Jura (rather a part of it) in 2 days. Jura is beautiful! And the tour turned out to be quite difficult&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/jura_route.jpg&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sprechen wir lieber Deutsch?</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/16/sprechen-wir-lieber-deutsch/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 17:12:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/16/sprechen-wir-lieber-deutsch/</guid>
      <description>Last Friday I completed German B2 examination. B2 is a fairly difficult level and it&amp;rsquo;s one step away (although a significant one) from complete fluency (C1). I&amp;rsquo;d like to share my experience of going from almost zero working German level to being employed at a German speaking company (I&amp;rsquo;m the only person at the office whose native language isn&amp;rsquo;t Swiss German or German) in roughly 1 year&amp;rsquo;s time. I should add that I started the job about 6 months after starting with German.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fail</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/04/fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 21:12:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/04/fail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We humans are first to share our greatest achievements and &amp;ldquo;ups&amp;rdquo; in life but rarely do we like to admit failures, especially when it&amp;rsquo;s related to our most cherished values and strivings. Well, I&amp;rsquo;m human and I fail. More often lately than ever before. My most recent failure is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/02/03/madrid-marathon-2017/&#34;&gt;Madrid marathon 2017 which I was looking forward to&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/anna_dance.gif&#34; class=&#34;noborder&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/&#34;&gt;After breaking a bone during my first &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; marathon in Lausanne in 2015&lt;/a&gt; I had to take a long break from training runs. Fractures take patience. Despite my best efforts and a reworked training plan I experienced an injury about 4 weeks before the marathon date, right after finishing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strava.com/activities/915541780&#34;&gt;a nice 19Km run along the lake&lt;/a&gt;. I hoped for recovery but refrained from making the injury worse. Well, it didn&amp;rsquo;t heal completely so I took a decision to withdraw from participation. That didn&amp;rsquo;t preclude me and my DW from seeing Madrid&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo static site generator</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/28/hugo-static-site-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2017 21:00:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/28/hugo-static-site-generator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/hugo-logo.png&#34; class=&#34;center noborder&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like talking about blog platforms. Usually, you find such posts on abandoned personal web pages. As a rule, such a post goes on to talk in length about the technical solution and the configuration. Unfortunately, the author then posts a couple of brief updates and disappears forever. In other words, posting about the blogging platform is a bad omen. I have restrained myself from discussing this blog&amp;rsquo;s setup until now and I hope this won&amp;rsquo;t ruin it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog is powered by a static site generator. I type content into plain text files and then a program generates a complete website with all the links, styles and pages. There is no admin console and no WYSIWYG editor. There is no database and no dynamic server-side environment. Last week I have migrated from one generator (&lt;a href=&#34;http://octopress.org/&#34;&gt;Octopress&lt;/a&gt;) to another (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;). In this post I&amp;rsquo;d like to briefly share how I run this blog and how the migration went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning math</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/25/learning-math/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2017 17:53:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/25/learning-math/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;$$
\int_{1}^2 x^2\,e^{2x}cos(x)\,dx
$$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you asked me early last year what these symbols mean I would not have had a clue! For the past 6 months I was on a mission to improve my understanding of mathematics from that of a rusty high school level to at least college level. One could call it a &amp;ldquo;side project&amp;rdquo; as I was averaging about 8-20 hours per week on it. I&amp;rsquo;d like to share the approach I took, explain my reasons for doing it as well as uncover the challenges I faced along the journey. Of course, this journey towards knowledge never ends and is still ongoing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Madrid Marathon 2017</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/02/03/madrid-marathon-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/02/03/madrid-marathon-2017/</guid>
      <description>To complete a full Iron Man is still an important milestone for me. I really dig endurance challenges. However, I reluctantly decided to reduce the number of hours of training per week and let the ultimate deadline slip a year or two into the future. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend 15 hours per week of training on it yet. There are ongoing projects that I am not willing to sacrifice. In a way I&amp;rsquo;m adapting to the opportunities that currently present themselves instead of forcefully pushing a preconceived plan against the reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - From First to Bussalp</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/03/photo-report-from-first-to-bussalp/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/03/photo-report-from-first-to-bussalp/</guid>
      <description>This week we went to the Grindelwald area for hiking. Getting there wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy &amp;ndash; a relatively long 4-hour train journey each way plus additional delays due to an accident on the tracks. The accidents seem to become common as the same happened the week before. Anyhow, Grindelwald is vast with hiking routes. I&amp;rsquo;ve been to Grindelwald several times before and even stayed overnight once. Our hike wasn&amp;rsquo;t difficult but very pretty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of my consumerism addiction</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/02/the-many-faces-of-my-consumerism-addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/02/the-many-faces-of-my-consumerism-addiction/</guid>
      <description>Just like junkies deny their addictions I denied mine for as long as I could. Perhaps I am predisposed to addictions as I notice just how quickly obsessions form in my mind from even the most remote sparks of excitement. Mainstream drugs &amp;ndash; alcohol, nicotine, etc &amp;ndash; have never caught my fancy but the more subtle hijackers haven&amp;rsquo;t left my brain&amp;rsquo;s reward system untouched. In this post I&amp;rsquo;m going share my struggle against a deeply rooted consumerism addiction that I have only recently taken a hold of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewell, BMW F800GS Adventure!</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28495010395&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8479/28495010395_0fe544ede9_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, my beloved motorbike is gone to another owner. This leaves me with zero motorized vehicles. At the outset of 2016 I have decided to part ways with a BMW F800GS Adventure I had purchased brand new about two years ago. With a little help from my matchmaking the beamer and the new owner successfully found each other and left the garage not to be seen again. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep fond memories of the wonderful spaceship-like machine that enabled &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/&#34;&gt;an epic and life-changing 8000Km tour of Northern and Central Europe&lt;/a&gt; and left positive emotions. I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to completely quit riding bikes but I have no intentions to own another motorbike in foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - Silent Nanztal Valley Crossing</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/20/photo-report-silent-nanztal-valley-crossing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/20/photo-report-silent-nanztal-valley-crossing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday I hiked a fantastic route together with my wife. It&amp;rsquo;s the first real hike this year and given the busy times it&amp;rsquo;s unsurprising. But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just the first of a season. It was the most difficult hike my wife has ever completed and I was left totally impressed with her pace and endurance. Not only we walked for more than 15 kilometers but we also climbed almost a thousand vertical meters. For my wife, who normally prefers flat walks along ridges or lakes, it is a considerable accomplishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27778716403&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8896/27778716403_ef72bbbe0e.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cube Cross Disc Mk3</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have purchased the Cube Cross Disc bicycle second-hand back in 2014 as an ultimate do-it-all machine to replace somewhat petite &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/&#34;&gt;BMC hybrid bike&lt;/a&gt; I had started cycling on. No other bike in my stable went through as many alterations as the venerable Cube, transitioning from an object of admiration to almost scrap and most recently getting resurrected to fulfill a pragmatic new purpose. It was the bike I rode during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/&#34;&gt;legendary Rhine tour&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps it is also the bike I&amp;rsquo;ve learned most of the bike mechanic skills on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27799786284&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8682/27799786284_5b8f05055e_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First 4000m climb</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/16/first-4000m-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/16/first-4000m-climb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am not a peak collector by any stretch of imagination. Indeed I avoid &amp;ldquo;the best&amp;rdquo; like plague. I leave &amp;ldquo;the best&amp;rdquo; for the unsuspecting tourist crowds and boastful blabbers. But the fact is that I&amp;rsquo;ve climbed to the highest altitude in my life. And I&amp;rsquo;ve already paid my dues by feeling the wrath of Gods &amp;ndash; reaching the peak left me untouched and the corresponding up-and-down motions were anything but mindful. Yet the purpose of this 2-day mountaineering trip has been fulfilled &amp;ndash; I am now &lt;em&gt;formally&lt;/em&gt; skilled in the basic skills of alpine walking and climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28288171755&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8862/28288171755_3c9cc512a8_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Triathlon progress update</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update/</guid>
      <description>I enjoy training for triathlon immensely. The sport attracts me with multidimensionality and the numerous skills involved. There is so much room for growth. It&amp;rsquo;s an art really. I will regularly share some of my observations as I progress towards my next triathlon goal - completing a half Ironman.
Cycling After raving about Zwift and following its 4 month training program I chose to continue my training using TrainerRoad software instead.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samaria Gorge hike</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/30/samaria-gorge-hike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Exactly two weeks ago I thought I was exhausted from preparing for job interviews (I will write a separate post explaining my study strategy). After all, I have been averaging 6-8 hours of algorithms and Java study almost every day for 2 months (I am switching careers and going full-time in software engineering). In reality, it was a virus that caused physical break-down, an eye infection and fever. In what can be described as the most spontaneous decision of my life I decided we need to take a short break and go to the sea. How spontaneous? I felt debilitating headache Monday morning and we flew out on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/26720077554&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7444/26720077554_8d954f1239_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indoor cycling lab</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Around Christmas in 2015 I received doctor&amp;rsquo;s diagnosis that my left tibia bone is fractured and that I can&amp;rsquo;t run for the foreseeable future. Of course, I tried against all reason but the persisting pain made me realize it&amp;rsquo;s in my own best interest to let it heal peacefully and not break it completely. Luckily, I discovered that cycling and swimming don&amp;rsquo;t hurt at all. I suppose that&amp;rsquo;s because the load spread is altered and tibia is not as stressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306868565&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7345/27306868565_5c29150c79_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rigimarsch 2016</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/27/rigimarsch-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another year, another &lt;a href=&#34;http://rigimarsch.ch/&#34;&gt;Rigimarsch&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;Last year&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve participated in an annual night hike up to the Rigi mountain. It was a tough yet exhilerating experience. This year I&amp;rsquo;ve repeated the challenge together with John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27262027875&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7316/27262027875_338b6e78de_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike fitting basics for triathlon and road cycling</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/</guid>
      <description>As a complete triathlon newbie I benefit tremendously from the experience and knowledge of others. Just a few little steps save years, if not decades, of trial-and-error, not to mention decrease chances of injuries and increase enjoyment of the sport. My friend Ilya Nedbailo who has successfully completed his first 70.3 Ironman in Rapperswil this year generously shared a couple of tips.
The first of which is getting a professional bike fitting service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A long new journey ahead</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/</guid>
      <description>Training for a half-marathon and then successfully finishing one (although not without an injury) hooked me on pursuing further challenges. I haven&amp;rsquo;t run a half-marathon as a way to prove anything. Rather the competition had given me an opportunity to reassure myself that I&amp;rsquo;m capable of carrying out longer undertakings. Ten weeks from zero to finish has been a fantastic learning experience so I am looking forward to the next step which is not only longer but also more challenging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The wonderful way of carabike</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In September, following a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/&#34;&gt;Fargo rebuild&lt;/a&gt; with s Rohloff Speedhub I have went to ride it in Italy. This time, though, I haven&amp;rsquo;t ridden my bike from A to B. Instead, I cheated and went my wife on a car. The revelation that had followed I have succinctly nicknamed &amp;ldquo;car-a-bike&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22802670766&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5719/22802670766_f754cb289e.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;I FUCKING DID IT&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; keeps resonating in my head as I am crossing the finish line. I can already feel latent excruciating pain (amplified by an adrenaline-fueled last half-mile sprint) slowly setting in. Few minutes later I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to walk but at this glorious energizing moment I feel that my whole life is coming together.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s how successfully finishing a half-marathon felt to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025248504&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5699/22025248504_84a4c75689.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salsa Fargo Mk3 - now with Rohloff!</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with a Salsa Fargo bicycle exactly one year ago. The bike made me newly excited about cycling. No wonder I&amp;rsquo;ve put more than 4000 kilometers on it. I never rode the bike stock and rebuilt it with custom parts as soon as I received it by post (frames were out of stock in July last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21125844901&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/587/21125844901_1e84167b89_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the tour around France I decided to change a few things on the bike to better suit the kind of riding that I do:
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trip report from bicycle tour across France</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/</guid>
      <description>Riding vs buying I am amused with the nontrivial amount of invented needs by the bicycle industry as well as the strength of its marketing departments. Each year brings new wheel/tire size standards, new drive-train groupsets and mass-produced lifestyles and attitudes. Suddenly, many enthusiasts desperately realize their need for full-suspension fat bikes with a certain kind of axles for &amp;ldquo;backpacking&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;adventure&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;expeditions&amp;rdquo;. I don&amp;rsquo;t see how bicycle gear obsession is any different from the common consumerism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Across France on a bicycle</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/</guid>
      <description>Following numerous episodes of soul searching I finally came to realize that enjoy cycling more than an average person. While I enjoy many flavors of it, such as road cycling and mountain down-hill riding my absolute favorites are endurance and touring rides.
My dream is to visit as many places on a bicycle as I could. Somehow biking[1] feels to me just the right way to explore the world. Last year I joined my very first cycling tour along the river Rhine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mountaineering in Valais</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/10/mountaineering-in-valais/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There comes a moment in a life of a dormant adventurer when the curtains of undesired comfort are torn away and the world is finally seen through wide-open eyes, fueled by challenge and gore, excitement and joy. In this very moment feelings of inadequacy and out-of-placeness give way to sincere enthusiasm and appreciation and beauty of the world. I am boundlessly joyful to cross that imaginary line and thirstily imbibe from the cup of mountaineering and alpine beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19397145808&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19397145808_340b94e192_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such life-changing shift of perception comes from just a single adventure that I have had the tremendous luck to be a part of. Last Saturday I joined company of JD, Samuel and Clément to trek for 5 days through a mountain range in the French canton Valais of Switzerland, through ice, snow and rock. In the best tradition of Sergey the journey has been one of the hardest things he has ever done in his life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going to a first alpine tour</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/going-to-a-first-alpine-tour/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m feeling excited because tomorrow I&amp;rsquo;m going on my first alpine tour. It&amp;rsquo;s a 5 day tour and we&amp;rsquo;re going to walk on ice and snow. We&amp;rsquo;re heading to region Valais which is not far from Mont Blanc that I had visited earlier this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I already have relatively lots of mountain/climbing gear I had to purchase new stiff boots and other stuff. Packing is in progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/19388461925&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/421/19388461925_fbfcdc2fa9_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s hope for good weather and some nice shots!
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - summer walk in Flumserberg</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-summer-walk-in-flumserberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-summer-walk-in-flumserberg/</guid>
      <description>Flumserberg is a popular ski destination because it is close to Zürich. But it&amp;rsquo;s also beautiful in summer. I&amp;rsquo;ve visited Flumserberg last Sunday for an easy downhill walk.
It&amp;rsquo;s popular with paragliders:

Mountain shed:

Panoramic view from the top:

Säschmoor peak (2196m):

Seebenalp hotel / restaurant:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - walk along the Mont Blanc massif</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-walk-along-the-mont-blanc-massif/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/03/photo-report-walk-along-the-mont-blanc-massif/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Weather conditions in Mont Blanc, France, has been favorable this week. So we spontaneously decided to visit it. On a last year&amp;rsquo;s visit we were unlucky as the region was covered in clouds and it was raining so we couldn&amp;rsquo;t see a thing nor go for a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/mini-rescue.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/mini-rescue.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way to Mont Blanc we experienced what it feels like to have a car tire burst while going at highway speeds. Nothing exciting or dangerous. Our rental car did not have a spare wheel and the tire was torn to shreds so we had to call evacuation. All in all, only 1.5 hours lost on the incident.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longest non-stop bicycle ride in my life</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After gruesome 27+ hours of cycling I feel elated to announce that I have successfully completed the challenge! I have cycled non-stop for 420.8 kilometers, climbing 4953 metres worth of hills and obstacles along the way. The ride has been the greatest physical challenge I&amp;rsquo;ve done in my life. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;The longest non-stop hike goes to 2nd place now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/400km_ride.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/400km_ride.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Across Switzerland in one day</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/23/across-the-switzerland-in-one-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/23/across-the-switzerland-in-one-day/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE: Success! I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to complete the ride, totaling 420.8 km and 4953m of vertical ascent in 27 hours of biking.
Last year I&amp;rsquo;ve successfully completed a 300km bicycle day ride and earned a new personal record for distance. On a wonderful day of today I&amp;rsquo;m going to set a new personal record and ride for 400-or-so kilometers across Switzerland in less than 24 hours.
My route follows a slightly shortened version of the official Swiss route number 9:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Startlit silk factory</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/18/startlit-silk-factory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/18/startlit-silk-factory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I always wanted to experiment with night photographs of the sky. A pre-requisite is a clear sky and as little light pollution as possible. The island of Rodos in Greece is a perfect contender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and my wife took our little rental car and drove along the road while we searched for pitch black spots and possible places to stop. We found an ancient silk factory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18314135863&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/starlit-rodos.jpg&#34; width=&#34;427&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result seems okay for a first try. I admit it was a bit scary to stand alone in the darkness in a middle of nowhere.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I have quit an awesome job</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18863676532&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3716/18863676532_dd50531ca1_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke up at five in the morning today and headed to the airport with my beloved wife to fly out to celebrate our wedding anniversary on one of the beautiful Greek islands. As I am typing this on my computer during the flight I do not yet fully comprehend that our vacation is not going to end like most vacations do: two weeks later at the office. That is because earlier in May I inked a decision to voluntarily resign from one of the best places to work in the world. Since I made the announcement I have been predominantly asked three questions:
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twenty first CENTURY ride</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a hot Sunday I have joined a couple of cycling enthusiasts to cover an imperial century in the vicinity of canton Zurich:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/century-ride.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/century-ride.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zug to Ziegelbrucke ride</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/04/zug-to-ziegelbrucke-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/04/zug-to-ziegelbrucke-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a Saturday two weeks ago I went on a bike ride from Zug to Ziegelbrucke through Einsideln and Pfaffikon. I was pretty familiar with many parts of the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/zug-ziegelbrucke.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/zug-ziegelbrucke.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longest non-stop hike in my life</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 13th I established a new personal record for the longest non-stop hike in my life. Not only it involved 52km and 12 hours of walking but also an ascent of 1500m up to Rigi mountain at the very end of the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me and my friend Ilya have participated in an annual Swiss event called Rigimarsch. It is a night time hike from a town called Bremgarten all the way up to the Rigi mountain. This year the event attracted 2112 participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note how uplifted we were in the beginning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18037115871&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7734/18037115871_4bd103eb54.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updates to the 802.11ac guide</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/05/updates-to-the-802-dot-11ac-guide/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/05/updates-to-the-802-dot-11ac-guide/</guid>
      <description>I have previuosly written a guide to configure a 802.11ac access point using hostapd in gentoo linux. Another enthusiast discovered that my guide does not lead to a working access point. Turns out I missed crucial steps to configure DFS which is required for operating on higher frequencies. In this guide I diagnose the problem and correct the mistakes. I also show how to increase transmission (TX) power of the wireless card.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Centovalli bike ride</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/22/centovalli-bike-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/22/centovalli-bike-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since I rode with my friend John around Swiss-Italian lakes 2 weeks ago I wanted to return and do a loop that goes into Italian valley Centovalli. We had omitted it from our tour because topographical maps were suggesting that there&amp;rsquo;s 2200m of climbing involved and that was outside of our &amp;ldquo;daily budget&amp;rdquo;. However, so much ascent seemed excessive for an altitude difference of 600m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/centovalli-loop.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/centovalli-loop.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday me and my friends Riccardo and Codrin came back to bust this myth once and for all. Turns out that a loop that goes into the valley from Locarno involves just 800-900m of climbing! Since that was too easy for us I added a small surprise at the final half of the route bringing total ascent to respectable 1561m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Credit card tour of Italian/Swiss lakes</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/05/credit-card-tour-of-italian-slash-swiss-lakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/05/credit-card-tour-of-italian-slash-swiss-lakes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I commute daily all year round my cycling season never stops. Longer rides, however, mostly don&amp;rsquo;t happen in winter. To open 2015 biking season I went with my friend John on a 2-day cycling tour during the Easter holiday. Because the weather forecast was predicting windy and rainy conditions in most of the Switzerland we decided to go south and ride along several lakes in Italy and Ticino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/italylakemap.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/italylakemap.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to order Dell XPS 13 with US keyboard in Europe</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/05/how-to-order-dell-xps-13-with-us-keyboard-in-europe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/05/how-to-order-dell-xps-13-with-us-keyboard-in-europe/</guid>
      <description>I decided to purchase a laptop as I find myself longing for a computer away from my beloved workstation more often. Last time I bought a laptop was 8 years ago.
Dell built a laptop I feel genuinely excited about - the new XPS 13. It&amp;rsquo;s as small as 11&amp;rdquo; machine with really narrow bezel. It comes with specs that are just right for me.

However, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that buying from Dell is not that easy!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The problems I don&#39;t have</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/03/03/the-problems-i-dont-have/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/03/03/the-problems-i-dont-have/</guid>
      <description>The bookshelves and the Internet are filled with articles and books containing life-changing ideas. Between fiction, non-fiction, psychology, biographies and self-help literature lies a curriculum unfulfillable in thousands of life times. Many of the ideas have the potential to drastically improve one&amp;rsquo;s life. But there is a world of difference between just agreeing and truly internalizing any one of those ideas. And there&amp;rsquo;s even a wider gap between applying an idea in a safe limited environment versus applying it in a high stakes situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beginners guide to a custom 802.11ac setup</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/02/01/beginners-guide-to-802-dot-11ac-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/02/01/beginners-guide-to-802-dot-11ac-setup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/80211ac.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/80211ac.jpg&#34; class=&#34;right&#34; width=&#34;240&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 3 months ago I had nothing better to do so I decided to replace an off-the-shelf Linksys E4200 wireless router with a custom build running an unrestricted O/S. I admit E4200 worked reliably through the years on stock firmware but I never felt comfortable with the privacy and network vulnerability aspects of commonly sold devices. And I find third-party router firmwares too complicated to fully comprehend and tweak. There&amp;rsquo;s simply too much configuration becauase it needs to satisfy many use cases.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycle adventure in Norway</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In May 2014 I embarked on a motorcycle journey through many European countries with Norway as the destination. The round-trip tour from Zürich, Switzerland was about 8000 Km long and took about 4 unrushed weeks to complete. It was a first ride of such length for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/16169221988/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/16169221988_f3d234f1fd_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from a 10 day bicycle tour, part 2</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;continued from part 1.
12. Nutrition and hydration Regular nutrition is key to riding sustainably for many kilometers. In the morning or the previous evening you should stock up on dried fruit, bananas, bars and other snacks. I can ride for many hours if I eat something small every hour or so.
Big meals are great but they are time consuming. There&amp;rsquo;s also a fat chance of overeating. I recommend planning for dinner and nothing else.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from a 10 day bicycle tour, part 1</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</guid>
      <description>2014 is a pivotal year in my cycling &amp;ldquo;career&amp;rdquo;. I went on my first multi-day tour. I went on my first multi-week tour. I&amp;rsquo;ve set a personal distance record. And I&amp;rsquo;ve set a personal vertical ascent record. Admittedly, I did not do the best job documenting and sharing. But I digress.
On the 1st of May 2014 me and a 4 friends from work embarked on a biking trip from Andermatt, Switzerland, to Rotterdam, Netherlands, along the river Rhine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To the north</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/29/to-the-north/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/29/to-the-north/</guid>
      <description>Switzerland-Germany-Denmark-Sweden-Norway-Latvia-Lithuania-Poland-Czech-Germany-Switzerland, day T-1!
Phew, that was a mouthful. Tomorrow I am leaving for a 4 week motorcycle tour across Europe heading to the North. Every summer for the past couple of years I was swearing that next year I am going to be somewhere North, rather than elbowing annoying tourists in the Southern honeypot tourist traps. Finally, I am doing it!
I have been dreaming of this trip for years. I am not going to lie and say that I planned this trip in detail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 3</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/26/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/26/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the part 3 of cyclocross bicycle build series. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/&#34;&gt;Jump to part 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly mentioned in one of the previous posts that I am building this bike specifically for touring around Switzerland and Europe. Together with a couple of colleagues we went on a bike tour from Andermatt, Switzerland to Rotterdam, Netherlands along the Rhine river. I&amp;rsquo;ll be covering the tour separately in a series of posts. In this post, however, I would like to share lessons learned from the building process and the bike itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/14089596650/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2901/14089596650_1cb8553bdd.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycle tour: days T-414 and T-64, California Superbike School and BMW Enduro Park Hechlingen</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/25/bmw-enduro-park-hechlingen/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/25/bmw-enduro-park-hechlingen/</guid>
      <description>I always had passion for motorbikes, especially so because everyone around me tried to prevent me from riding as I was growing up. I have started riding motorcycles just 3 years ago not knowing what to expect. I was not sure about whether I want to ride sport bikes or off-road monsters or touring rigs or choppers. Last year I went to a 2 day training camp at California Superbike School to their Las Vegas Motor Speedway offering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 2</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/</guid>
      <description>This is the part 2 of cyclocross bicycle build series. Jump to part 1.
Disassembly preparation With the bicycle, materials, tools and parts figured out I was ready to begin the disassembly process. Taking things apart is fun and bicycles are not exception to this rule. As a guide I reversed the bike assembly order from Parking Tool website. The process starts with the chain removal and continue along the drive train until the levers and controls are taken off.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first solder job</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/my-first-solder-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/my-first-solder-job/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year I realized that I am wasteful with photo gear so I decided to switch to one digital camera system. I&amp;rsquo;ve sold all cameras and various gear I had from before and settled on Sony A7R. One thing I appreciated from my Canon collection is Yongnuo set of flashes and remote radio triggers. Yongnuo are inexpensive and for a price of one Canon flash I got two flashes and radio controllers. However, despite the fact the flash mounts are the same on Sony A7R and Canon 70D the Yongnuo RF603 radio trigger did not work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out the solution is one resistor away! I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered the following YouTube video that explains how to make the trigger work with Sony cameras. The solution is to solder a 120kOhm transistor between yellow wire and battery contact plate.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Iiy4zGEt5xU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For years I have avoided any DIY job that requires soldering. I decided now it&amp;rsquo;s finally the time to purchase a solder iron and finally understand basics of electronics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/solder/solder_station.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/solder/solder_station_s.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/solder/yongnuo_solder.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/solder/yongnuo_solder_s.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aaaand success! The trigger now works great on Sony. I know this job was extremely simple but for me it has been satisfying to make a physical electronic thing work differently.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee experiment 2 months later</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13697133974/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/13697133974_4624909376_n.jpg&#34; class=&#34;left&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;213&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I had initially &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/&#34;&gt;experimented with drinking enormous amounts of coffee per day&lt;/a&gt; I abandoned coffee completely. The side effects were too bothersome. I slept too long, crashed too hard during the day and felt pronounced headaches unless I&amp;rsquo;ve drank a cup a day. Two extremes got me thinking - could I perhaps find an optimal middle ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 1</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Prologue There is a trend I noticed myself going through. First, I tend to acquire lots of equipment and accessories for a hobby or an activity. Then I realize what my true needs are. At some point I get overwhelmed with the gear I don&amp;rsquo;t use regularly and feel wasteful. Finally, I minimize possessions by trading them to fewer precious alternatives. I went through this process with PCs and servers, laptops, digital cameras, motorcycles and now I&amp;rsquo;m going through the same with bicycles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A sinister camper</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/sinister-camper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/sinister-camper/</guid>
      <description>This sinister camper is found terrorizing streets of Zürich:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee is not my friend</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/</guid>
      <description>About 2 years ago I completely gave up on caffeine. I&amp;rsquo;ve stopped drinking coffee, most kinds of tea and caffeinated beverages such as diet coke. Giving up was not that difficult. I&amp;rsquo;ve never been a die hard fan of coffee though I savor a well prepared black tea and an occasional coke.
A negative consequence of completely giving up on caffeine is that even the tiniest bit disrupts a good night sleep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - essential Seattle</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-essential-seattle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-essential-seattle/</guid>
      <description>Visiting Seattle for the first time has been an unexpectedly pleasant experience.

    
The city is walkable and has great infrastructure. I found bike lanes everywhere and public transport. It&amp;rsquo;s the first US city that I find appealing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - intentionality</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-intentionality/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/02/photo-report-intentionality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been lately practicing intentional photography - having a purpose and a general idea/plan in mind before making captures. The biggest change I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed is that the number of keepers has risen from an average of 2-6% to 15-25%!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I present two projects that I undertook during a recent stay in Seattle, Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trainspotting&#34;&gt;Trainspotting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love trains. It turns out that I love making pictures of them too! I suspect that together with landscapes and abandoned places trains are my favorite subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248701365&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2862/12248701365_0cff763be3_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248668105&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7305/12248668105_ab33bde7be_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248850553&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5485/12248850553_2167955d74_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248671175&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3800/12248671175_349365dcb4_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248664195&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5506/12248664195_5d66f5709d_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have asked a colleague to provide a map with markers to local trainspotting places. On a Saturday morning I packed the gear and went walking along one of the major lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12248656935&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3738/12248656935_7a8f7bf725_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249263096&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3781/12249263096_f822922ec8_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249122624&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7344/12249122624_b9421dfc87_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not feel safe. Everywhere I found signs saying that trespassing is illegal and that BNSF police is going to arrest me. I was careful not to cross any legal lines. I wish I could get closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chronos&#34;&gt;Chronos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second project I took pictures of clocks I could find in our Seattle office. The building screams with interesting art objects and decorations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249639094&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7434/12249639094_a5c66cc3f1_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249204355&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3712/12249204355_6ff341e06a_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249636794&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3788/12249636794_2551b0ca0f_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249643254&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2877/12249643254_7bdaa8e9f8_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/12249768446&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7340/12249768446_2c87c64358_q.jpg&#34; width=&#34;150&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dilbert cartoonist on goals</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/</guid>
      <description>I have just finished reading Scott Adams&amp;rsquo; book How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big: Kind of the Story of My Life. In the book the cartoonist behind Dilbert comic shares his views on success in a witty and humorous way.
He talks about goals among other things. He finds goals to be inadequate for long-term personal success. Among the reasons is the perpetual feeling of failure. And what do you do after reaching a goal?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 months on a bike</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/</guid>
      <description>I like bicycles. I like riding them, I like fiddling with them. But for some reason I never consistently commuted by bicycle. 6 months ago I made a decision to commute by bicycle every single day regardless of the weather. Even if it rains or storms or snows.
As it turns out adverse weather conditions are conquerable with appropriate gear. I am lucky that I have an opportunity to change clothes and take a shower upon my arrival at work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investment portfolio update - December 2013</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/investment-portfolio-update-december-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/investment-portfolio-update-december-2013/</guid>
      <description>December&amp;rsquo;s update The R script does not work anymore! It turns out that Yahoo has disabled URL &amp;ldquo;charts.yahoo.com&amp;rdquo;. However, &amp;ldquo;icharts.finance.yahoo.com&amp;rdquo; works fine. The problem is that the URL is hard coded into quantmod package.
The quick solution is to check-out latest code and build the package from source. The alternative is to wait until CRAN includes quantmod with the fix applied. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I fixed the problem:
# check-out latest quantmod code using subversion $ svn checkout svn://svn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - snowshoeing in Leukerbad</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-leukerbad/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-leukerbad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On one of the last weekends of December me and my wife went to a weekend trip to Leukerbad to enjoy the hot springs and do a little snowshoe tour around a mountain lake Daubensee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving from train station in Zurich:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11675156726&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5501/11675156726_f2a46a740e.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the hotel in Leukerbad:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11674144615&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7445/11674144615_7ab8639d70.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On goals and purpose</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/</guid>
      <description>Christmas and New Year&amp;rsquo;s Eve evoke mass hysteria to reflect and to resolve to change unlike any other time of the year. People write down goals for themselves, think about their purpose in life. Planning and goal setting are praised important even outside of the festivities.
I believe it&amp;rsquo;s mostly harmless but also pointless. I look back to the moment I first embraced the Western custom of goal setting and I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to show for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - snowshoeing in Braunwald</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-braunwald/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-braunwald/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The weather on weekends has been excellent lately. On December 8th me and my friend John went for a snowshoe hike close to Braunwald.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/11372768584/in/set-72157638673432686/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3811/11372768584_33b3da0775.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated news sources</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have added a couple of sites and online magazines to my subscription list. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/news-sources&#34;&gt;News sources&lt;/a&gt; page for the full updated list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/&#34;&gt;Aeon magazine&lt;/a&gt; - Aeon Magazine is an online magazine about nature, culture and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/film/&#34;&gt;Aeon film&lt;/a&gt; - Aeon Film screens contemporary and classic short documentaries, exploring the intersections between nature, culture and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://habrahabr.ru/&#34;&gt;Habrahabr&lt;/a&gt; - (Russian) an online tech-oriented community/aggregator. Most of the articles are written from scratch, rather than republished. I had to spend considerable amount of time unsubscribing from different channels to bring volume down to a manageable level. But apart from that inconvenince there is lots of interesting material that is not published anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://digital-photography-school.com/&#34;&gt;Digital Photography School&lt;/a&gt; - regular tips and guides on digital photography. I like the amount of published material. Frequent enough to be intersting to follow but not as much to become overwhelming.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investment portfolio update - November 2013</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/30/investment-portfolio-update-november-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/30/investment-portfolio-update-november-2013/</guid>
      <description>Novembers&amp;rsquo;s update** As of **&amp;ldquo;2013-11-30&amp;rdquo;
VBK VBR VTV 16.93042 16.68999 14.38888 Last month&amp;rsquo;s VEA&amp;rsquo;s position has been taken by VTV.
We avoid investing if price is below 10 month SMA. Running through 10-month SMA check we get:
VBK VBR VTV TRUE TRUE TRUE This means portfolio should be fully invested in VBK, VBR, VTV.
As of **&amp;ldquo;2013-11-30&amp;rdquo;
symbol 1 3 6 12 avg VBK 2.3614663 11.351201 15.5519199 38.4571033 16.93042264 VBR 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeding brains</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/26/feeding-brains/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/26/feeding-brains/</guid>
      <description>Finding good sources of information is similar to finding a good diet &amp;ndash; there is an overwhelming amount of stuff available (abundance of calories) but the utility (healthiness) of it is close to zero. Many news outlets and online media have incentives that are in conflict with providing thoughtful quality material. Media chases advertisements. In the race to achieve highest numbers of visits and ad impressions it shamelessly bombards us readers with juicy junk articles with loud headlines that shamelessly grab our attention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing it my way</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/25/doing-it-my-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/25/doing-it-my-way/</guid>
      <description>I had a habit of regularly reading books that are of pseudo spiritual and self help and personal growth nature. I did not follow their contents word for word but I believed I could glean useful solutions to life problems and new ways to think about reality. Recently, I came to a conclusion that I&amp;rsquo;m not going to read such books anymore. No more productivity books. No more books on settings goals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - snowshoeing in Arosa</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/21/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-arosa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/21/photo-report-snowshoeing-in-arosa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been sick in and out with all kinds of cold during past several weeks. I had a lucky break last weekend and went for a snowshoe hike in Arosa, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10984441523&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7370/10984441523_6bb5bff50f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve taken the snowshoes on. I had a misconception that snowshoes will let you float on the surface. They won&amp;rsquo;t. After a couple of hours I got a hang of it and could even run. I know I&amp;rsquo;ll be spending time outdoors so I splurged on luxurious MSR ascent snowshoes. These snowshoes have good grip - I could not slide even if I wanted to.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - climbing up via ferrata Feurenwand</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/03/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-feurenwand/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/03/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-feurenwand/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Via ferratas come in different difficulty levels. Last week I&amp;rsquo;ve done a K2 climb. Yesterday I went to Fuerenalp along with two friends and did a K4 climb. The route is a lot more exciting. Wet and slippery stones and supports presented an additional challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10650891073/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5471/10650891073_9c9d90e8e9.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - Halloween special</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/31/photo-report-halloween-special/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/31/photo-report-halloween-special/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had inspiration to work on something creative today. I have decided to experiment with pseudo black back-drop shots. The idea is to setup a camera so that it picks-up light from the flash only. I have produced a video and a couple of photographs. See below!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10598689133/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3823/10598689133_85e0a27c11.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investment portfolio update - October 2013</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/30/investment-portfolio-update-october-2013/</guid>
      <description>Investments are a cornerstone for building passive income, increasing wealth and eventually reaching financial independence. I have passion for learning how the investment world functions and what are the different trading strategies. For the past 4 years I have mostly relied on low-cost index investments and company stock in distressed industries. In addition, I have had lots of interest towards quantitative strategies.
A couple of months ago I have faced a possibility of a major change in life so I have liquidated every investment into cash in preparation for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Photo report - climbing up via ferrata in Pinut</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-in-pinut/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/photo-report-climbing-up-via-ferrata-in-pinut/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This Saturday I had a pleasure to do my first &amp;ldquo;via ferrata&amp;rdquo; climb in Switzerland, in Pinut to be precise. Via ferrata routes do not require climbing experience. The idea is to climb up a mountain and various obstacles while being hooked-up to a metal cable that runs along the whole route. Equipment-wise prospective climbers need a harness, a via ferrata set (a Y-shaped lanyard with an energy absorber) and a helmet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/68217075@N08/10517919016/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3742/10517919016_c7b5b061bb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The photo curse</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/the-photo-curse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/the-photo-curse/</guid>
      <description>I am fascinated with photography. A picture inspires, tells a story, expresses an author&amp;rsquo;s view, captures a fleeting moment, gives an aesthetic pleasure. But there&amp;rsquo;s a way to kill inspiration and make this art forever painful for oneself.
Ever since I&amp;rsquo;ve purchased my own digital camera 4 years ago I&amp;rsquo;ve been both blessed and burdened by photography. I have even purposefully abstained from taking any pictures for at least a couple of lengthy periods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 sold gadgets later or welcome back to Microsoft Windows</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/21/5-sold-gadgets-later-or-welcome-back-to-microsoft-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/21/5-sold-gadgets-later-or-welcome-back-to-microsoft-windows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I honestly would not anticipate writing about Microsoft Windows. Not after I have irrevocably and irreversibly switched to Linux and OSX years ago when I was studying at the university.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here I am, happily typing this in Sublime2 editor on my desktop computer running nothing else but Microsoft Windows 8. Yes, the same computer that had been running Gentoo Linux a week or so ago!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why write at all</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/21/why-write-at-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/21/why-write-at-all/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I have deactivated my Facebook account. I&amp;rsquo;ve been intending to do that for months. Finally, I&amp;rsquo;ve left the service for good.
Looking all the way back to 2006 I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to show for it. You can&amp;rsquo;t call me an addict because I&amp;rsquo;ve never been hooked as much as people around me. Nevertheless, whenever I had cared to open Facebook&amp;rsquo;s trendy blue interface I have been bombarded with meaningless status updates and viral junk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My lucky night with a FreeNAS failure</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/09/08/my-lucky-night-with-freenas-failure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/09/08/my-lucky-night-with-freenas-failure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 1:35am right now and something really bad has happened about 4 hours ago. First, Time Machine on my Mac Mini complained that the backup network disk became inaccessible. Then network shares have stopped responding on all computers. This means something wrong has happened with the wonderful reliable NAS server that I had built weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I connect to the server via SSH and start poking around. Once I notice that file-system commands, such as &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;, cause sessions to hang I become worrisome. I do a reboot hoping that solves the problem. 10 minutes pass. The server does not start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HTPC build I&#39;m proud of</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/09/01/htpc-build-i-slash-m-proud-of/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/09/01/htpc-build-i-slash-m-proud-of/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You may notice that I am somewhat obsessed with reducing the number of possessions in my life. This directly contradicts another, though negative, characteristic of mine - to get more gadgets and possessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I have had a lot of good progress on challenging the negative trait. Not only I&amp;rsquo;ve been more successful on overcoming the purchasing obsession but I&amp;rsquo;ve also found ways to enjoy more and get creative at reusing what I already have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my recent projects was to combine several devices into one. I&amp;rsquo;ve got rid of Sony Playstation 3 and merged 2 computers together. Here&amp;rsquo;s the end-result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/htpc/2.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/htpc/2.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build an Android app using Google Cloud Endpoints and OAuth</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/08/29/build-an-android-app-using-google-cloud-endpoints-with-oauth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/08/29/build-an-android-app-using-google-cloud-endpoints-with-oauth/</guid>
      <description>Recently I came up with an idea for a mobile application. To be honest, it&amp;rsquo;s more of an excuse to try my hand at writing Android applications and do something new. Since I had almost zero experience with Android I have started by reading the official Google guides and then doing some napkin grade designs of the application architecture.
Immediately I have realized that app requires a back-end as some of the things cannot be reliably performed on the handset itself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a FreeNAS computer</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/08/28/impressions-from-freenas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/08/28/impressions-from-freenas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always fancied the idea of having a dedicated storage system to keep personal data and backups. For the last 3 years I have been happily using an off-the-shelf solution - acer easyStore H340.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/freenas/acer.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/freenas/acer.jpg&#34; class=&#34;right&#34; width=&#34;200&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trustedreviews.com/Acer-easyStore-H340-2TB_Peripheral_review&#34;&gt;Acer H340&lt;/a&gt; has 4 hot-swappable SATA slots, occupies little space and looks well. The on-board Atom N230 CPU is not powerful but has low TDP (4W). I have replaced the stock fan with a quieter one and the stock PSU with a passive one to make the server quieter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of software I had installed gentoo Linux with tons of different packages: file-sharing through NFS/CIFS, DNS server, OpenVPN, Bittorrent sync, transmission-web, BackupPC, various proxies and even Pandora ripper! I&amp;rsquo;ve run a RAID5 on 3 disks using mdadm and used the 4th drive for backups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But recently I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to switch to a custom-built solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/freenas/7.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/freenas/7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;450&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Replacing preview glass on Canon 500D</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/07/10/replacing-preview-glass-on-canon-500d/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/07/10/replacing-preview-glass-on-canon-500d/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Material things break all the time - one slightly wrong move and your beloved possession is cracked, damaged or shattered. My camera is no exception. Another SLR has slipped from a hand of my friend and landed on the corner of the preview screen of my Canon 500D causing an ugly crack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/canonrepair/01.jpg&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many folks like to buy new things whenever old ones break or pay a lot for repair. I prefer to fix as much as I can myself. It&amp;rsquo;s fun and very much in-line with the growing stoic inside of me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to fix this problem yourself?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>