<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pro on Sergey Pisarenko</title>
    <link>http://pisarenko.net/categories/pro/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pro on Sergey Pisarenko</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 20:23:07 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://pisarenko.net/categories/pro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Toolkits for Machine Learning</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/09/20/toolkits-for-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 20:23:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/09/20/toolkits-for-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>There are many toolkits available for doing typical data analysis/data mining/machine learning tasks. There are programming languages, libraries, frameworks and development environments to choose from. Some are aimed at solving particular problems, others at techniques and algorithms. This presents a challenge to all the newcomers. Which toolkits to learn? Just one? All of them?
I&amp;rsquo;ve done the mistake of trying to use too many. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using R, Octave, Python and Matlab on and off.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applied Machine learning</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/09/10/applied-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2017 13:34:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/09/10/applied-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to break another blogging taboo. Namely, I admit the prolonged silence. Somehow, &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/28/hugo-static-site-generator/&#34;&gt;talking about the blogging platform&lt;/a&gt; hasn&amp;rsquo;t killed this blog so, who knows, maybe this won&amp;rsquo;t either. I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy changing from one awesome job to another, which I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about in a separate post. From now on, though, I&amp;rsquo;ll keep posting once a week, rotating a few persistent themes: technology (software engineering and machine learning), sports (cycling, running, training), travel and personal reflections. To keep up I&amp;rsquo;ll give myself roughly 1 hour per week to get the post published. We&amp;rsquo;ll see how that goes&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internet-connected motorcycle project, Part 3</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/17/internet-connected-motorcycle-project-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 14:09:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/17/internet-connected-motorcycle-project-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/33707713890&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/3/2817/33707713890_ebf495be81.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final article I finish the series about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/16/internet-connected-motorcycle-project/&#34;&gt;IoT hackathon project&lt;/a&gt; by explaining the server side component of the system. Admittedly, it is the smallest part and I intentionally chose to make it trivially simple. 4 days of project of work is not infinite, after all. I think it took me roughly 4-6 hours to set everything up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internet-connected motorcycle project, Part 2</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/17/internet-connected-motorcycle-project-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 10:09:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/17/internet-connected-motorcycle-project-part-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/33959436251&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/4/3956/33959436251_6c6d9e1c5b.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this second post I continue with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/16/internet-connected-motorcycle-project/&#34;&gt;short hackathon project I worked on last week&lt;/a&gt;. The goal of the project was to hook into engine data of a KTM motorcycle and stream that data in real-time to the cloud. I explain how I reverse engineered the USB wire protocol of a proprietary device called Power Commander 5 from Dynojet and wrote a simple Java program that works on Linux. I also show the tools I used along the way and share my thinking process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internet-connected motorcycle project, Part 1</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/16/internet-connected-motorcycle-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/04/16/internet-connected-motorcycle-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/vitpilen.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/vitpilen.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since autumn 2016 I&amp;rsquo;m working at an IoT company &amp;ndash; we build Internet-connected home automation devices. Last week we had an internal hackathon to try something new. Essentially, it was a chance to work outside of the comfort zone and try out new APIs and hardware in the vast world of IoT. At first I was struggling to come up with an idea. Some ideas seemed trivial, others unrealistic. Finally, I brainstormed over available hardware and my surroundings and decided to make my KTM Duke 390 motorcycle join the IoT party!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Better at Solving Coding (Interview) Problems</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/08/getting-better-at-solving-coding-interview-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/08/getting-better-at-solving-coding-interview-problems/</guid>
      <description>This is part 2 of a series of articles themed &amp;ldquo;Preparing for Software Engineer Interviews&amp;rdquo;. My goal with the series is to document the steps I took while preparing for interviews for a software engineering position after working six years in predominantly support-leaning roles. I won&amp;rsquo;t break new ground here but rather share personal experience &amp;ndash; anything you see here is an echo of what you can find elsewhere on the Internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Kata of Code</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/06/12/the-kata-of-code/</guid>
      <description>This is part 1 of a series of articles themed &amp;ldquo;Preparing for Software Engineer Interviews&amp;rdquo;. My goal with the series is to document the steps I took while preparing for interviews for a software engineering position after working six years in predominantly support-leaning roles. I won&amp;rsquo;t break new ground here but rather share personal experience &amp;ndash; anything you see here is an echo of what you can find elsewhere on the Internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating dynamic task scheduler on AppEngine</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/09/03/creating-dynamic-task-scheduler-on-appengine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/09/03/creating-dynamic-task-scheduler-on-appengine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/app-engine.png&#34; class=&#34;right&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on a simple hobby project. The goal is to build an Android application which, as it turns out, requires a backend. The most important task of the backend is to perform certain things at specified times in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how I&amp;rsquo;ve designed a simple scheduler which relies on AppEngine cron, tasks and the datastore. We will make a new trivial AppEngine application that ties everything together. Although I normally prefer Python but I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen Java for this project. I guess that&amp;rsquo;s because I wanted some consistency with the Android counter-part that I&amp;rsquo;m also developing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing photofs: FUSE file-system for browsing photos</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-photofs-fuse-file-system-for-browsing-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-photofs-fuse-file-system-for-browsing-photos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With yeach passing year the number of photos in my collection is growing. The trend only hockey-sticked once I got my own camera. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried various programs to organize and browse photos. I recall using or trying ACDSee, digiKam, Adobe Bridge, IrfanView, F-Spot, Shotwell and possibly others that I don&amp;rsquo;t recall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing qeytaks: trivial photo tag editor</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-qeytaks-trivial-photo-tag-editor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/06/02/introducing-qeytaks-trivial-photo-tag-editor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the previous post I have introduced &lt;strong&gt;photofs&lt;/strong&gt; - a tool I have written for myself that universally solves my photo management problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;photofs&lt;/strong&gt; I can easily locate photos by albums, tags, dates. But how would I add the tags in the first place? I use Adobe Lightroom and absolutely love it! I don&amp;rsquo;t use it to manage photos. Lightroom is a gateway from the camera to my collection. Once I&amp;rsquo;m done processing photos Lightroom kisses them goodbye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>fruitcoins.com: on complexity and solutions to wrong problems</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/06/02/fruitcoins-dot-com-on-complexity-and-solutions-to-the-wrong-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/06/02/fruitcoins-dot-com-on-complexity-and-solutions-to-the-wrong-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About two years ago I had very little experience in programming in Python. I&amp;rsquo;ve heard of Django and felt excited how flexible it is and how complicated web applications can be elegantly written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracking expenses has always been important for me. At the time I&amp;rsquo;ve relied on KMyMoney program. Frankly, I did not (and still don&amp;rsquo;t) like any such programs. They&amp;rsquo;re either clunky and look like Windows 95 or too complicated or too inefficient. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to write my own web application in Python using the Django framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>