<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reflections on Sergey Pisarenko</title>
    <link>http://pisarenko.net/tags/reflections/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reflections on Sergey Pisarenko</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 17:00:45 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://pisarenko.net/tags/reflections/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The sorrows of high-paid work</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/26/the-sorrows-of-high-paid-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 17:00:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/26/the-sorrows-of-high-paid-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What to do when you&amp;rsquo;re in a handsomely paid position but feel dreadful of most working days? When you feel like you&amp;rsquo;re not challenged, your mind rotting away while others are excited about their work? What to do when you&amp;rsquo;re paid a fortune to do the work you hate or even abhor? I wish I have come across a post like this 2, 3, maybe 4 years ago. I probably won&amp;rsquo;t open anyone&amp;rsquo;s eyes but if just one person in the same pair of shoes finds this post encouraging and gets provoked to think further I consider my mission complete. &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of my consumerism addiction</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/02/the-many-faces-of-my-consumerism-addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/08/02/the-many-faces-of-my-consumerism-addiction/</guid>
      <description>Just like junkies deny their addictions I denied mine for as long as I could. Perhaps I am predisposed to addictions as I notice just how quickly obsessions form in my mind from even the most remote sparks of excitement. Mainstream drugs &amp;ndash; alcohol, nicotine, etc &amp;ndash; have never caught my fancy but the more subtle hijackers haven&amp;rsquo;t left my brain&amp;rsquo;s reward system untouched. In this post I&amp;rsquo;m going share my struggle against a deeply rooted consumerism addiction that I have only recently taken a hold of.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Farewell, BMW F800GS Adventure!</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/23/farewell-bmw-f800gs-adventure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/28495010395&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8479/28495010395_0fe544ede9_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, my beloved motorbike is gone to another owner. This leaves me with zero motorized vehicles. At the outset of 2016 I have decided to part ways with a BMW F800GS Adventure I had purchased brand new about two years ago. With a little help from my matchmaking the beamer and the new owner successfully found each other and left the garage not to be seen again. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep fond memories of the wonderful spaceship-like machine that enabled &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/01/25/motorcycle-adventure-in-norway/&#34;&gt;an epic and life-changing 8000Km tour of Northern and Central Europe&lt;/a&gt; and left positive emotions. I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to completely quit riding bikes but I have no intentions to own another motorbike in foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;I FUCKING DID IT&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; keeps resonating in my head as I am crossing the finish line. I can already feel latent excruciating pain (amplified by an adrenaline-fueled last half-mile sprint) slowly setting in. Few minutes later I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to walk but at this glorious energizing moment I feel that my whole life is coming together.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s how successfully finishing a half-marathon felt to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025248504&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5699/22025248504_84a4c75689.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I have quit an awesome job</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/16/why-i-have-quit-an-awesome-job/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/18863676532&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3716/18863676532_dd50531ca1_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke up at five in the morning today and headed to the airport with my beloved wife to fly out to celebrate our wedding anniversary on one of the beautiful Greek islands. As I am typing this on my computer during the flight I do not yet fully comprehend that our vacation is not going to end like most vacations do: two weeks later at the office. That is because earlier in May I inked a decision to voluntarily resign from one of the best places to work in the world. Since I made the announcement I have been predominantly asked three questions:
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The problems I don&#39;t have</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/03/03/the-problems-i-dont-have/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/03/03/the-problems-i-dont-have/</guid>
      <description>The bookshelves and the Internet are filled with articles and books containing life-changing ideas. Between fiction, non-fiction, psychology, biographies and self-help literature lies a curriculum unfulfillable in thousands of life times. Many of the ideas have the potential to drastically improve one&amp;rsquo;s life. But there is a world of difference between just agreeing and truly internalizing any one of those ideas. And there&amp;rsquo;s even a wider gap between applying an idea in a safe limited environment versus applying it in a high stakes situation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee experiment 2 months later</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/07/coffee-experiment-2-months-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/13697133974/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7380/13697133974_4624909376_n.jpg&#34; class=&#34;left&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;213&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I had initially &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/&#34;&gt;experimented with drinking enormous amounts of coffee per day&lt;/a&gt; I abandoned coffee completely. The side effects were too bothersome. I slept too long, crashed too hard during the day and felt pronounced headaches unless I&amp;rsquo;ve drank a cup a day. Two extremes got me thinking - could I perhaps find an optimal middle ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coffee is not my friend</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/02/07/coffee-is-not-my-friend/</guid>
      <description>About 2 years ago I completely gave up on caffeine. I&amp;rsquo;ve stopped drinking coffee, most kinds of tea and caffeinated beverages such as diet coke. Giving up was not that difficult. I&amp;rsquo;ve never been a die hard fan of coffee though I savor a well prepared black tea and an occasional coke.
A negative consequence of completely giving up on caffeine is that even the tiniest bit disrupts a good night sleep.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dilbert cartoonist on goals</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/07/dilbert-cartoonist-on-goals/</guid>
      <description>I have just finished reading Scott Adams&amp;rsquo; book How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big: Kind of the Story of My Life. In the book the cartoonist behind Dilbert comic shares his views on success in a witty and humorous way.
He talks about goals among other things. He finds goals to be inadequate for long-term personal success. Among the reasons is the perpetual feeling of failure. And what do you do after reaching a goal?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On goals and purpose</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/25/on-goals-and-purpose/</guid>
      <description>Christmas and New Year&amp;rsquo;s Eve evoke mass hysteria to reflect and to resolve to change unlike any other time of the year. People write down goals for themselves, think about their purpose in life. Planning and goal setting are praised important even outside of the festivities.
I believe it&amp;rsquo;s mostly harmless but also pointless. I look back to the moment I first embraced the Western custom of goal setting and I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to show for it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated news sources</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/12/14/updated-news-sources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have added a couple of sites and online magazines to my subscription list. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/news-sources&#34;&gt;News sources&lt;/a&gt; page for the full updated list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/&#34;&gt;Aeon magazine&lt;/a&gt; - Aeon Magazine is an online magazine about nature, culture and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aeon.co/film/&#34;&gt;Aeon film&lt;/a&gt; - Aeon Film screens contemporary and classic short documentaries, exploring the intersections between nature, culture and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://habrahabr.ru/&#34;&gt;Habrahabr&lt;/a&gt; - (Russian) an online tech-oriented community/aggregator. Most of the articles are written from scratch, rather than republished. I had to spend considerable amount of time unsubscribing from different channels to bring volume down to a manageable level. But apart from that inconvenince there is lots of interesting material that is not published anywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://digital-photography-school.com/&#34;&gt;Digital Photography School&lt;/a&gt; - regular tips and guides on digital photography. I like the amount of published material. Frequent enough to be intersting to follow but not as much to become overwhelming.
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feeding brains</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/26/feeding-brains/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/26/feeding-brains/</guid>
      <description>Finding good sources of information is similar to finding a good diet &amp;ndash; there is an overwhelming amount of stuff available (abundance of calories) but the utility (healthiness) of it is close to zero. Many news outlets and online media have incentives that are in conflict with providing thoughtful quality material. Media chases advertisements. In the race to achieve highest numbers of visits and ad impressions it shamelessly bombards us readers with juicy junk articles with loud headlines that shamelessly grab our attention.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing it my way</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/25/doing-it-my-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/11/25/doing-it-my-way/</guid>
      <description>I had a habit of regularly reading books that are of pseudo spiritual and self help and personal growth nature. I did not follow their contents word for word but I believed I could glean useful solutions to life problems and new ways to think about reality. Recently, I came to a conclusion that I&amp;rsquo;m not going to read such books anymore. No more productivity books. No more books on settings goals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The photo curse</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/the-photo-curse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/27/the-photo-curse/</guid>
      <description>I am fascinated with photography. A picture inspires, tells a story, expresses an author&amp;rsquo;s view, captures a fleeting moment, gives an aesthetic pleasure. But there&amp;rsquo;s a way to kill inspiration and make this art forever painful for oneself.
Ever since I&amp;rsquo;ve purchased my own digital camera 4 years ago I&amp;rsquo;ve been both blessed and burdened by photography. I have even purposefully abstained from taking any pictures for at least a couple of lengthy periods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why write at all</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/21/why-write-at-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2013/10/21/why-write-at-all/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I have deactivated my Facebook account. I&amp;rsquo;ve been intending to do that for months. Finally, I&amp;rsquo;ve left the service for good.
Looking all the way back to 2006 I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to show for it. You can&amp;rsquo;t call me an addict because I&amp;rsquo;ve never been hooked as much as people around me. Nevertheless, whenever I had cared to open Facebook&amp;rsquo;s trendy blue interface I have been bombarded with meaningless status updates and viral junk.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>