<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Training on Sergey Pisarenko</title>
    <link>http://pisarenko.net/tags/training/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Training on Sergey Pisarenko</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 17:45:19 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://pisarenko.net/tags/training/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Santis Classic 2018</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/06/16/santis-classic-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2018 17:45:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/06/16/santis-classic-2018/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I rode Santis Classic &amp;ndash; an annual bike sportive in the Eastern part of Switzerland, with the start near a town Weinfelden. Getting there from Zurich area takes just an hour by car so I borrowed a fancy Audi A5 from our local car sharing pool in the morning. A bike race is a special occasion, after all.
Santis Classic is an explicitly non-competitive and very inclusive event. For that reason there was no timing provided.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third time&#39;s a charm</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/04/24/third-times-a-charm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Apr 2018 21:08:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2018/04/24/third-times-a-charm/</guid>
      <description>Three years ago in 2015 I started a sabbatical with a couple of commitments, among which was to run a half marathon. The challenge felt invigorating and extremely exciting. For two and a half months I&amp;rsquo;ve trained hard and got to the finish line. Sadly, in the race I broke my left leg due to what is known as a stress fracture.
I never gave up on the challenge and that single episode motivated me to make sports an important part of everyday life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first ever bike race</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/20/my-first-ever-bike-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 17:28:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/06/20/my-first-ever-bike-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/im703.jpg&#34; class=&#34;noborder&#34; width=&#34;740&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;On June 11th I have entered and completed my first bike race! About 4 months ago, as I climbed off my bike after a training session, a surge of endorphins pushed me to call Ilya to sign-up for a team race. The race consisted of 1km swim, 90km bike and 21km run. I have regretted the decision shortly thereafter but it was already too late to bail out&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fail</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/04/fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 21:12:09 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/05/04/fail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We humans are first to share our greatest achievements and &amp;ldquo;ups&amp;rdquo; in life but rarely do we like to admit failures, especially when it&amp;rsquo;s related to our most cherished values and strivings. Well, I&amp;rsquo;m human and I fail. More often lately than ever before. My most recent failure is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/02/03/madrid-marathon-2017/&#34;&gt;Madrid marathon 2017 which I was looking forward to&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/anna_dance.gif&#34; class=&#34;noborder&#34; /&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/&#34;&gt;After breaking a bone during my first &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; marathon in Lausanne in 2015&lt;/a&gt; I had to take a long break from training runs. Fractures take patience. Despite my best efforts and a reworked training plan I experienced an injury about 4 weeks before the marathon date, right after finishing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strava.com/activities/915541780&#34;&gt;a nice 19Km run along the lake&lt;/a&gt;. I hoped for recovery but refrained from making the injury worse. Well, it didn&amp;rsquo;t heal completely so I took a decision to withdraw from participation. That didn&amp;rsquo;t preclude me and my DW from seeing Madrid&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Madrid Marathon 2017</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/02/03/madrid-marathon-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2017/02/03/madrid-marathon-2017/</guid>
      <description>To complete a full Iron Man is still an important milestone for me. I really dig endurance challenges. However, I reluctantly decided to reduce the number of hours of training per week and let the ultimate deadline slip a year or two into the future. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend 15 hours per week of training on it yet. There are ongoing projects that I am not willing to sacrifice. In a way I&amp;rsquo;m adapting to the opportunities that currently present themselves instead of forcefully pushing a preconceived plan against the reality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Triathlon progress update</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/06/23/triathlon-progress-update/</guid>
      <description>I enjoy training for triathlon immensely. The sport attracts me with multidimensionality and the numerous skills involved. There is so much room for growth. It&amp;rsquo;s an art really. I will regularly share some of my observations as I progress towards my next triathlon goal - completing a half Ironman.
Cycling After raving about Zwift and following its 4 month training program I chose to continue my training using TrainerRoad software instead.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indoor cycling lab</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/05/28/indoor-cycling-lab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Around Christmas in 2015 I received doctor&amp;rsquo;s diagnosis that my left tibia bone is fractured and that I can&amp;rsquo;t run for the foreseeable future. Of course, I tried against all reason but the persisting pain made me realize it&amp;rsquo;s in my own best interest to let it heal peacefully and not break it completely. Luckily, I discovered that cycling and swimming don&amp;rsquo;t hurt at all. I suppose that&amp;rsquo;s because the load spread is altered and tibia is not as stressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27306868565&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7345/27306868565_5c29150c79_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bike fitting basics for triathlon and road cycling</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/19/bike-fitting-basics-for-triathlon/</guid>
      <description>As a complete triathlon newbie I benefit tremendously from the experience and knowledge of others. Just a few little steps save years, if not decades, of trial-and-error, not to mention decrease chances of injuries and increase enjoyment of the sport. My friend Ilya Nedbailo who has successfully completed his first 70.3 Ironman in Rapperswil this year generously shared a couple of tips.
The first of which is getting a professional bike fitting service.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A long new journey ahead</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/12/14/a-long-new-journey-ahead/</guid>
      <description>Training for a half-marathon and then successfully finishing one (although not without an injury) hooked me on pursuing further challenges. I haven&amp;rsquo;t run a half-marathon as a way to prove anything. Rather the competition had given me an opportunity to reassure myself that I&amp;rsquo;m capable of carrying out longer undertakings. Ten weeks from zero to finish has been a fantastic learning experience so I am looking forward to the next step which is not only longer but also more challenging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goals</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/10/31/goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;I FUCKING DID IT&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; keeps resonating in my head as I am crossing the finish line. I can already feel latent excruciating pain (amplified by an adrenaline-fueled last half-mile sprint) slowly setting in. Few minutes later I won&amp;rsquo;t be able to walk but at this glorious energizing moment I feel that my whole life is coming together.*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s how successfully finishing a half-marathon felt to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22025248504&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5699/22025248504_84a4c75689.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>