<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bicycle on Sergey Pisarenko</title>
    <link>http://pisarenko.net/tags/bicycle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bicycle on Sergey Pisarenko</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://pisarenko.net/tags/bicycle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cube Cross Disc Mk3</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2016/07/19/cube-cross-disc-mk3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have purchased the Cube Cross Disc bicycle second-hand back in 2014 as an ultimate do-it-all machine to replace somewhat petite &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/&#34;&gt;BMC hybrid bike&lt;/a&gt; I had started cycling on. No other bike in my stable went through as many alterations as the venerable Cube, transitioning from an object of admiration to almost scrap and most recently getting resurrected to fulfill a pragmatic new purpose. It was the bike I rode during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/&#34;&gt;legendary Rhine tour&lt;/a&gt;. Perhaps it is also the bike I&amp;rsquo;ve learned most of the bike mechanic skills on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/27799786284&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8682/27799786284_5b8f05055e_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The wonderful way of carabike</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/11/05/the-wonderful-way-of-carabike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In September, following a &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/&#34;&gt;Fargo rebuild&lt;/a&gt; with s Rohloff Speedhub I have went to ride it in Italy. This time, though, I haven&amp;rsquo;t ridden my bike from A to B. Instead, I cheated and went my wife on a car. The revelation that had followed I have succinctly nicknamed &amp;ldquo;car-a-bike&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/22802670766&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5719/22802670766_f754cb289e.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salsa Fargo Mk3 - now with Rohloff!</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/09/03/salsa-fargo-rohloff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with a Salsa Fargo bicycle exactly one year ago. The bike made me newly excited about cycling. No wonder I&amp;rsquo;ve put more than 4000 kilometers on it. I never rode the bike stock and rebuilt it with custom parts as soon as I received it by post (frames were out of stock in July last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/21125844901&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/587/21125844901_1e84167b89_c.jpg&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the tour around France I decided to change a few things on the bike to better suit the kind of riding that I do:
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trip report from bicycle tour across France</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/08/07/trip-report-from-bicycle-tour-across-france/</guid>
      <description>Riding vs buying I am amused with the nontrivial amount of invented needs by the bicycle industry as well as the strength of its marketing departments. Each year brings new wheel/tire size standards, new drive-train groupsets and mass-produced lifestyles and attitudes. Suddenly, many enthusiasts desperately realize their need for full-suspension fat bikes with a certain kind of axles for &amp;ldquo;backpacking&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;adventure&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;expeditions&amp;rdquo;. I don&amp;rsquo;t see how bicycle gear obsession is any different from the common consumerism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Across France on a bicycle</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/07/25/across-france-on-a-bicycle/</guid>
      <description>Following numerous episodes of soul searching I finally came to realize that enjoy cycling more than an average person. While I enjoy many flavors of it, such as road cycling and mountain down-hill riding my absolute favorites are endurance and touring rides.
My dream is to visit as many places on a bicycle as I could. Somehow biking[1] feels to me just the right way to explore the world. Last year I joined my very first cycling tour along the river Rhine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Longest non-stop bicycle ride in my life</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/26/longest-non-stop-bicycle-ride-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After gruesome 27+ hours of cycling I feel elated to announce that I have successfully completed the challenge! I have cycled non-stop for 420.8 kilometers, climbing 4953 metres worth of hills and obstacles along the way. The ride has been the greatest physical challenge I&amp;rsquo;ve done in my life. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/05/24/longest-non-stop-hike-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;The longest non-stop hike goes to 2nd place now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/400km_ride.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/400km_ride.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Across Switzerland in one day</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/23/across-the-switzerland-in-one-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/23/across-the-switzerland-in-one-day/</guid>
      <description>UPDATE: Success! I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to complete the ride, totaling 420.8 km and 4953m of vertical ascent in 27 hours of biking.
Last year I&amp;rsquo;ve successfully completed a 300km bicycle day ride and earned a new personal record for distance. On a wonderful day of today I&amp;rsquo;m going to set a new personal record and ride for 400-or-so kilometers across Switzerland in less than 24 hours.
My route follows a slightly shortened version of the official Swiss route number 9:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twenty first CENTURY ride</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/11/twenty-first-century-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a hot Sunday I have joined a couple of cycling enthusiasts to cover an imperial century in the vicinity of canton Zurich:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/century-ride.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/century-ride.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zug to Ziegelbrucke ride</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/04/zug-to-ziegelbrucke-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/06/04/zug-to-ziegelbrucke-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a Saturday two weeks ago I went on a bike ride from Zug to Ziegelbrucke through Einsideln and Pfaffikon. I was pretty familiar with many parts of the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/zug-ziegelbrucke.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/zug-ziegelbrucke.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Centovalli bike ride</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/22/centovalli-bike-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/22/centovalli-bike-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever since I rode with my friend John around Swiss-Italian lakes 2 weeks ago I wanted to return and do a loop that goes into Italian valley Centovalli. We had omitted it from our tour because topographical maps were suggesting that there&amp;rsquo;s 2200m of climbing involved and that was outside of our &amp;ldquo;daily budget&amp;rdquo;. However, so much ascent seemed excessive for an altitude difference of 600m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/centovalli-loop.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/centovalli-loop.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday me and my friends Riccardo and Codrin came back to bust this myth once and for all. Turns out that a loop that goes into the valley from Locarno involves just 800-900m of climbing! Since that was too easy for us I added a small surprise at the final half of the route bringing total ascent to respectable 1561m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Credit card tour of Italian/Swiss lakes</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/05/credit-card-tour-of-italian-slash-swiss-lakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2015/04/05/credit-card-tour-of-italian-slash-swiss-lakes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I commute daily all year round my cycling season never stops. Longer rides, however, mostly don&amp;rsquo;t happen in winter. To open 2015 biking season I went with my friend John on a 2-day cycling tour during the Easter holiday. Because the weather forecast was predicting windy and rainy conditions in most of the Switzerland we decided to go south and ride along several lakes in Italy and Ticino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/italylakemap.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/images/italylakemap.png&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from a 10 day bicycle tour, part 2</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/15/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;continued from part 1.
12. Nutrition and hydration Regular nutrition is key to riding sustainably for many kilometers. In the morning or the previous evening you should stock up on dried fruit, bananas, bars and other snacks. I can ride for many hours if I eat something small every hour or so.
Big meals are great but they are time consuming. There&amp;rsquo;s also a fat chance of overeating. I recommend planning for dinner and nothing else.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from a 10 day bicycle tour, part 1</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/12/03/what-i-learned-from-a-10-day-bicycle-tour/</guid>
      <description>2014 is a pivotal year in my cycling &amp;ldquo;career&amp;rdquo;. I went on my first multi-day tour. I went on my first multi-week tour. I&amp;rsquo;ve set a personal distance record. And I&amp;rsquo;ve set a personal vertical ascent record. Admittedly, I did not do the best job documenting and sharing. But I digress.
On the 1st of May 2014 me and a 4 friends from work embarked on a biking trip from Andermatt, Switzerland, to Rotterdam, Netherlands, along the river Rhine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 3</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/26/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/05/26/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the part 3 of cyclocross bicycle build series. &lt;a href=&#34;http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/&#34;&gt;Jump to part 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly mentioned in one of the previous posts that I am building this bike specifically for touring around Switzerland and Europe. Together with a couple of colleagues we went on a bike tour from Andermatt, Switzerland to Rotterdam, Netherlands along the Rhine river. I&amp;rsquo;ll be covering the tour separately in a series of posts. In this post, however, I would like to share lessons learned from the building process and the bike itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/tentaclephotos/14089596650/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2901/14089596650_1cb8553bdd.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; /&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 2</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/13/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-2/</guid>
      <description>This is the part 2 of cyclocross bicycle build series. Jump to part 1.
Disassembly preparation With the bicycle, materials, tools and parts figured out I was ready to begin the disassembly process. Taking things apart is fun and bicycles are not exception to this rule. As a guide I reversed the bike assembly order from Parking Tool website. The process starts with the chain removal and continue along the drive train until the levers and controls are taken off.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cyclo-cross bicycle build - part 1</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/04/03/cyclo-cross-bicycle-build-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Prologue There is a trend I noticed myself going through. First, I tend to acquire lots of equipment and accessories for a hobby or an activity. Then I realize what my true needs are. At some point I get overwhelmed with the gear I don&amp;rsquo;t use regularly and feel wasteful. Finally, I minimize possessions by trading them to fewer precious alternatives. I went through this process with PCs and servers, laptops, digital cameras, motorcycles and now I&amp;rsquo;m going through the same with bicycles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 months on a bike</title>
      <link>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://pisarenko.net/blog/2014/01/02/6-months-on-a-bike/</guid>
      <description>I like bicycles. I like riding them, I like fiddling with them. But for some reason I never consistently commuted by bicycle. 6 months ago I made a decision to commute by bicycle every single day regardless of the weather. Even if it rains or storms or snows.
As it turns out adverse weather conditions are conquerable with appropriate gear. I am lucky that I have an opportunity to change clothes and take a shower upon my arrival at work.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>